<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.ftc.gov/">
  <channel>
    <title>Business Blog Posts</title>
    <link>https://www.ftc.gov/</link>
    <description/>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.ftc.gov/feeds/blog-business.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    <item>
  <title>Hey Nineteen: Nine FTC developments that could impact your business in 2019</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2019/01/hey-nineteen-nine-ftc-developments-could-impact-your-business-2019</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;Hey Nineteen: Nine FTC developments that could impact your business in 2019&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/96"&gt;lfair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2019-01-28T14:40:29-05:00" title="Monday, January 28, 2019 | 2:40PM"&gt;January 28, 2019 | 2:40PM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2019/01/hey-nineteen-nine-ftc-developments-could-impact-your-business-2019" hreflang="en"&gt;Hey Nineteen: Nine FTC developments that could impact your business in 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Lesley Fair&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Steely Dan may be one of the best duos of the rock era. (Sorry, Donnie and Marie fans.) Their song “Hey Nineteen” reminds us to mention some FTC consumer protection developments that could be of interest to your company or clients in 2019. As “Any Major Dude Will Tell You,” when you’re “Reelin’ in the Years” – or at least recapping the past one – consider this non-exhaustive and in-no-particular-order case compilation. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Health claims.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; In 2019, you can count on the FTC to continue to challenge unsubstantiated health claims. The agency’s recent efforts have spanned the demographic spectrum from products raising safety concerns for kids to so-called treatments for serious illnesses affecting older consumers. Cases against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/10/stemming-unproven-stem-cell-therapy-claims" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Regenerative Medical Group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/01/ftc-challenges-claims-products-could-treat-side-effects" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Cellmark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/09/guy-walks-bar-punchline-isnt-what-you-think" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;iV Bars&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/12/endorsement-enforcement-deceptive-diabetes-claims-challenged" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Nobetes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; challenged unproven representations for products promising to treat Parkinson’s disease, macular degeneration, cancer, multiple sclerosis, and diabetes. Other actions addressed deceptive claims aimed at Boomer Consumers – for example, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/02/younger-games-ftc-challenges-anti-aging-claims" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Telomerase&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s anti-aging promises and representations that &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/05/listen-ftc-challenges-hearing-claims-msa-30x-device" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;MSA 30X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was “independently tested to help you hear up to 30 times better.” A &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/02/ad-agency-pay-2-million-role-deceptive-weight-loss-free" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;$2 million settlement with ad agency Marketing Architects&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; reminded advertising professionals of the weighty consequences of false diet claims. And joint warning letters from the FTC and FDA targeted &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/01/ftc-fda-warn-sellers-questionable-opioid-treatment-products" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;unproven representations for treating opioid addiction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the sale of nicotine-laced liquids for e-cigarettes in &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/05/ftc-fda-warning-letters-ask-it-kids-treat-or-tobacco-product" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;packaging that mimicked kids’ candy and treats&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Made in USA. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;When evaluating competing products, many consumers consider country-of-origin information in deciding what goes in the basket and what stays on the shelf. FTC actions against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/03/mattress-sellers-stick-buyers-misleading-usa-claim-0" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;mattress seller Nectar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/03/mattress-sellers-stick-buyers-misleading-usa-claim-0" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;backpack purveyor Sandpiper of California&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/09/ftc-puck-seller-backpack-company-face-made-usa-claims" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Patriot Puck&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – which touted its hockey disks as “100% American Made!” – allege the companies made Made in USA claims for products actually made in other countries. The FTC said &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/01/making-made-usa-claims-hang-your-hat-accuracy" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Bollman Hat Company&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; made similar statements about its headgear despite the fact that more than 70% of its styles were wholly imported as finished products. But Bollman took the additional step of setting up a subsidiary to market its “American Made Matters” seal to other companies. The FTC alleged the seal falsely conveyed that an independent organization had objectively evaluated the products for compliance.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Automobiles. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;The daily cost of getting from here to there remains a major line item on consumers’ budgets, which is why the FTC pays close attention to allegations of deception in how cars are marketed. A settlement with Los Angeles-based Sage Auto Group for misleading yo-yo financing and add-on charges resulted in more than &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2018/12/ftc-returns-more-35-million-consumers-subjected-deceptive-unfair" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;$3.5 million back for consumers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In a pending action against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/08/ftc-alleges-car-dealers-falsified-consumers-income-financing" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Tate’s Auto Group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the FTC alleges the company falsified consumers’ income on financial forms and made deceptive financing claims in ads. You may recall the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/10/car-dealer-marketing-firm-called-out-bogus-recall-notices" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;FTC’s action against Passport Auto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for sending out fake “urgent recall” notices to lure consumers into the showroom. The FTC also sued the marketing firm that worked with Passport on the promotion. For used car dealers, January 28, 2018, marked the date they needed to display &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/07/ftc-goes-used-car-shopping-test-drives-2300-vehicles" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;the revised Buyers Guide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in vehicle windows.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Fintech.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; Developments in financial technology have the potential to help consumers get a better deal when borrowing, but only if companies honor established consumer protection principles. &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/04/ftc-challenges-lending-clubs-no-hidden-fees-claims" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The FTC’s pending action against Lending Club&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; alleges the company advertised loans with “no hidden fees,” but then charged consumers additional amounts that weren’t clearly disclosed. In a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/10/law-averages-ftc-challenges-sofis-student-loan-refinancing" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;proposed settlement with SoFi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the FTC says the online student loan refinancer deceptively used inflated numbers when advertising how much money borrowers have saved or would save by refinancing with the company. Among other counts, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/02/venmo-settlement-addresses-availability-funds-privacy" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;an action against Venmo&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; alleged that the peer-to-peer payment service now owned by PayPal failed to disclose material information about the availability of consumers’ funds. But companies and consumers aren’t the only ones to flock to new financial technologies. Fraudsters often try to sneak in the side door, which is why the FTC hosted a national workshop, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events-calendar/2018/06/decrypting-cryptocurrency-scams" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Decrypting Cryptocurrency Scams&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, to discuss what can be done to empower and protect consumers from questionable cryptocurrency promotions.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Social media marketing and customer reviews. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;The use of influencers, native advertising, and consumer reviews remain hot enforcement topics. For example, the FTC alleged &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/11/planning-social-media-marketing-campaign-read-first" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;public relations firm Creaxion Corporation and sports magazine publisher Inside Publications&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; promoted a brand of insect repellent using endorsements by Olympic gymnasts and “advertorials.” But according to the complaint, the material connection between the athletes and the manufacturer wasn’t clearly disclosed. If 2017 was the Year of the Selfie Seal – certifications that falsely appear to come from independent groups – 2018 may go down as the Year of the Selfie Star. In the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/11/planning-social-media-marketing-campaign-read-first" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Creaxion-Inside Publishing settlement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and an unrelated action against the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/05/word-about-substantiation-mosquito-season-approaches-bit" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;marketer of the insect repellent Aromaflage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the FTC alleged that company insiders, their family, or friends gave the products five-star reviews on major retail sites without disclosing their connections to the company. While we’re talking about consumer reviews, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2018/09/court-rules-ftcs-favor-case-against-weight-loss-supplement" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;a federal judge ruled that Roca Labs’ use of gag clauses&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in an effort to stop consumers from talking about their products was an unfair practice under the FTC Act. And &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/08/first-consumer-review-fairness-case-takes-promoters-big" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;the FTC brought its first case&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; under the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/guidance/consumer-review-fairness-act-what-businesses-need-know" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Consumer Review Fairness Act&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Data security and privacy. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; One notable observation about 2018 is the number of cases raising both privacy and data security concerns. For example, the complaint against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/01/vtech-settlement-cautions-companies-keep-coppa-covered-data" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;connected toymaker VTech&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; alleged the company failed to provide direct notice of its policies to parents – a typical count under the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Rule&amp;nbsp; – but also charged a violation of &lt;a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=bc9f40467d74a97874ce4ba2cb1e7147&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=se16.1.312_18&amp;amp;rgn=div8" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Section 312.8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the Rule, which requires COPPA-covered companies to “establish and maintain reasonable procedures to protect the confidentiality, security, and integrity of personal information collected from children.” (&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/01/vtech-settlement-cautions-companies-keep-coppa-covered-data" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Read the blog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for details about how a hacker stole personal information about kids and parents who used the company’s products.) &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/04/lesson-blu-make-right-privacy-security-calls-when-working" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;The complaint against smartphone maker BLU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; challenged the company’s privacy and security promises, especially as they related to the undisclosed transfer of customers’ personal information to a third-party service provider in China. Announced last year, the FTC’s proposed settlement with Uber initially addressed both privacy and security issues. But it turns out that in the middle of that investigation, Uber experienced another data breach that it didn’t disclose to the FTC until much later. The FTC nixed that settlement and entered into an expanded order with the company. In other developments, the FTC announced a total of five settlements alleging that companies made misrepresentations about their participation in the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/privacy-and-security/privacy-shield"&gt;&lt;span&gt;EU-U.S. Privacy Shield&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Then there’s the granddaddy of all data security and consumer privacy statutes, the Fair Credit Reporting Act, which the FTC has been enforcing for almost 50 years. The latest action – &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/10/3-million-fcra-settlement-puts-tenant-background-screening" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;a $3 million settlement with tenant screening company RealPage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – alleged the company’s failure to follow reasonable procedures to assure maximum possible accuracy caused big problems for consumers unfortunate enough to have names or birthdates similar to people with criminal records. Other developments that will impact business in 2019: &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/09/new-freeze-law-effect-september-21st-your-business-ready" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;a new credit freeze law&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that gives consumers the right to freeze and unfreeze their credit for free, &lt;a href="http://ftc.gov/cybersecurity" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;a suite of cybersecurity resources&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; designed especially for small businesses, and the announcement of the next &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events-calendar/privacycon-2019" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;PrivacyCon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on June 27, 2019.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;ROSCA.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt; We had hoped 2018 would be the year the internet was free of deceptive “free trial” offers that violate the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/statutes/restore-online-shoppers-confidence-act" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Restore Online Shoppers’ Confidence Act&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but it wasn’t to be. A district court order imposing a $5.2 million judgment in the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/07/district-court-rules-redress-rosca-disclosures" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Credit Bureau Center&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; case delves into ROSCA’s requirement that online sellers of products with a negative option feature must clearly and conspicuously disclose the material terms of the transaction up front and must obtain the consumer’s “express informed consent” to the charges. And lawsuits against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/07/time-rosca-recap-ftc-says-risk-free-trial-was-risky-not-free" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Triangle Media Corporation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/11/complaint-alleges-unauthorized-charges-credit-card" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Apex Capital Group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are pending against marketers alleged to have violated (among other things) ROSCA and the FTC Act.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Practices targeting small businesses and entrepreneurs. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;2018 saw an uptick in FTC lawsuit to protect small businesses and prospective business owners from deceptive practices. &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/06/operation-main-street-targets-scams-against-small-business" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Operation Main Street&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was a coordinated initiative involving 24 civil and criminal actions against pitch people who targeted small entities with office supply scams, bogus dunning notices, and other shady B2B schemes. According to the FTC’s ongoing action against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/05/ftc-challenges-robocallers-false-threat-small-businesses" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Point Break Media&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, the defendants – who falsely claim to be affiliated with Google – contact small businesses, threaten then with removal from Google search results, and then falsely promise they can help the company become one of the top Google results – for a hefty fee, of course. 2018 also saw cases against companies that deceptively pitch business opportunities or other money-making ventures. The FTC says &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/10/listen-how-sellers-pitched-business-coaching-services" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Vision Solutions Marketing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; used misleading claims to sell their business “coaching” services and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2018/06/operators-get-rich-amazon-scheme-settle-ftc" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Amazing Wealth Systems’&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; “system” was based on deceptive representatives about making mammoth money by selling products on Amazon. &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2018/12/defendants-sellers-playbook-get-rich-scheme-settle-ftc-minnesota" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Sellers Playbook&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, another “big bucks on Amazon” outfit, settled charges brought by the FTC and Minnesota AG. The order includes lifetime bans to prevent the defendants from using similar tactics in the future. An ongoing action against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/06/ftc-alleges-mobe-tells-whale-tale-misleading-money-making" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;MOBE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; also challenges pie-in-the-sky promises about making big money by working from home. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Financial injury. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;Here’s a prediction for 2019: The FTC will continue to bring cases that challenge financial deception in its myriad forms. The breadth of actions brought in 2018 illustrates that point. For example, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/11/telegram-moneygram-stop-fraud-pay-again" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;MoneyGram agreed to pay $125 million&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to settle charges it failed to take steps required by an FTC order to crack down on fraudulent transfers. The FTC, AGs from all 50 states, the District of Columbia, American Samoa, Guam, and Puerto Rico, and 16 additional state agencies that oversee charities joined forces to announce &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/07/operation-donate-honor-law-enforcers-unite-challenge" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Operation Donate with Honor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a coordinated effort targeting deceptive fundraising for military and veterans causes. &lt;span&gt;And 1.1 million consumers who did business with online payday lender AMG received checks totaling more than $505 million. In addition, t&lt;/span&gt;he fight against illegal robocalls continues on all fronts, including an action brought with the Florida Attorney General against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2018/12/ftc-state-florida-win-summary-judgment-court-orders-ringleader" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;debt relief ringleader Kevin W. Guice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. That case resulted in a $23 million judgment and a lifetime ban from telemarketing. We also filed suit against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/06/ftc-goes-court-unravel-robocalling-net" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;James Christiano and NetDotSolutions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, defendants charged with facilitating billions of illegal calls. Misleading lead generation practices continue to be a focus, including a case against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/09/camouflaged-commerce-what-was-going-armycom" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Sunkey Publishing and others&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that mimicked the look of military recruiting sites – including using URLs like army.com, air-force.com, and navyenlist.com – to generate sales leads for post-secondary schools. And FTC cases like &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/09/phantom-debt-collectors-jump-banned-wagon" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Advance Mediation Group&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and ongoing actions against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/06/sounding-phantom-debt-collection-alarm-again" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Hylan Asset Management&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2018/11/ftc-new-york-attorney-general-sue-operators-debt-collection" target="_BLANK"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Campbell Capital&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; – both brought with the New York Attorney General – illustrate efforts to enforce the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;There’s more, of course, including a unanimous opinion in &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/122-3253/att-mobility-llc-mobile-data-service"&gt;&lt;span&gt;FTC v. AT&amp;amp;T Mobility LLC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, ruling in the FTC’s favor on a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2018/02/en-banc-court-appeals-rules-ftcs-favor-common-carrier-issue"&gt;&lt;span&gt;key issue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; involving the agency’s jurisdiction, and the ongoing &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/policy/hearings-competition-consumer-protection"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Hearings on Competition and Consumer Protection in the 21st Century&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://public.govdelivery.com/accounts/USFTCBUSINESS/subscriber/new?topic_id=USFTCBUSINESS_1"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Subscribe to the Business Blog&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for insights into developments in 2019.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 19:40:29 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>lfair</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54364 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>The Avant settlement: New financial platforms, established consumer protections</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2019/04/avant-settlement-new-financial-platforms-established-consumer-protections</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;The Avant settlement: New financial platforms, established consumer protections&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/96"&gt;lfair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2019-04-15T14:53:20-04:00" title="Monday, April 15, 2019 | 2:53PM"&gt;April 15, 2019 | 2:53PM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2019/04/avant-settlement-new-financial-platforms-established-consumer-protections" hreflang="en"&gt;The Avant settlement: New financial platforms, established consumer protections&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Lesley Fair&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;“There is nothing new under the sun.” It’s from the Book of Ecclesiastes and who are we to disagree? So even when innovative products enter the market – for example, new platforms offering financial services – fundamental consumer protection principles remain constant. And as the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2019/04/online-lending-company-agrees-settle-ftc-charges-it-engaged"&gt;FTC’s $3.85 million settlement with Avant, LLC&lt;/a&gt;, demonstrates, that includes representations and practices related to online lending.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Offering &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;unsecured installment loans to consumers, Avant handles&lt;span&gt; marketing &lt;/span&gt;to servicing to the collection of payments. The FTC’s complaint alleges that Avant engaged in deceptive and unfair practices at a number of critical stages of the process. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;You’ll want to read the seven-count &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/162-3090/avant-llc"&gt;complaint&lt;/a&gt; to get the full picture, but here are some of the practices challenged as illegal. One FTC concern was Avant’s insistence on illegal methods of payment that violated regulations that ensure borrowers have the right to control which bills they pay and when. As a condition of getting credit, Avant required consumers to agree to pay by automatic payments from their bank accounts – either remotely created checks or preauthorized electronic fund transfers. However, some of Avant’s dealings with consumers are covered by the Telemarketing Sales Rule, which expressly bans the use of remotely created checks. And Avant’s insistence on preauthorized electronic fund transfers as the only alternative to illegal remotely created checks violated the Electronic Fund Transfer Act, which prohibits the conditioning of credit on that payment method. These protections are critically important for consumers and preserve their ability to prioritize which bills to pay each month. By requiring consumers to agree to repay their loans by recurring debits to their bank account each month, Avant illegally deprived consumers of control over which bills to pay and when.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Avant also told people that after they completed their loan application, they could change their payment method to “any other reasonable form of payment, including but not limited to paper check, money order, debit card or credit card” and even listed on its website the credit and debit cards it accepted. But when consumers tried to pay by credit or debit card, in many instances, Avant refused. Consumers who had relied on Avant’s representation and planned to pay off their loans early with a credit card were instead stuck with their Avant loans, resulting in additional interest.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The FTC says even people who paid by check or money order ran into problems with Avant. According to the complaint, in some cases, the company waited days – or even weeks – to deposit consumers’ checks and credit them to their account. The upshot: Avant charged consumers late fees and interest they didn’t owe. The lawsuit alleges that, even after the company received complaints from consumers about mishandled checks, Avant failed to implement routine mail handling controls like date-stamping payment envelopes when they were received.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The company also claimed that people could pay their loans off early without penalty, but some consumers reported receiving the run-around. Because Avant charges daily simple interest on its loans, it’s not easy for consumers to calculate down to the penny the amount of their final payout because it will depend on the exact date they make the payment. So consumers called Avant or contacted them by email or through Avant’s online tool for their calculated payoff amount. But even when consumers got an email or verbal confirmation from Avant that their loan was paid off, the company came back for more – sometimes months later – claiming the payoff quote was erroneous. The FTC says Avant dinged consumers for extra fees and interest and even reported to credit bureaus that loans were delinquent after consumers paid the quoted payoff amount. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The lawsuit also alleges that Avant charged consumers’ credit cards or took payments from their bank accounts without permission or in amounts larger than authorized. Sometimes Avant charged duplicate payments. One unfortunate consumer’s monthly payment was debited from his account eleven times in a single day. Another person called Avant’s customer service number trying to reduce his monthly payment only to be charged his entire balance. In other instances, Avant took consumers’ payoff balance twice. One consumer was stuck with overdraft fees and angry creditors when Avant withdrew his monthly payment three times in one day. According to the lawsuit, despite hundreds of consumer complaints about unauthorized charges and internal documents acknowledging there was a problem, Avant continued to charge people without authorization.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/162-3090/avant-llc"&gt;settlement&lt;/a&gt; in the case imposes a judgment of $3.85 million, which will be returned to consumers who were harmed by Avant’s unlawful practices. The order also includes injunctive provisions to stop the kinds of deceptive and unfair conduct alleged in the complaint.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;What’s the primary takeaway for others in the industry? Online lending may be relatively new, but unauthorized payments and untruthful claims have been around way too long. It benefits consumers – and in the long run, it benefits business – if 21st century financial platforms abandon misleading 20th century practices. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 18:53:20 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>lfair</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54405 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Report tax identity theft with IdentityTheft.gov</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2018/04/report-tax-identity-theft-identitytheftgov</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;Report tax identity theft with IdentityTheft.gov&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/158"&gt;sgressin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2018-04-03T10:58:23-04:00" title="Tuesday, April 3, 2018 | 10:58AM"&gt;April 3, 2018 | 10:58AM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2018/04/report-tax-identity-theft-identitytheftgov" hreflang="en"&gt;Report tax identity theft with IdentityTheft.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Seena Gressin&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&lt;span&gt;If you’re a tax professional, business owner, or in a human resources department, the FTC and IRS can help you help clients, employees, or other people who discover they’re victims of tax-related identity theft. &lt;a href="https://identitytheft.gov/"&gt;&lt;img alt="IdentityTheft.gov website on a laptop, tablet, and smartphone." src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/idt_multidevice_2500px.jpg" style="float:right; height:167px; margin-bottom:5px; margin-top:5px; width:250px"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Tax-related identity theft happens when someone uses your stolen Social Security number (SSN) to file a tax return and claim your refund. You might find out about it when you try to e-file — only to find that someone else already has submitted a return — or when the IRS sends you a letter saying it has identified a suspicious tax return that used your SSN. That’s when you’ll need to file an &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/f14039.pdf#_blank"&gt;IRS Identity Theft Affidavit&lt;/a&gt; (IRS Form 14039), so that the IRS can begin resolving your case.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Until now, you had to complete an Affidavit from the IRS website, print it, then fax or mail it to the IRS. Now, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2018/04/ftc-irs-initiative-aims-make-it-easier-consumers-report-tax"&gt;the FTC and IRS have collaborated&lt;/a&gt; to let people report tax-related identity theft to the IRS online, using the FTC’s &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.identitytheft.gov/#_blank"&gt;IdentityTheft.gov&lt;/a&gt; website. It’s the only place you can submit your IRS Form 14039 electronically.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&lt;span&gt;What are the benefits? &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://identitytheft.gov/#_blank"&gt;IdentityTheft.gov&lt;/a&gt; will:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li class="IndexStyle"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Walk you through the process of completing the Form 14039&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="IndexStyle"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Transfer your Form 14039 to the IRS securely&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="IndexStyle"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Guide you through placing fraud alerts on your credit files, checking your credit reports, and taking other steps to stop the tax identity theft from harming your accounts, and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li class="IndexStyle"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Help you resolve any other problems the tax identity theft may have caused.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Here’s how it works: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="http://identitytheft.gov/#_blank"&gt;IdentityTheft.gov&lt;/a&gt; will first ask you questions to collect the information the IRS needs, then use your information to populate the Form 14039 and let you review it. Once you’re satisfied, you can submit the Form 14039 to the IRS through &lt;a href="http://identitytheft.gov/#_blank"&gt;IdentityTheft.gov&lt;/a&gt; and download a copy for yourself. About 30 days later, the IRS will send you a letter confirming it received the information.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&lt;span&gt;Remember, though — filing the Affidavit doesn’t eliminate the need to pay your taxes. If you couldn’t e-file your tax return, you’ll still need to mail it to the IRS and pay any taxes you owe.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class="s2" style="margin-bottom:.0001pt"&gt;&lt;span&gt;We hope you can share this information with any victims of tax-related identity theft you encounter and remind them to visit &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.identitytheft.gov/#_blank"&gt;IdentityTheft.gov&lt;/a&gt; to report the problem and get fast and effective recovery help.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2018 14:58:23 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>sgressin</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54443 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Future of the COPPA Rule: What’s on the agenda</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2019/10/future-coppa-rule-whats-agenda</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;Future of the COPPA Rule: What’s on the agenda&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/96"&gt;lfair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2019-10-01T11:46:39-04:00" title="Tuesday, October 1, 2019 | 11:46AM"&gt;October 1, 2019 | 11:46AM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2019/10/future-coppa-rule-whats-agenda" hreflang="en"&gt;Future of the COPPA Rule: What’s on the agenda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Lesley Fair&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Technology changes at the speed of light, but the touchstone of the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Act Rule remains constant. When it comes to the collection of their kids’ personal information online, parents are in charge. But how does that principle apply in technologies not originally anticipated by the &lt;a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=6d2e378a33b8aa2ba05e88cb2fbe00c7&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=pt16.1.312&amp;amp;rgn=div5"&gt;COPPA Rule&lt;/a&gt;? Whether it’s social media, the Internet of Things, or educational technology, do changes in media and the marketplace warrant updates to the Rule?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FTC staff asked &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2019/07/ftc-seeks-comments-childrens-online-privacy-protection-act-rule"&gt;that question and others&lt;/a&gt; a few months ago and the time has come to talk it over. On October 7, 2019, we’re hosting &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events-calendar/future-coppa-rule-ftc-workshop"&gt;The Future of the COPPA Rule: An FTC Workshop&lt;/a&gt; and you’ll want to check out the just-posted agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FTC Commissioner Christine Wilson will open the event with comments at 9:00 AM Eastern Time. After a presentation by Dr. Jenny Radesky, Assistant Professor of Pediatrics at the University of Michigan Medical School, Panel #1 will examine the &lt;strong&gt;State of the World in Children’s Privacy&lt;/strong&gt;. One panelist of particular note: Jo Pedder, Head of Regulatory Strategy for the United Kingdom’s Information Commissioner’s Office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next on the agenda: remarks from FTC Commissioner Noah Phillips, followed by Panel #2, which will explore the &lt;strong&gt;Scope of the COPPA Rul&lt;/strong&gt;e.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The afternoon session will begin with comments from Morgan Reed, President of ACT, The App Association. Then Panel #3 will discuss &lt;strong&gt;Definitions, Exceptions, and Misconceptions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan Mayer, Assistant Professor in Princeton University’s Department of Computer Science will speak on &lt;strong&gt;Technology Trends Since the Revised COPPA Rul&lt;/strong&gt;e. Panel #4 will consider the &lt;strong&gt;Uses and Misuses of Persistent Identifiers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Closing remarks from Maneesha Mithal, Associate Director of the FTC’s Division of Privacy &amp;amp; Identity Protection, will put the day in perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events-calendar/future-coppa-rule-ftc-workshop"&gt;The Future of the COPPA Rule&lt;/a&gt; is free and open to the public. You can attend in person at the FTC’s Constitution Center conference facility, 400 7th Street, S.W., in Washington, DC, or watch the webcast from a link on the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events-calendar/future-coppa-rule-ftc-workshop"&gt;event page&lt;/a&gt; that will go live moments before the 9:00 ET start on October 7th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested in filing a public comment on the subject? The record will remain open until October 23, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events-calendar/future-coppa-rule-ftc-workshop"&gt;&lt;img alt="FTC Future of COPPA workshop logo" src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/coppa_2019_workshop.png" style="float:left; height:116px; width:600px"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 15:46:39 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>lfair</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54480 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Pump fiction? FTC challenges claims for fuel cards</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2019/12/pump-fiction-ftc-challenges-claims-fuel-cards</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;Pump fiction? FTC challenges claims for fuel cards&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/96"&gt;lfair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2019-12-20T11:29:09-05:00" title="Friday, December 20, 2019 | 11:29AM"&gt;December 20, 2019 | 11:29AM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2019/12/pump-fiction-ftc-challenges-claims-fuel-cards" hreflang="en"&gt;Pump fiction? FTC challenges claims for fuel cards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Lesley Fair&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants to save money at the pump. And no one wants to cut fuel costs more than companies – including many small businesses – that are in the trucking industry or have company cars. &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2019/12/ftc-alleges-fuel-card-marketer-fleetcor-charged-hundreds-millions"&gt;The FTC just filed a complaint&lt;/a&gt; alleging that Georgia-based FleetCor Technologies has made misleading representations in pitching its “Fuelman” and co-branded fuel cards to businesses around the country. According to the complaint, FleetCor hasn’t lived up to its marketing promises and has charged customers unexpected fees that to date total hundreds of millions of dollars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="FlletCor ad" src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/fleetcor_ad.jpg" style="float:right; height:498px; margin:5px 15px; width:390px"&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/182-3000/fleetcor-technologies"&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt;, which names FleetCor and CEO Ronald Clarke, alleges that despite the defendants’ claim that businesses using its fuel cards would achieve specific per-gallon savings – for example, “Save 10¢ per gallon on diesel fuel with a customized fleet management solution.*” – FleetCor’s own data show that these customers have saved, on average, less than a penny per gallon even before taking into account FleetCor’s hefty unexpected fees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About those fees: The defendants have promised “[n]o set-up, transaction or annual fees,” but according to the FTC, the defendants have charged customers millions in a broad array of unexpected fees. For example, some ads said that customers could enjoy the “convenience” of filling up at tens of thousands of locations nationwide. However, when customers buy fuel at a number of national retailers, including Pilot, Texaco, Chevron, and Loves, they’re in for a surprise. First, FleetCor doesn’t honor promised discounts at those large chains. And second, FleetCor imposes a transaction fee of $2.00 or more for each fill-up at those locations. FleetCor considers those retailers to be part of its “Convenience Network,” but according to the FTC, that term really means a non-preferred or out-of-network station where FleetCor customers have to pay more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FTC says the defendants also bill customers for an array of other unexpected fees, including Account Administration Fees, Program Fees, High Credit Risk Account Fees, and Minimum Program Administration Fees. To the extent that FleetCor has mentioned some of those fees, the FTC says it’s in dense blocks of fine print in hard-to-read and hard-to-understand Terms and Conditions documents. Other fees, including fees for unwanted subscription programs, aren’t mentioned even there. In addition, the complaint alleges the defendants have charged some customers “Late Fees and Interest and Finance Charges” totaling hundreds or thousands of dollars in a single billing cycle even when a customer paid on time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of how just one of those fees works. Buried in the fine print is the fact that FleetCor charges certain customers fees if FleetCor deemed them to be “High Credit Risk Accounts.” Who has fallen within FleetCor’s definition? Customers with a lower credit score, customers who have paid late, and customers who “operate[] in the trucking or transportation industry.” You read that right. According to the FTC, the defendants pitch fuel cards to members of that industry and yet have allegedly soaked them for at least $1.7 million in High Credit Risk Account fees solely because they’re part of FleetCor’s target market. Factoring in other customers, FleetCor has allegedly taken in a total of more than $108 million in High Credit Risk Account fees alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s more, the FTC alleges that when customers complain to FleetCor and are successful in getting one fee removed, in many instances, the defendants simply have swapped it out for a different unexpected fee. You’ll want to read the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/182-3000/fleetcor-technologies"&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt; for more allegations about how the defendants’ billing practices have cost customers hundreds of millions of dollars – conduct that has led tens of thousands of people to complain to the company, government agencies, and the BBB. The FTC also cites in-house documents to illustrate the defendants’ failure to take action in response to what the defendants describe as “noise,” a derogatory term some highly-placed corporate officials have used to describe complaints and concerns voiced by FleetCor’s customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case is pending in federal court in Georgia.&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 16:29:09 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>lfair</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54518 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Chairman Simons’ statement regarding consumer protection</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2020/03/ftc-chairman-simons-statement-regarding-consumer-protection</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;FTC Chairman Simons’ statement regarding consumer protection&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/96"&gt;lfair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2020-03-26T14:37:57-04:00" title="Thursday, March 26, 2020 | 2:37PM"&gt;March 26, 2020 | 2:37PM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2020/03/ftc-chairman-simons-statement-regarding-consumer-protection" hreflang="en"&gt;FTC Chairman Simons’ statement regarding consumer protection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Lesley Fair&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s an unprecedented time. But even in the midst of monumental change, the FTC’s commitment to its consumer protection mission remains constant. &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2020/03/ftc-chairman-joe-simons-outlines-agencys-approach-safeguarding"&gt;Here’s a statement from Chairman Simons&lt;/a&gt; about the ongoing work of the Bureau of Consumer Protection:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-left:80px; margin-right:80px"&gt;“Federal Trade Commission staff in the Bureau of Consumer Protection remain hard at work protecting consumers from deceptive and unfair commercial practices. Despite the difficult circumstances, the FTC’s law enforcement, policy, and investigative work continues, and our dedicated professional staff are fully engaged in our mission to protect consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-left:80px; margin-right:80px"&gt;We are working closely with federal and state law enforcers, and with other stakeholders, including consumer advocates and the business community, and are devoting significant resources to tackling scammers and unfair and deceptive business practices. We will not tolerate businesses seeking to take advantage of consumers’ concerns and fears regarding coronavirus disease, exigent circumstances, or financial distress. Information to educate consumers about emerging coronavirus scams, and what each of us can do, is available at &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/coronavirus"&gt;ftc.gov/coronavirus&lt;/a&gt;. We encourage you to share these educational materials broadly to help protect those you love from scams. You can also help us by reporting such scams at &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/complaint"&gt;ftc.gov/complaint&lt;/a&gt;. Reporting these scams to the FTC not only informs us, but also can help to protect your family, friends, and community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="margin-left:80px; margin-right:80px"&gt;In this time of national emergency with the pandemic putting enormous strain on all sectors of commerce, we are all doing our part. We recognize enormous challenges for consumers, as well as for businesses trying to get goods and services to people across the country. Over the next few weeks, the FTC will remain flexible and reasonable in enforcing compliance requirements that may hinder the provision of important goods and services to consumers. To be clear, by being flexible and reasonable, I am not suggesting that we will tolerate companies deceiving consumers, using tactics that violate well-established consumer protections, or taking unfair advantage of these uniquely challenging times. At all times, good faith efforts undertaken to provide needed goods and services to consumers will be taken into account in making enforcement decisions. The FTC is ready to assist businesses that may seek guidance about compliance obligations on consumer protection issues during this unprecedented time. If you seek guidance for your business, please email &lt;a href="mailto:Business.covid@ftc.gov"&gt;Business.covid@ftc.gov&lt;/a&gt; and FTC staff will respond to your inquiries as quickly as possible.”&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 18:37:57 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>lfair</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54553 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>$40.2 million reminder about the importance of due diligence and monitoring </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2020/05/402-million-reminder-about-importance-due-diligence-and-monitoring</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;$40.2 million reminder about the importance of due diligence and monitoring &lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/96"&gt;lfair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2020-05-20T12:41:45-04:00" title="Wednesday, May 20, 2020 | 12:41PM"&gt;May 20, 2020 | 12:41PM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2020/05/402-million-reminder-about-importance-due-diligence-and-monitoring" hreflang="en"&gt;$40.2 million reminder about the importance of due diligence and monitoring &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Lesley Fair&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Companies that deceive consumers often don’t act alone. Pull back the curtain and you may find behind-the-scenes businesses that lend a hand. The FTC alleges that Atlanta-based First Data Merchant Services and its former vice president, Chi “Vincent” Ko, engaged in conduct that helped scammers rake in megabucks at consumers’ expense. &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2020/05/worldwide-payment-processor-payments-industry-executive-pay-402"&gt;The $40.2 million total proposed settlement&lt;/a&gt; should warn other companies of the hazards of looking the other way when fraud stares you in the face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Access to the credit card system is the lifeblood of many businesses. But banks that are members of credit card networks won’t open merchant accounts for just anyone. Various entities – including payment processors and independent sales organizations (ISOs) – serve as intermediaries between banks and merchants. Credit card networks impose anti-fraud policies on banks and other third parties. They, in turn, enter into contracts with payment processors and ISOs that mandate compliance with those rules, including due diligence and monitoring. The purpose of those multi-layered requirements is evident: to keep scammers out of the credit card ecosystem and to ensure that payment processors and others take quick action if there’s evidence they’ve wormed their way in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll want to read the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/162-3180/first-data-merchant-services-llc"&gt;complaint&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;for an in-depth look, but according to the FTC’s lawsuit, the defendants opened merchant accounts and processed payments for at least four scam operations. Three of them – &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/152-3233/thrive-learning-llc"&gt;Thrive Learning&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/132-3121-x140018/apply-knowledge-llc"&gt;Coaching Department&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/152-3155/em-systems-services-llc"&gt;E.M. Systems&lt;/a&gt; – were subjects of FTC law enforcement. A fourth operation that used stolen credit card data to bill consumers without their consent resulted in &lt;a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-sdny/pr/two-florida-men-sentenced-their-roles-multimillion-dollar-credit-card-fraud-scheme"&gt;criminal prosecutions&lt;/a&gt; by the Department of Justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FTC says that as early as 2012, defendant Ko, through his company First Pay Solutions, started approving hundreds of facially false merchant applications for the four scam operations. For example, the applications often used straw men and shell companies. In addition, they often described business activities prohibited by credit card rules. (Examples of banned categories include “debt consolidation services,” “get rich quick opportunities,” and “any merchant engaged in any form of deceptive marketing practices.”) Given that some of Ko’s sales agents had multiple criminal convictions, F ratings with the Better Business Bureau, or civil judgments for deceptive conduct, he shouldn’t have been surprised by what was going on. Indeed, other members of Ko’s staff warned him early on that some sales agents were opening merchant accounts based on phony applications. But according to the FTC, Ko violated his obligation&amp;nbsp;to monitor what was going on and to take action in light of evidence that fraud was afoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What role did First Data – one of the largest payments processors in the country – play? First Data employed Ko and First Pay Solutions as an ISO to sell its services and processed payments for the four operations mentioned in the complaint. Throughout its relationship with First Pay Solutions, First Data had what the industry calls “shadow underwriting,” which gave First Data access to information regarding First Pay Solutions merchants’ processing activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the FTC, by April 2012, First Data had already started to question the kind of accounts First Pay Solutions was opening. For the next several years, First Data and First Pay Solutions communicated about deceptive conduct and high chargeback rates, but never seemed to do much about them. How bad was the problem? Very. At one point, First Pay Solutions’ merchants accrued over 300,000 chargebacks in less than a year, totaling approximately 40% of First Data’s excessive chargeback violations for its entire wholesale merchant business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FTC says First Data continued to receive warnings and direct evidence that First Pay Solutions’ portfolio was permeated by fraud, and yet continued to allow Ko and his company to open merchant accounts with minimal oversight. Then in 2014, a Wells Fargo’s executive vice-president emailed the General Counsel of First Data’s parent corporation, asking this prescient question: “Why is First Data signing ISOs like [First Pay]? They are going to get First Data and Wells Fargo in trouble with the FTC and CFPB due to consumer deceptive practices . . . .” Toward the end of that year, Wells Fargo terminated its processing contract First Pay Solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, in December 2014, Visa banned First Pay Solutions from bringing high-risk merchants on board until a full audit could be performed. Visa also required First Data to pay $18.7 million restitution in connection with First Pay Solutions’ merchants. In April 2015, a forensic accounting firm found major failures in risk management practices, including deficient monitoring of merchant transactions and failures in due diligence by Ko and his company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on those developments, you might expect that First Data cut First Pay Solutions loose for highly questionable conduct, right? On the contrary, in May 2015, First Data acquired the company’s merchant accounts, took over its office space, and hired most of its employees. A few months later, First Data asked Wells Fargo to allow former First Pay Solutions’ employees to solicit high-risk merchants. Wells Fargo said yes, but on two conditions: that the employees weren’t “associated with or related to Vincent Ko” and that First Data could confirm that “Vincent Ko has no influence.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those caveats make a subsequent personnel decision by First Data seem particularly ironic – because in January 2017, who did First Data hire as its Vice-President of Strategic Partnerships? Vincent Ko.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/162-3180/first-data-merchant-services-llc"&gt;complaint&lt;/a&gt; offers much more detail about the FTC’s allegations. Count 1 charges that First Data and Ko violated the FTC Act by engaging in unfair payment processing practices, including opening or maintaining accounts for shell companies or others engaged in fraud, processing transactions for merchants who were defrauding consumers, failing to terminate merchants, and ignoring evidence of fraudulent activity on merchant accounts. According to Count 2, defendant Ko engaged in credit card laundering, in violation of the &lt;a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=a8bcbae3446b7832ee0b3618ac1f26fa&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=pt16.1.310&amp;amp;rgn=div5"&gt;Telemarketing Sales Rule&lt;/a&gt;. Count 3 alleges that First Data violated the TSR by assisting and facilitating credit card laundering. And Count 4 charges First Data and Ko with violating the TSR by assisting and facilitating companies who (among other things) used false or misleading statements to market debt relief services or investment opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the $40 million judgment against First Data and the $270,373 judgment against Ko, the terms of the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/162-3180/first-data-merchant-services-llc"&gt;proposed settlement&lt;/a&gt; require First Data to submit to annual audits for the next three years by an FTC-approved independent assessor. The order also bans Ko for life from processing payments for high-risk merchants.&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 16:41:45 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>lfair</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54593 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Whose life?! MyLife charged with creating misleading background reports</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2020/07/whose-life-mylife-charged-creating-misleading-background-reports</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;Whose life?! MyLife charged with creating misleading background reports&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/158"&gt;sgressin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2020-07-27T17:04:18-04:00" title="Monday, July 27, 2020 | 5:04PM"&gt;July 27, 2020 | 5:04PM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2020/07/whose-life-mylife-charged-creating-misleading-background-reports" hreflang="en"&gt;Whose life?! MyLife charged with creating misleading background reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Seena Gressin&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As adage-writers go, whoever penned, “Sticks and stones will break my bones, but words will never hurt me,” should have looked for another line of work. And, the writer should have hoped that prospective employers wouldn’t spot a promotion for MyLife.com, saying they could see the writer’s criminal and sexual offender records by subscribing to MyLife’s background reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2020/07/ftc-alleges-california-purveyor-background-reports-misled"&gt;lawsuit announced today&lt;/a&gt; alleges that MyLife.com, Inc., and its founder and CEO, Jeffrey Tinsley, enticed people to subscribe to MyLife’s background report services by posting false and misleading “teaser” background reports on MyLife’s website. The reports implied that a particular person had criminal or sex offender records that the viewer could see by subscribing to MyLife. According to the &lt;a href="https://ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/182-3022/mylifecom-inc"&gt;lawsuit&lt;/a&gt;, often, when MyLife displayed the reports, the person either had no such records or had only minor traffic citations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Department of Justice filed the lawsuit on behalf of the FTC. It charges that in addition to violating the FTC Act with misleading claims, MyLife violated consumer protections of the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/statutes/fair-credit-reporting-act"&gt;Fair Credit Reporting Act&lt;/a&gt; (FCRA), used misleading billing practices, in violation of the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/statutes/restore-online-shoppers-confidence-act"&gt;Restore Online Shoppers’ Confidence Act&lt;/a&gt; (ROSCA), and misrepresented its refund and cancellation policies, in violation of the &lt;a href="https://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=8834f81fe5c9cba39cad2af1de2c0ba9&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=pt16.1.310&amp;amp;rgn=div5"&gt;Telemarketing Sales Rule&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(TSR)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;. There’s a lot going on in this case. If you create, use, or are the subject of a background report (and that should include most adults), you’ll want to take a closer look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the lawsuit, since 2009, MyLife has promoted its background reports by letting people search for someone’s name on its website for free and get a teaser background report. When the searched-for person had no had no history of criminal, traffic, or sex offenses, the teaser report typically said the person “may have” such records. It also prominently displayed large, clickable buttons, one inviting the user to “View [searched-for person’s] Court, Arrest, or Criminal Records,” and another inviting the user to “View [searched-for person’s] Sex Offender Records.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complaint alleges that the prominent “View” buttons, together with statements that the searched-for person “may have” arrest, criminal, or sex offender records, led users to conclude that the person had such records, even if they did not. Many people reported they bought subscriptions to MyLife to see the records, the complaint says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does the FCRA come in? The law defines a “consumer report” as a “communication of any information” by a consumer reporting agency (CRA) that bears on a person’s “credit worthiness, credit standing, credit capacity, character, general reputation, personal characteristics, or mode of living” that is used (or expected to be used) as a factor in establishing their eligibility for credit, insurance, employment, or other reasons outlined in the law. The complaint alleges that MyLife is a CRA and subject to the FCRA because it assembles consumer report information, like court or arrest records, then markets and sells it to third parties to use in making decisions like whether to give someone credit, a job, or a lease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complaint alleges that MyLife skirted its obligations under the FCRA. It charges that MyLife failed to make sure the information it sold was used only for legally permissible purposes, failed to ensure the information was accurate, and failed to tell users about their obligations under the FCRA, including the requirement to notify consumers if the user took an adverse action against them based on information in the report. Inaccurate information in a consumer report can cost a consumer a job, housing, or even a loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for MyLife’s alleged violations of ROSCA, MyLife sold its subscriptions through &lt;span&gt;auto-renewing, or negative option, plans, triggering its obligations to comply with ROSCA. According to the complaint, MyLife struck out on ROSCA’s basic compliance requirements, including requirements that it clearly disclose all material terms of the deal before getting a consumer’s billing information, and that it give customers a simple mechanism for stopping the recurring charges. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The complaint charges MyLife violated the TSR by, among other things, failing to truthfully and clearly disclose the terms of its refund or cancellation policies – including that MyLife “had a policy of not making refunds and of discouraging cancellations,” according to the complaint.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case, filed in federal court in the Central District of California, is worth watching. Meanwhile, if you’re a consumer reporting agency, or you use background reports, consider whether it’s time for an FCRA refresher. Start out by visiting &lt;span&gt;our Business Center for resources on &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/privacy-and-security/credit-reporting"&gt;&lt;span&gt;complying with the FCRA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, including &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/guidance/background-checks-what-employers-need-know"&gt;Background Checks: What Employers Need to Know&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Note: This blog post was corrected on July 29, 2020, to identify the Central District of California as the court where the case was filed.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 21:04:18 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>sgressin</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54635 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Zooming in on Zoom’s unfair and deceptive security practices: More about the FTC settlement</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2020/11/zooming-zooms-unfair-and-deceptive-security-practices-more-about-ftc-settlement</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;Zooming in on Zoom’s unfair and deceptive security practices: More about the FTC settlement&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/96"&gt;lfair&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2020-11-09T10:42:45-05:00" title="Monday, November 9, 2020 | 10:42AM"&gt;November 9, 2020 | 10:42AM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2020/11/zooming-zooms-unfair-and-deceptive-security-practices-more-about-ftc-settlement" hreflang="en"&gt;Zooming in on Zoom’s unfair and deceptive security practices: More about the FTC settlement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Lesley Fair&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;This time last year, “zoom” was just a word related to speed. But the pandemic has made video conferencing platform Zoom a daily fixture for business people conferring about trade secrets, doctors and mental health professionals discussing sensitive patient information, kids keeping up with school work, and the rest of us sharing everything from the details of day-to-day life to confidential family matters. &lt;a href="https://ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2020/11/ftc-requires-zoom-enhance-its-security-practices-part-settlement"&gt;According to a just-announced FTC complaint&lt;/a&gt;, Zoom allegedly engaged in deceptive and unfair practices that misled consumers about the security of their communications on the platform and that put certain users at risk when the company undermined a security feature built into the Safari browser. A proposed settlement will require Zoom to honor its security promises and implement a comprehensive program designed to protect consumers’ information in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="FTC Zoom infographic" src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/zoom_infographic.png" style="float:right; height:197px; margin:20px 10px; width:375px"&gt;Use Zoom just a few times and you’ll understand the breadth of data the company collects: names, email addresses, approximate locations, credit card numbers, the identity of attendees, and a plethora of information collected while people use the service – including chats, messages, files, and recorded meetings stored on Zoom’s cloud storage. Obviously aware of consumers’ concerns about the security of their communications, Zoom claimed on its website and elsewhere that it takes “security seriously,” that it “places privacy and security as the highest priority,” and that it “is committed to protecting your privacy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its site, in its app, in security guides, and in direct communications with potential customers, Zoom prominently touted its “end-to-end AES 256-bit encryption” for all meetings. End-to-end encryption is a way of securing communications so that only the sender and recipients – and no one else, not even the platform provider – can read the contents. AES 256-bit encryption is such a strong level of encryption that it can be used to secure “TOP SECRET” messages. According to a 2015 Zoom blog post, “Zoom’s use of AES 256 encryption” made “it impossible for a hacker to grab anything outside of a hopelessly garbled transmission . . . . ” The company also represented to healthcare providers that “end-to-end AES 256-bit encryption of all meeting data and instant messages” made the platform suitable for the enhanced security needs of telehealth video conferencing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what the company claimed, but the FTC says Zoom delivered far less. In fact, Zoom didn’t provide end-to-end encryption for most Zoom meetings because Zoom’s servers – including some located in China – maintained the cryptographic keys that could allow Zoom to access the content of its customers’ meetings. What’s more, the FTC says the company’s claim of “256-bit encryption” was false or misleading because Zoom delivered a lower level of encryption that provided less protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For paying customers, Zoom also offered the option of storing their recorded meetings in Zoom’s secure cloud immediately after the meeting had ended. However, according to the FTC, recordings were kept on Zoom’s servers unencrypted for up to 60 days before they were transferred to Zoom’s secure cloud storage, where they were stored encrypted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FTC also alleges that for Mac users, Zoom installed software – called ZoomOpener – that raised particular privacy and security concerns. Mac owners will want to read the &lt;a href="https://ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/192-3167/zoom-video-communications-inc-matter"&gt;complaint&lt;/a&gt; for details, but here’s the summary. To help defend against malware and malicious actors, Apple had updated its Safari browser to require users to interact with a dialogue box when a website or link attempted to launch an outside app. So if a consumer received an invitation link to a Zoom meeting, they had to click that it was “okay” to open the Zoom app and join the meeting. However, to avoid this dialogue box, in July 2018, Zoom updated its app for Macs with its ZoomOpener software. The company claimed the purpose of the update was to resolve “minor bug fixes,” but the FTC says Zoom had something else in mind. In fact, Zoom’s “fix” circumvented that safeguard in Apple’s Safari browser. The upshot: Consumers could automatically be joined to Zoom meetings with their cameras also automatically activated unless the consumers had changed their Zoom default video settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, Zoom did not put in place any offsetting measures to protect users, and the FTC alleges Zoom’s behind-the-scenes ploy put Mac users at risk. For example, no-goodniks could send phishing emails that were really Zoom invitations in disguise. If consumers clicked on a link, it could open a Zoom meeting without their permission and allow strangers to spy on them through their webcams or install malware onto their computers. Even if users deleted the Zoom app, the ZoomOpener remained – along with its accompanying vulnerabilities. What’s more, Zoom could re-install the Zoom app without the user’s permission or knowledge. Apple removed the ZoomOpener web server from users’ computers in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/192-3167/zoom-video-communications-inc-matter-0"&gt;proposed administrative complaint&lt;/a&gt; alleges Zoom violated the FTC Act by making deceptive end-to-end encryption claims, false promises about the level of encryption it provided, and misleading representations regarding secured cloud storage for recorded meetings. In addition, the FTC charges that Zoom’s installation of the ZoomOpener unfairly circumvented third-party privacy and security safeguards and that Zoom deceptively failed to give consumers the full scoop about the ZoomOpener.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://ftc.gov/enforcement/cases-proceedings/192-3167/zoom-video-communications-inc-matter-0"&gt;proposed settlement&lt;/a&gt; prohibits Zoom from making a wide variety of privacy- and security-related misrepresentations. It also requires Zoom to put in place a far-reaching information security program that includes – among other things – a security review for all new software before release, a vulnerability management program, regular security training for all employees, specialized training for developers and engineers, and independent program assessments by a qualified third party within 180 days and every other year after that for the next 20 years. Once the proposed settlement is published in the Federal Register, the FTC will accept public comments for 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though Zoom has discontinued most of the practices challenged in the complaint, the most effective means for future compliance is a comprehensive security make-over assessed by a qualified third party, monitored by the FTC, and enforceable in court. The hundreds of millions of consumers who rely on Zoom every day to conduct business, get healthcare, educate their kids, and connect with family members have a right to expect the company to take steps to protect their personal information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for more information about using video conferencing platforms? Read &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/blogs/business-blog/2020/04/video-conferencing-10-privacy-tips-your-business"&gt;Video conferencing: 10 privacy tips for your business&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2020 15:42:45 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>lfair</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54680 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Screening tenants? Check out the FTC’s new guidance</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2016/11/screening-tenants-check-out-ftcs-new-guidance</link>
  <description>
&lt;span&gt;Screening tenants? Check out the FTC’s new guidance&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;span lang about="https://www.ftc.gov/user/122"&gt;lschifferle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span&gt;&lt;time datetime="2016-11-28T10:04:57-05:00" title="Monday, November 28, 2016 | 10:04AM"&gt;November 28, 2016 | 10:04AM&lt;/time&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;h3 class="node-title"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/blog/2016/11/screening-tenants-check-out-ftcs-new-guidance" hreflang="en"&gt;Screening tenants? Check out the FTC’s new guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-field-author field--type-string field--label-inline"&gt;
            &lt;div class="field__label"&gt;By&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;Lisa Weintraub Schifferle&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="field field--name-body field--type-text-with-summary field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Using background checks to screen tenants? Or maybe your company provides those background checks to landlords? Make sure you’re complying with the Fair Credit Reporting Act (FCRA). The FTC’s new guidance &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/guidance/using-consumer-reports-what-landlords-need-know"&gt;for landlords&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/guidance/what-tenant-background-screening-companies-need-know-about-fair"&gt;for tenant background screening companies&lt;/a&gt; can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do landlords need to know?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Landlords must take certain steps before getting a consumer report and after taking an adverse action based on the report. A consumer report can include a credit report, a rental history report or a criminal history report. Landlords can only get consumer reports if they have a “permissible purpose,” like tenant screening. Before you get a consumer report, you must certify to the company providing the report that you’ll use the report only for housing purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you, as a landlord, take an adverse action against a tenant or rental applicant, then you must give notice – orally, in writing or electronically. An adverse action could include denying a lease, requiring a co-signor, or requiring higher rent than for another applicant. The FTC’s guidance has more examples of when an adverse action notice is required. When you send an adverse action notice, it must include the contact information for the company who supplied the report and an explanation of the right to dispute the report.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What should tenant background screening companies keep in mind?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you don’t think of your company as a consumer reporting agency, it may be one if it provides information about people to landlords for use in housing decisions. Background screening reports provided by your company are covered by the FCRA if they’re used to help decide eligibility for housing and include information “bearing on a consumer’s creditworthiness, credit standing, credit capacity, character, general reputation, personal characteristics, or mode of living.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your tenant background screening company is covered by the FCRA, then you have four main requirements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow reasonable procedures to ensure accuracy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get certifications from your clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide your clients with information about the FCRA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honor the rights of applicants and tenants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new guidance includes details about each of these requirements, as well as a handy chart of key FCRA provisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you’re a landlord or a screening company, when you’re done using a consumer report, you must securely dispose of it. For more information, read &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/guidance/disposing-consumer-report-information-rule-tells-how"&gt;Disposing of Consumer Report Information? Rule Tells How&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Share these resources – and the FTC’s &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/consumer-protection/credit-reporting"&gt;Credit Reporting&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/tips-advice/business-center/selected-industries/human-resources"&gt;Human Resources&lt;/a&gt; portals – with others in your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 15:04:57 +0000</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>lschifferle</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">54736 at https://www.ftc.gov</guid>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
