<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.ftc.gov/">
  <channel>
    <title>Federal Trade Commission - Protecting America's Consumers</title>
    <link>https://www.ftc.gov/</link>
    <description/>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.ftc.gov/feeds/press-release-competition.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    <item>
  <title>FTC Requests Public Comment on EnCap, Verdun, XCL Petition to Modify Order</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/04/ftc-requests-public-comment-encap-verdun-xcl-petition-modify-order</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is seeking public comment on a petition to reopen and modify a 2022 final consent order involving Verdun Oil Company II LLC’s (Verdun) acquisition of EP Energy LLC (EP).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s 2022 order settled charges that the acquisition would harm competition for the sale of Uinta Basin waxy crude oil to Salt Lake City refiners. The FTC’s final consent order required the divestiture of EP’s entire business and assets in Utah. The final order also required Verdun, XCL Resources Holdings, LLC (XCL), and their parent entities, EnCap Energy Capital Fund XI, L.P. and EnCap Investments L.P. (together, EnCap), to obtain prior approval from the Commission before engaging in certain acquisition transactions across several counties in Utah.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Relevant parties to the 2022 order &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/c4760-petition_of_respondents_to_reopen_and_modify_decision_and_order_-_public.pdf"&gt;filed a petition&lt;/a&gt; with the Commission that seeks to remove this prior approval requirement covering EnCap, Verdun, and XCL from the final consent order.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the petition, there have been significant changes since the order was entered that now justify removing the prior approval requirement. These changes include EnCap’s and XCL’s exit from crude oil exploration and production in the Uinta Basin after selling those assets to an unrelated party in 2024.&amp;nbsp;Given these changes, the prior approval requirement is no longer necessary, the petition states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comments on the petition to modify the consent order must be filed by May 2, 2025 through&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.regulations.gov/document/FTC-2025-0027-0001"&gt;Regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;. Instructions for filing comments appear on the docket.&amp;nbsp;Once processed, they will be posted on Regulations.gov.&amp;nbsp;After the comment period closes, the Commission will vote on whether to approve the application.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87991</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title> FTC Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson Appoints Deputy Directors of the Bureaus of Competition and Consumer Protection</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-chairman-andrew-n-ferguson-appoints-deputy-directors-bureaus-competition-consumer-protection</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson today announced he has appointed Taylor C. Hoogendoorn as Deputy Director of the Bureau of Competition and Katherine White as Deputy Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hoogendoorn is a talented litigator with expertise in a wide range of litigation, including antitrust, tort, contractual, energy, and intellectual property matters. Hoogendoorn joins the FTC after spending time in private practice at a law firm in Houston. He clerked for the Hon. Samuel A. Alito Jr. on the Supreme Court of the United States; the Hon. Gregory G. Katsas on the United States Court of Appeals for the D.C. Circuit; and the Hon. J. Harvie Wilkinson III on the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hoogendoorn holds a J.D. from Yale Law School, where he won the Morris Tyler Moot Court of Appeals and served on the Yale Law Journal, and a B.B.A. with majors in Economics, Finance, Mathematics, and Business Fellows from Baylor University. While at Baylor, he served on the university’s Board of Regents and graduated as the top-ranked student in the Hankamer School of Business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;White is an experienced privacy and consumer protection attorney, with a career in both government service and private practice. White has deep experience in all aspects of consumer protection law and has led complex investigations relating to privacy, data security, and credit reporting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most recently, White was a partner at a law firm. Prior to joining the firm, White spent nearly 15 years at the FTC and served in a variety of roles, including as an Attorney Advisor to former Commissioner Noah Phillips during the first Trump administration, Counsel to the Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection, and as a senior attorney in the Division of Privacy and Identity Protection. In addition, White worked on detail for the Senate Commerce Committee where she provided advice on a range of consumer protection issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She is a graduate of the George Washington University Law School and the University of Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87662</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Staff Reaffirm Opposition to Proposed Indiana Hospital Merger</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-staff-reaffirm-opposition-proposed-indiana-hospital-merger</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, Federal Trade Commission staff again urged the Indiana Department of Health to deny Union Hospital, Inc. (Union Health) and Terre Haute Regional Hospital, L.P.’s (THRH) application to merge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;FTC staff said Union Health and THRH’s second attempt to merge under a proposed&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/features/certificates-public-advantage-copas" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="16cab5ca-cef6-4146-87ed-58d40cd675fc" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;certificate of public advantage&lt;/a&gt;, also known as a COPA, presents the same anticompetitive harms as their original application did, according to the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/in-copa-comment-3-17-2025-public-redacted.pdf"&gt;FTC’s comment letter&lt;/a&gt;. Union Health and THRH’s COPA application would shield the proposed merger from antitrust scrutiny. The FTC warned that the merger poses substantial anticompetitive risks such as higher healthcare costs for patients and lower wages for hospital workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“This repackaged COPA application presents the same problems as before. Competition consistently results in better outcomes for patients and workers than consolidation subject to COPAs,” said Clarke Edwards, Acting Director of the FTC’s Office of Policy Planning. “The Indiana Department of Health should deny this attempt by Vigo County’s only two hospitals to eliminate competition and avoid antitrust review.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s latest comment letter follows a similar letter issued in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/09/ftc-staff-opposes-proposed-indiana-hospital-merger" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="3c68c3ec-66c5-4f34-9281-1d7ad91ccbec" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;September 2024&lt;/a&gt; opposing the proposed COPA. Following the FTC’s opposition, Union Health and THRH withdrew their COPA application in November 2024. FTC&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/11/statement-regarding-union-healths-copa-application-withdrawal" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="99f3c688-9d1d-43ca-9d0c-85008fdd6a99" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;staff applauded&lt;/a&gt; the withdrawal as a win for patients and healthcare workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Union Health and THRH submitted a second COPA application in February 2025. The resubmitted application presents little new information and the concerns the FTC raised in 2024 remain the same, the FTC’s latest comment letter states. The deal continues to pose serious harm to competition and consumers through higher healthcare costs, lower quality, reduced innovation, reduced access to care, and depressed wages for hospital employees, according to the FTC’s comment letter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to submit the staff comment to the Indiana Department of Health was 4-0.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87632</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Challenges Medical Device Coatings Deal</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-challenges-medical-device-coatings-deal</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today sued to block GTCR BC Holdings, LLC’s (GTCR) acquisition of Surmodics, Inc. (Surmodics), alleging that the deal, which seeks to combine the two largest manufacturers of critical medical device coatings, is anticompetitive.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/d9440_part_3_complaint_public_redacted.pdf"&gt;FTC charges&lt;/a&gt; that private equity firm GTCR’s proposed acquisition of Surmodics would create a combined company controlling more than 50% of the market for outsourced hydrophilic coatings. These coatings are often used by medical device manufacturers and are applied to lifesaving medical devices such as catheters and guidewires.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Medical device makers rely on high-quality coatings in designing and bringing to market life-saving devices, such as neurovascular catheters,” said Daniel Guarnera, Director of the FTC’s Bureau of Competition. “This merger threatens to disrupt competitive dynamics that have ultimately benefited patients. Today, the FTC is stepping in to protect patients from this unlawful acquisition.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GTCR currently owns a majority stake in Biocoat, Inc., which is the second-largest provider of outsourced hydrophilic coatings. Surmodics is the largest provider of outsourced hydrophilic coatings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As the FTC’s complaint alleges, GTCR’s acquisition of Surmodics would lead to a highly concentrated market for outsourced hydrophilic coatings and eliminate significant head-to-head competition between Biocoat and Surmodics. This direct competition has spurred lower prices, higher quality coatings, and product innovation. The proposed deal would change those competitive dynamics and harm medical device manufacturers as well as patients, the complaint states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hydrophilic coatings allow physicians to maneuver medical devices within the tight confines of the body—within a blood vessel in the brain, for example—without damaging sensitive tissue or vital structures. Medical devices with hydrophilic coatings are used in a range of interventional neurovascular, structural heart, coronary, and peripheral vascular procedures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market Dynamics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;GTCR’s acquisition of Surmodics would significantly increase market concentration in the outsourced hydrophilic coatings sector, which already suffers from few competitors. The merger would result in a level of market concentration that violates the 2023 Merger Guidelines, the FTC’s complaint states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internal documents from both companies, as well as competitor and customer testimony, recognize Surmodics and Biocoat as head-to-head competitors. As alleged in the complaint, Surmodics and Biocoat closely monitor each other’s business strategy and often target the same large, small, and startup medical device manufacturers, also known as original equipment manufacturers (OEMs). This fierce competition has driven Surmodics and Biocoat to improve coating quality and services, lower prices, and increase innovation. The benefits of these competitive dynamics, however, would be eliminated by the proposed merger, the FTC’s complaint alleges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing of hydrophilic coatings requires specialized expertise, years of research, and millions of dollars in investments. Many OEMs prefer to outsource this process instead of manufacturing it in-house. Often, OEMs outsource to coatings manufacturers with a proven track record, like Biocoat and Surmodics. Given these dynamics, it is unlikely any new coating provider could emerge to meaningfully compete with GTCR and Surmodics post-merger, the FTC’s complaint alleges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to issue an administrative complaint and authorize staff to seek a temporary restraining order and a preliminary injunction was 4-0. Commissioner Rebecca Kelly Slaughter joined by Commissioner Alvaro M. Bedoya &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/statement-commissioner-rebecca-kelly-slaughter-joined-commissioner-alvaro-m-bedoya-matter-gtcr-bc" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="51d74d7d-9353-4f9c-b47c-c327127a7e7a" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The federal court complaint and request for preliminary relief will be filed in the U.S. District Court for the Northern District of Illinois to halt the transaction pending an administrative proceeding. A public version of the complaint will be available and linked to this news release as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Mergers I Division of the FTC’s Bureau of Competition led the investigation in this matter.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE&lt;/strong&gt;: The Commission issues an administrative complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the law has been or is being violated, and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest. The issuance of the administrative complaint marks the beginning of a proceeding in which the allegations will be tried in a formal hearing before an administrative law judge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87587</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Approves Final Order Requiring Building Service Contractor to Stop Enforcing a No-Hire Agreement</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-approves-final-order-requiring-building-service-contractor-stop-enforcing-no-hire-agreement</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today finalized a consent order that requires building services contractor Planned Building Services and its affiliated companies to cease their enforcement of no-hire agreements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2410029plannedcomplaint.pdf"&gt;issued a complaint&lt;/a&gt; in January 2025 against Planned Building Services, Inc., Planned Security Services, Inc., Planned Lifestyle Services, Inc., and Planned Technologies Services, Inc. which do business as Planned Companies, (Planned), alleging that the companies’ enforcement of their no-hire agreements limited workers’ ability to negotiate for higher wages, better benefits, and improved working conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the no-hire agreements, residential and commercial building owners were limited from hiring building service workers that were employed by Planned. The no-hire agreements were included in customer service agreements with building owners, according to the FTC’s complaint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2410029PlannedCompaniesOrder.pdf"&gt;final consent order&lt;/a&gt; places several restrictions and requirements on Planned, including ordering Planned to cease and desist from, directly or indirectly, enforcing a no-hire agreement or communicating to any prospective or current customer that a Planned employee is subject to a no-hire agreement. It also requires Planned to stop including no-hire agreements in their customer contracts and to notify customers and employees that their existing no-hire agreements are no longer enforceable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a public comment period, the Commission vote to approve the final order was 4-0.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87552</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Launches Joint Labor Task Force to Protect American Workers</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-launches-joint-labor-task-force-protect-american-workers</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson directed the FTC to form a Joint Labor Task Force that will work to prioritize rooting out and prosecuting deceptive, unfair, and anticompetitive labor-market practices that harm American workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pursuant to a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/public-statements/directive-regarding-labor-markets-task-force" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="97c63754-8479-4869-8b1d-c843ad055af3" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;memorandum&lt;/a&gt; issued by Chairman Ferguson, the FTC’s Bureau of Competition, Bureau of Consumer Protection, Bureau of Economics, and Office of Policy Planning are directed to work together to carry out a variety of responsibilities. The task force will focus on, for example, prioritizing investigations and prosecutions of deceptive, unfair, or anticompetitive labor market conduct and coordinating all such actions across the Bureaus, creating information-sharing protocols across the FTC’s Bureaus and offices to exchange best practices for uncovering and investigating such conduct, and promoting research regarding harmful labor market practices to inform the FTC and the public.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A healthy labor market is critical to the country’s success. But deceptive, unfair, and anticompetitive labor practices are widespread. They negatively affect workers across all types of industries by limiting their mobility and ability to earn a living. Such harmful practices come in a variety of forms. For example, the Chairman’s directive highlights no-poach, non-solicitation, or no-hire agreements, noncompete agreements, wage-fixing agreements, deceptive job advertising such as misleading earnings claims, deceptive business opportunities, misleading franchise offerings, and collusion or unlawful coordination on DEI employment metrics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chairman’s directive seeks to harmonize the FTC’s law-enforcement efforts on behalf of workers to ensure that the FTC prioritizes labor issues in both its consumer-protection and competition matters.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87551</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Federal Trade Commission Launches Inquiry on Tech Censorship</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/federal-trade-commission-launches-inquiry-tech-censorship</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, the Federal Trade Commission launched a public inquiry to better understand how technology platforms deny or degrade users’ access to services based on the content of their speech or affiliations, and how this conduct may have violated the law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Censorship by technology platforms is not just un-American, it is potentially illegal. Tech firms can employ confusing or unpredictable internal procedures that cut users off, sometimes with no ability appeal the decision. Such actions taken by tech platforms may harm consumers, affect competition, may have resulted from a lack of competition, or may have been the product of anti-competitive conduct.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC issued a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/P251203CensorshipRFI.pdf"&gt;Request for Information (RFI)&lt;/a&gt; requesting &lt;a href="https://www.regulations.gov/docket/FTC-2025-0023/document"&gt;public comment&lt;/a&gt; on how consumers may have been harmed by technology platforms that limited their ability to share ideas or affiliations freely and openly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Tech firms should not be bullying their users,” said FTC Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson. “This inquiry will help the FTC better understand how these firms may have violated the law by silencing and intimidating Americans for speaking their minds.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tech platform users who have been banned, shadow banned, demonetized, or otherwise censored are encouraged to share their comments in response to the RFI. The FTC is interested in understanding how consumers—including by potentially unfair or deceptive acts or practices, or potentially unfair methods of competition—have been harmed by the policies of tech firms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The public will have until May 21, 2025 to &lt;a href="https://www.regulations.gov/docket/FTC-2025-0023/document"&gt;submit a comment&lt;/a&gt;. Once submitted, comments will be posted to Regulations.gov. If consumers would prefer to file a private report with the FTC instead, they can go to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Freportfraud.ftc.gov%2F&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7Cjhenderson2%40ftc.gov%7Cbbcdb33a908b472e0b9b08dd51cac936%7C7302cabc5af5469baf17700007935a01%7C0%7C0%7C638756653585499846%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=fxah%2FqaiTMUWwLc0dCmr%2BYUDcrCJ%2FuL8DBCwHqRRHnk%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0"&gt;ReportFraud.ftc.gov&lt;/a&gt; and click “Report Now.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87524</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson Announces that the FTC and DOJ’s Joint 2023 Merger Guidelines Are in Effect</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-chairman-andrew-n-ferguson-announces-ftc-dojs-joint-2023-merger-guidelines-are-effect</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson announced today that the FTC and Department of Justice’s joint 2023 Merger Guidelines are in effect and will serve as the framework for the FTC’s merger-review analysis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Stability is good for the enforcement agencies.&amp;nbsp;The wholesale rescission and reworking of guidelines is time consuming and expensive,” Chairman Ferguson said.&amp;nbsp;“We should undertake this process sparingly.&amp;nbsp;We have limited resources to patrol the beat and constant turnover undermines agency credibility.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chairman Ferguson’s memo to staff on the Merger Guidelines can be found &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/chairman-ferguson-memo-re-merger-guidelines" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="7db1b16f-67b4-4f31-b069-b390617c979b" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>hbarber</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87496</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Publishes Inflation-Adjusted Civil Penalty Amounts for 2025</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-publishes-inflation-adjusted-civil-penalty-amounts-2025</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission has adjusted the maximum civil penalty dollar amounts for violations of 16 provisions of law the FTC enforces, as required by the Federal Civil Penalties Inflation Adjustment Act Improvements Act of 2015. The Act directs agencies to implement annual inflation adjustments based on a prescribed formula.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new maximum civil penalty amounts became effective once they were published in the Federal Register on January 17, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The maximum civil penalty amount has increased from $51,744 to $53,088 for violations of Sections 5(l), 5(m)(1)(A), and 5(m)(1)(B) of the FTC Act, Section 7A(g)(l) of the Clayton Act, and Section 525(b) of the Energy Policy and Conservation Act. It has increased from $680 to $698&amp;nbsp;for violations of Section 10 of the FTC Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The maximum civil penalty amount has increased from $1,472,546 to $1,510,803 for violations of Section 814(a) of the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007. The maximum civil penalty amounts for other law violations within the agency’s jurisdiction&amp;nbsp;are listed in the Federal Register notice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to publish the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2025/01/17/2025-01361/adjustments-to-civil-penalty-amounts"&gt;Federal Register notice&lt;/a&gt; amending Commission Rule 1.98 was 5-0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>mkatz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87476</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Chairman Ferguson Appoints Daniel Guarnera as Director of Bureau of Competition</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-chairman-ferguson-appoints-daniel-guarnera-director-bureau-competition</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson has appointed Daniel Guarnera as Director of the Bureau of Competition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I am thrilled Dan is joining the FTC as Director of the Bureau of Competition,” said Chairman Ferguson. “He has tremendous experience litigating antitrust cases in critical markets, including agriculture and Big Tech. Few lawyers in America have as much experience taking on Big Tech as Dan. He also has experience using the antitrust laws to promote competition in labor and healthcare markets—two of my top priorities. Under Dan’s leadership, the Bureau of Competition will do its part to fulfill President Trump’s promise to lower the cost of living for all Americans, to promote innovation, and to protect the interests of American workers.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guarnera joins the Commission from the U.S. Department of Justice Antitrust Division, where he served as chief of the Civil Conduct Task Force. During his tenure, the task force filed monopolization suits against Google and Apple, as well as multiple cases involving agriculture and labor markets. Prior to his role as chief, Guarnera participated in conduct and merger matters in industries such as transportation, healthcare, and technology, including&amp;nbsp;as a trial attorney and counsel to the Assistant Attorney General of the Antitrust Division during the first Trump Administration.&amp;nbsp;He previously served as special counsel to U.S. Senate Judiciary Committee Chairman Charles Grassley&amp;nbsp;during the confirmation of President Trump’s Supreme Court appointee, Justice Neil Gorsuch. He also worked in private practice and clerked for the Honorable Diane S. Sykes of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guarnera earned bachelor’s degrees in political science and French-European studies from American University and earned law and business administration degrees from the University of Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote approving Guarnera’s appointment as Director of the Bureau of Competition was 4-0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87469</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Seeks Public Comments on Enbridge Inc.’s Petition to Set Aside 2017 Order</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-seeks-public-comments-enbridge-incs-petition-set-aside-2017-order</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is seeking public comment on a petition by Enbridge Inc. requesting that the Commission reopen and set aside a final consent order issued in 2017 regarding Enbridge’s merger with energy infrastructure company Spectra Energy Corp.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s 2017 order with Enbridge&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2017/02/ftc-preserves-competition-merger-enbridge-inc-spectra-energy-corp"&gt;settled charges&lt;/a&gt; alleging that the proposed merger between Enbridge and Spectra would harm competition in the market for pipeline transportation of natural gas in three production areas off the coast of Louisiana. The FTC’s complaint alleged the merger likely would reduce natural gas pipeline competition within the Green Canyon, Walker Ridge, and Keathley Canyon production areas in the Gulf of Mexico because, after the acquisition, Enbridge would have an indirect ownership interest in the Discovery pipeline, the main competitor to Enbridge’s own Walker Ridge pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2017/03/ftc-approves-final-order-preserving-competition-3-natural-gas-production-areas-coast-louisiana"&gt;final consent order&lt;/a&gt; Enbridge was required to establish firewalls to limit its access to non-public information about the Discovery pipeline. Also, with two limited exceptions, board members of the Spectra-affiliated companies that hold a 40 percent share in the Discovery pipeline are required to recuse themselves from any vote involving the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/c4604enbridgepetitiontoreopenmodify.pdf"&gt;petition&lt;/a&gt;, Enbridge has asked the Commission to reopen and set aside the 2017 order since it no longer holds an indirect ownership interest in the Discovery pipeline. In 2024, Enbridge exited the partnership that gave it an indirect ownership interest in Discovery.&amp;nbsp;As a result, Enbridge no longer has access to the Discovery pipeline’s competitively sensitive information, nor does it have an ability to influence decisions concerning the Discovery pipeline, according to the petition.&amp;nbsp;Thus, the petition requests that the Commission should reopen and set aside the order.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comments on Enbridge’s application must be filed by February 21, 2025, through &lt;a href="https://www.regulations.gov/docket/FTC-2025-0006/document"&gt;regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;Instructions for filing comments appear on the docket.&amp;nbsp;Once processed, they will be posted on Regulations.gov.&amp;nbsp;After the comment period closes, the Commission will vote on whether to approve the application.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87322</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Releases Summary of Key Accomplishments</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-releases-summary-key-accomplishments</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Federal Trade Commission Chair Lina M. Khan released a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/public-statements/federal-trade-commission-accomplishments-june-2021-january-2025" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="9146b0e1-1e05-4f1f-a41a-a2ac922959e9" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;summary of the agency’s key accomplishments&lt;/a&gt; over the last four years that have improved Americans’ everyday lives and stopped illegal consolidation that raises prices and hampers innovation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These actions include&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Putting Money Back in Americans’ Pocketbooks:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission has helped put more money back into the pockets of American consumers by banning&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/federal-trade-commission-announces-bipartisan-rule-banning-junk-ticket-hotel-fees"&gt;junk fees&lt;/a&gt; for short-term lodging and live-event ticketing; finalizing a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/10/federal-trade-commission-announces-final-click-cancel-rule-making-it-easier-consumers-end-recurring"&gt;“click to cancel”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;rule requiring companies to make it just as easy to cancel subscriptions as it is to sign up; and banning&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/12/ftc-announces-cars-rule-fight-scams-vehicle-shopping" target="_blank"&gt;auto dealers&lt;/a&gt; from sticking American consumers with junk fees.&amp;nbsp;The agency took action against companies that use deceptive dark patterns to trick consumers into making unwanted purchases, obtaining more than $245 million for consumer refunds from Fortnite maker&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/03/ftc-finalizes-order-requiring-fortnite-maker-epic-games-pay-245-million-tricking-users-making"&gt;Epic Games&lt;/a&gt;. The FTC also secured $48 million in refunds for consumers who the agency alleged were charged junk fees, suffered unfair eviction practices, and unfairly had their security deposits withheld by corporate landlord&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/09/ftc-takes-action-against-invitation-homes-deceiving-renters-charging-junk-fees-withholding-security"&gt;Invitation Homes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stopping Illegal Consolidation that Raises Prices and Reduces Innovation:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The FTC successfully sued to block the $24.6 billion merger between&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/statement-ftc-victory-securing-halt-kroger-albertsons-grocery-merger"&gt;Kroger and Albertsons&lt;/a&gt;, a deal the agency alleged would have raised prices, led to store closures, and reduced compensation for unionized workers. The agency has vigorously policed consolidation across critical sectors of the economy, including&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/02/statement-regarding-termination-nvidia-corps-attempted-acquisition-arm-ltd"&gt;semiconductors&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/02/statement-regarding-termination-lockheed-martin-corporations-attempted-acquisition-aerojet"&gt;defense&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/05/ftc-order-bans-former-pioneer-ceo-exxon-board-seat-exxon-pioneer-deal"&gt;energy&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/04/ftc-moves-block-tapestrys-acquisition-capri"&gt;consumer products&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/07/statement-regarding-termination-novant-healths-acquisition-hospitals-community-health-systems"&gt;healthcare&lt;/a&gt;, and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/12/statement-regarding-termination-sanofis-proposed-acquisition-maze-therapeutics-pompe-disease-drug"&gt;pharmaceuticals&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;The agency also defeated &lt;a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.ftc.gov%2Fnews-events%2Fnews%2Fpress-releases%2F2021%2F08%2Fftc-alleges-facebook-resorted-illegal-buy-or-bury-scheme-crush-competition-after-string-failed&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7Cjhenderson2%40ftc.gov%7Caf87f673581c4bb75c8b08dd373bd4cb%7C7302cabc5af5469baf17700007935a01%7C0%7C0%7C638727452299397248%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=Gr8tc8z2rOAyQUnbhqNqoWwvs687%2BomMcoxRSkFdjcI%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0" target="_blank"&gt;Meta&lt;/a&gt;’s summary judgment motion in the FTC’s ongoing lawsuit alleging&amp;nbsp;Meta engaged in a series of acquisitions, including Instagram and WhatsApp, to illegally maintain its monopoly power.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Securing Americans’ Access to Healthcare:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The FTC took numerous actions to help ensure Americans have access to affordable health care, including&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/11/ftc-challenges-more-100-patents-improperly-listed-fdas-orange-book"&gt;challenging patents on drug products,&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;including inhalers and EpiPens, that were improperly listed in the FDA’s Orange Book. The FTC’s efforts led pharma companies to slash out-of-pocket costs for inhalers from $500 or more to just $35.&amp;nbsp;The agency sued the three largest pharmacy benefit managers (PBMs) for allegedly engaging in anticompetitive rebating practices that&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/09/ftc-sues-prescription-drug-middlemen-artificially-inflating-insulin-drug-prices" target="_blank"&gt;inflated the cost of insulin&lt;/a&gt;, sued a Texas&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/09/ftc-challenges-private-equity-firms-scheme-suppress-competition-anesthesiology-practices-across"&gt;anesthesiology provider&lt;/a&gt; that allegedly engaged in a private-equity roll-up scheme that consolidated the market and raised prices, and banned&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/01/statement-second-circuit-order-upholding-pharma-bro-martin-shkrelis-lifetime-ban" target="_blank"&gt;“Pharma Bro” Martin Shkreli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;from doing business in the pharmaceutical industry after he hiked the price of a lifesaving medication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protecting Workers from Coercion and Deception:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The FTC banned&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/04/ftc-announces-rule-banning-noncompetes" target="_blank"&gt;noncompete clauses&lt;/a&gt; from most employment contracts, which the agency estimated would increase the average American worker’s wages by $524 a year. The FTC has also taken enforcement actions in the space, ordering &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/03/ftc-approves-final-order-requiring-michigan-based-security-companies-drop-noncompete-restrictions" target="_blank"&gt;security guard&lt;/a&gt; and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/02/ftc-approves-final-orders-requiring-two-glass-container-manufacturers-drop-noncompete-restrictions" target="_blank"&gt;glass container&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/06/ftc-approves-final-order-requiring-anchor-glass-container-corp-drop-noncompete-restrictions-it" target="_blank"&gt;manufacturing&lt;/a&gt; companies to drop coercive noncompete clauses on low-wage workers and ordering two &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-building-service-contractors-no-hire-agreement" target="_blank"&gt;building services&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-orders-building-service-contractors-stop-enforcing-no-hire-agreement" target="_blank"&gt;contractors&lt;/a&gt; to drop&amp;nbsp;“no-hire” clauses with their customers that blocked the ability of employees to freely switch jobs and negotiate for better pay or benefits. The Commission took action against companies such as&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/08/ftc-takes-action-against-carecom-deceiving-caregivers-about-wages-availability-jobs-its-site"&gt;Care.com&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-illinois-attorney-general-take-action-against-grubhub-harming-diners-workers-small-businesses"&gt;Grubhub&lt;/a&gt; and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/10/ftc-takes-action-stop-lyft-deceiving-drivers-misleading-earnings-claims"&gt;Lyft&lt;/a&gt; for misleading workers about how much money they would make, and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2021/11/ftc-returns-nearly-60-million-drivers-whose-tips-were-illegally-withheld-amazon"&gt;returned nearly $60 million&lt;/a&gt; to more than 140,000 Amazon Flex drivers after Amazon illegally withheld tips from its drivers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Checking Harmful Commercial Surveillance:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The agency has aggressively policed the illegal collection, use, and sale of consumers’ sensitive personal information, banning&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/04/ftc-finalizes-order-x-mode-successor-outlogic-prohibiting-it-sharing-or-selling-sensitive-location" target="_blank"&gt;data&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/05/ftc-finalizes-order-inmarket-prohibiting-it-selling-or-sharing-precise-location-data" target="_blank"&gt;brokers&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-mobilewalla-collecting-selling-sensitive-location-data" target="_blank"&gt;selling&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;consumers’ precise geolocation data and banning&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/04/proposed-ftc-order-will-prohibit-telehealth-firm-cerebral-using-or-disclosing-sensitive-data"&gt;digital&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/07/ftc-gives-final-approval-order-banning-betterhelp-sharing-sensitive-health-data-advertising"&gt;health&lt;/a&gt; apps from disclosing consumers’ sensitive health data for advertising purposes. And, in the FTC’s first privacy action related to connected cars, the FTC banned&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-takes-action-against-general-motors-sharing-drivers-precise-location-driving-behavior-data"&gt;General Motors&lt;/a&gt; for five years from disclosing drivers’ geolocation data and driving behavior information to consumer reporting agencies. The agency has been particularly focused on protecting kids and teens online,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-finalizes-changes-childrens-privacy-rule-limiting-companies-ability-monetize-kids-data"&gt;strengthening the Children’s Online Privacy Protection Rule (COPPA)&lt;/a&gt; to&amp;nbsp;further limit companies’ ability to profit from kids’ personal data. The agency took numerous enforcement actions against companies for violating COPPA, including obtaining a record $275 million penalty from Fortnite creator&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/12/fortnite-video-game-maker-epic-games-pay-more-half-billion-dollars-over-ftc-allegations"&gt;Epic Games&lt;/a&gt; and suing&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/08/ftc-investigation-leads-lawsuit-against-tiktok-bytedance-flagrantly-violating-childrens-privacy-law"&gt;TikTok over charges that it flagrantly&lt;/a&gt; violated the children’s privacy law and its 2019 order related to previous COPPA violations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protecting Americans’ Right to Repair&lt;/strong&gt;: The FTC has worked to combat unlawful restrictions on consumers ability to repair products they buy, saving Americans money and allowing independent repair shops to thrive. The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-states-sue-deere-company-protect-farmers-unfair-corporate-tactics-high-repair-costs"&gt;agency recently&amp;nbsp;sued&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Deere &amp;amp; Company over its use of unfair practices that have driven up equipment repair costs for farmers while depriving farmers of the ability to make timely repairs on critical farming equipment, and it previously&amp;nbsp;obtained orders against&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/07/ftc-takes-action-against-weber-illegally-restricting-customers-right-repair" target="_blank"&gt;Weber&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/06/ftc-takes-action-against-harley-davidson-westinghouse-illegally-restricting-customers-right-repair-0" target="_blank"&gt;Harley-Davidson&lt;/a&gt;, and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/06/ftc-takes-action-against-harley-davidson-westinghouse-illegally-restricting-customers-right-repair-0" target="_blank"&gt;Westinghouse&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;to protect consumers’ right to repair&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;products they buy from those companies.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Helping Small Businesses Compete on a Level Playing Field&lt;/strong&gt;: The FTC sued&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/09/ftc-sues-amazon-illegally-maintaining-monopoly-power" target="_blank"&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; for raising costs for sellers that rely on the platform to reach consumers, ordered&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/05/ftc-approves-final-order-requiring-mastercard-stop-blocking-use-competing-debit-payment-networks" target="_blank"&gt;Mastercard&lt;/a&gt; to stop illegally blocking merchants from routing debit card payments through its payment network and raising costs for small businesses, and protected franchisees from junk fees and preserved their&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/07/ftc-takes-action-ensure-franchisees-complaints-are-heard-protect-against-illegal-fees" target="_blank"&gt;right to report law violations&lt;/a&gt; to the government. The agency also reinvigorated enforcement of the Robinson-Patman Act, which prohibits price discrimination that squeezes independent retailers, by suing&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-sues-southern-glazers-illegal-price-discrimination" target="_blank"&gt;Southern Glazer’s Wine and Spirits&lt;/a&gt;, the largest U.S. distributor of wine and spirits, and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-sues-pepsico-rigging-soft-drink-competition"&gt;Pepsi&lt;/a&gt; for favoring one large, big box retailer over other competitors when providing promotions and services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the last four years, the FTC has worked to maximize its authority to carry out its mission to protect consumers and promote competition, including by reactivating enforcement of the Robinson-Patman Act. It has proposed and finalized new rules that allow the agency to return money back to injured consumers, and it has brought its first-ever actions under the Health Breach Notification Rule with cases against prescription drug discount provider&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/02/ftc-enforcement-action-bar-goodrx-sharing-consumers-sensitive-health-info-advertising" target="_blank"&gt;GoodRx&lt;/a&gt; and fertility tracking app &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/05/ovulation-tracking-app-premom-will-be-barred-sharing-health-data-advertising-under-proposed-ftc" target="_blank"&gt;PreMom&lt;/a&gt;, the Military Lending Act in a case against&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/11/federal-court-orders-harris-jewelry-restore-its-website-claims-portal-servicemembers-request-refunds" target="_blank"&gt;Harris Jewelers&lt;/a&gt; and the Opioid Addiction Recovery Fraud Prevention Act, in cases against&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/05/ftc-hits-r360-its-owner-38-million-civil-penalty-judgment-preying-people-seeking-treatment-addiction" target="_blank"&gt;R360&lt;/a&gt; and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/04/alcohol-addiction-treatment-firm-will-be-banned-disclosing-health-data-advertising-settle-ftc" target="_blank"&gt;Monument&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87308</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Secures Settlement with Private Equity Firm in Antitrust Roll-Up Scheme Case</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-secures-settlement-private-equity-firm-antitrust-roll-scheme-case</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today announced a settlement with private equity firm Welsh, Carson, Anderson, and Stowe and its affiliates (collectively referred to as “Welsh Carson”) that resolves a potential second, administrative antitrust case against Welsh Carson.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2010031USAPWelshCarsonComplaint.pdf"&gt;complaint&lt;/a&gt;, the Commission alleges Welsh Carson, through its portfolio company U.S. Anesthesia Partners (USAP), engaged in anticompetitive acquisitions to suppress competition and drive up prices for anesthesiology services across Texas.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under a proposed &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2010031USAPWelshCarsonOrder.pdf"&gt;consent order&lt;/a&gt; resolving the FTC’s concerns, Welsh Carson will be required to limit its involvement with USAP and notify the FTC of specified future acquisitions and investments in anesthesia and other hospital-based physician practices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The settlement follows an initial September 2023&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/09/ftc-challenges-private-equity-firms-scheme-suppress-competition-anesthesiology-practices-across"&gt;federal court&lt;/a&gt; complaint in which the Commission alleged that USAP and Welsh Carson, which created USAP in 2012, engaged in a roll-up scheme by systemically buying up nearly every large anesthesia practice in Texas to create a single dominant provider with the power to demand higher prices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In May 2024, the district court dismissed Welsh Carson from the FTC’s federal challenge on procedural grounds, finding that the FTC lacked authority to bring the case against Welsh Carson in federal court because the complaint did not allege that Welsh Carson was currently violating the law, as required under Section 13(b) of the FTC Act. The Commission’s antitrust case against USAP continues to proceed in federal court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s latest action underscores that the common corporate tactic of seeking dismissal of a federal case on Section 13(b) grounds may delay—but will not deny—the FTC’s efforts to challenge anticompetitive conduct. If necessary, the Commission will bring suit in administrative court to protect consumers from anticompetitive conduct. The settlement here avoids the Commission bringing such an administrative action.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed Order&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s consent order outlines a variety of terms that protect the public from Welsh Carson’s potential future anticompetitive conduct and deter others from engaging in similar anticompetitive conduct.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s proposed consent agreement, among several other provisions, requires that Welsh Carson:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Limit its ongoing ownership rights and entanglements with USAP by freezing its investment in USAP at current levels and reducing its board representation to a single, non-chair seat. This will prevent Welsh Carson and its affiliates from retaking control over USAP and will reduce Welsh Carson’s ability to benefit from USAP’s monopoly position in Texas;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Obtain prior approval for any future investments in anesthesia nationwide, as well as prior approval for certain acquisitions by any majority-owned Welsh Carson anesthesia group nationwide; and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide 30-days advance notice for certain transactions involving other hospital-based physician practices nationwide.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to accept the consent agreement for public comment was 5-0. Chair Lina M. Khan &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/statement-chair-lina-m-khan-joined-commissioner-slaughter-commissioner-bedoya-regarding-welsh-carson" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="8497c1c4-5c14-4a1c-b55f-9d427920bfd9" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioners Rebecca Kelly Slaughter and Alvaro M. Bedoya. Commissioner Andrew N. Ferguson &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/concurring-statement-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-joined-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-matter-us" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="ad8dfc61-2238-4c38-a7e4-a712e4d731ad" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioner Melissa Holyoak.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further details about the proposed consent order can be found in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2010031USAPWelshCarsonAAPC.pdf"&gt;analysis to aid public comment&lt;/a&gt;. The FTC will publish the consent agreement package in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/"&gt;Federal Register&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;shortly. Instructions for filing comments appear in the published notice. Comments must be received 30 days after publication in the Federal Register. Once processed, comments will be posted on&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.regulations.gov/"&gt;Regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;The Commission issues an administrative complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the law has been or is being violated, and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest. When the Commission issues a consent order on a final basis, it carries the force of law with respect to future actions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87240</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Issues Staff Report on AI Partnerships &amp; Investments Study</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-issues-staff-report-ai-partnerships-investments-study</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today issued a staff report on the corporate partnerships and investments formed between the largest cloud service providers (CSPs)—Alphabet, Inc., Amazon.com, Inc., and Microsoft, Corp.—and two of the most prominent generative AI developers—Anthropic PBC and OpenAI OpCo, LLC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/reports/ftc-staff-report-ai-partnerships-investments-6b-study" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="96cee7c0-c3c5-4d8a-93bc-3fd7d99a3308" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; details key aspects regarding the structure of the CSP and AI developer partnerships, such as the equity and revenue-sharing rights retained by CSPs in these partnerships and certain consultation, control, and exclusivity rights CSPs gained through their investments with AI developers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report outlines some potential competition implications, including that: the partnerships may impact access to certain inputs, such as computing resources and engineering talent; the partnerships may increase switching costs for the AI developer partners; and the partnerships provide CSP partners access to sensitive technical and business information that may be unavailable to others.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“As companies rapidly deploy generative AI technologies, enforcers and policymakers must stay vigilant to guard against business strategies that undermine open markets, opportunity, and innovation,” said FTC Chair Lina M. Khan. “The FTC’s report sheds light on how partnerships by big tech firms can create lock-in, deprive start-ups of key AI inputs, and reveal sensitive information that can undermine fair competition.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff report stems from&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/01/ftc-launches-inquiry-generative-ai-investments-partnerships"&gt;FTC orders&lt;/a&gt; issued in January 2024 under Section 6(b) of the FTC Act. The orders were sent to five companies involved in three separate multi-billion-dollar investments: Microsoft and OpenAI, Amazon and Anthropic, and Alphabet and Anthropic.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s report is aimed at helping the Commission, the public, and policymakers deepen their understanding of the corporate partnerships between the generative AI developers and CSPs. The report’s findings also help equip the FTC to better evaluate the attributes and potential implications of partnerships involving large technology companies and the impact they may have on hundreds of millions of consumers, countless businesses, and huge segments of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Findings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The report highlights several key terms of the AI partnerships, which include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Significant equity and certain revenue-sharing rights for CSP partners in their AI developer partners;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Certain consultation, control, and exclusivity rights CSP partners hold to varying degrees with respect to their AI developer partners;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Commitments that require AI developers to spend a large portion of their CSP partner’s investment on cloud services from their partner;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sharing of key resources and information including access to large amounts of computing resources at discounted rates; assets and IP related to AI developers’ cutting-edge models; and certain financial and training data; and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Opportunities to expand current products including through integration of AI models into CSPs’ products or deployment of AI models on CSPs’ platforms.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the report highlights the following areas to watch regarding potential implications of the AI partnerships:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Their ability to impact access to certain inputs, such as computing resources and engineering talent, in ways that could affect competition for both AI developer partners and non-partner AI developers;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The potential to increase contractual and technical switching costs for AI developer partners, making it more difficult for them to change CSPs or restricting their use of multiple CSPs; and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;CSP partners’ access to sensitive technical and business information that may be unavailable to others, such as information related to generative AI models, AI development methods, confidential chip co-design, partner finances, and customer usage and revenue numbers.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Findings in the report represent information available to staff as of September 2024 as well as publicly available information through January 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission voted 5-0 to allow staff to issue the report. Chair Lina M. Khan will be issuing a statement. Commissioner Andrew N. Ferguson issued a concurring and dissenting &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/concurring-dissenting-statement-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-joined-commissioner-melissa-holyoak" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="72631aad-3efd-43b5-84e9-f7d120f276d9" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioner Melissa Holyoak. Commissioner Holyoak issued a concurring and dissenting &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/concurring-dissenting-statement-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-joined-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="19545e3d-e66a-473f-a1ab-96ba8201128c" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioner Ferguson.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87275</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Approves Final Order in Exxon-Pioneer Deal</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-approves-final-order-exxon-pioneer-deal</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today finalized a consent order that resolves antitrust concerns surrounding Exxon Mobil Corporation’s (Exxon) acquisition of oil producer Pioneer Natural Resources.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final consent order settles FTC charges first announced in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/05/ftc-order-bans-former-pioneer-ceo-exxon-board-seat-exxon-pioneer-deal"&gt;May 2024&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2410004-c4815-exxonpioneerfinalorderpublic.pdf"&gt;final consent order&lt;/a&gt;, Exxon is prohibited from nominating, designating, or appointing founder and former Pioneer CEO Scott Sheffield to the Exxon board or from serving in an advisory capacity in any way to the Exxon board or Exxon’s management.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the final consent order requires that for a period of five years, Exxon shall not nominate, designate, or appoint any Pioneer employee or director, other than certain named individuals, to the Exxon board. In addition, under the final order, Exxon, for a period of 10 years, will agree to certain Clayton Act Section 8 attestation and reporting obligations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a public comment period, the Commission voted 3-2 to approve the final order, with Commissioners Andrew N. Ferguson and Melissa Holyoak dissenting. Chair Lina M. Khan &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/statement-chair-lina-m-khan-matter-exxon-mobil-corp" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="494580b3-94e6-4d41-af94-f914f28052af" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a statement&lt;/a&gt;. Commissioner Holyoak &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/dissenting-statement-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-joined-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-matter-0" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="ece28098-8fa3-4004-80f1-23d4acceb7fe" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a dissenting statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioner Ferguson.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87246</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Approves Final Order Requiring Building Service Contractor to Stop Enforcing No-Hire Agreement</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-approves-final-order-requiring-building-service-contractor-stop-enforcing-no-hire-agreement</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, the Federal Trade Commission finalized a consent order that requires building services contractor Guardian Service Industries, Inc. (Guardian) to stop enforcing a no-hire agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC alleged in a complaint filed in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-building-service-contractors-no-hire-agreement"&gt;December 2024&lt;/a&gt; that Guardian’s no-hire agreement prohibited building owners and competing building service contractors from hiring Guardian’s employees. For Guardian employees—which include concierge personnel, custodians, and maintenance technicians—these no-hire agreements limit their ability to negotiate for higher wages, better benefits, and improved working conditions, the FTC’s complaint alleged.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2410082c4813guardianfinalorder.pdf"&gt;final consent order&lt;/a&gt; places several requirements and restrictions on Guardian, including ordering Guardian to cease and desist from, directly or indirectly, enforcing a no-hire agreement or communicating to any prospective or current customer that a Guardian employee is subject to a no-hire agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a public comment period, the Commission voted 3-2 to approve the final order, with Commissioners Holyoak and Ferguson dissenting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87242</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sues PepsiCo for Rigging Soft Drink Competition </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-sues-pepsico-rigging-soft-drink-competition</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today sued PepsiCo, Inc. (Pepsi) alleging that the second-largest food company in the world has engaged in illegal price discrimination by providing one customer—a large, big box retailer—with unfair pricing advantages, while raising prices for competing retailers and customers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years, Pepsi has disadvantaged retailers—ranging from large grocery chains to independent, local convenience stores—who compete with one of its largest big box customers by consistently giving that favored large, big box retailer customer key benefits and advantages, such as promotional payments, while denying those same benefits to its competitors, the FTC’s complaint alleges.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pepsi’s unfair practices have led to inflated prices for American families, while denying competing retailers the ability to fairly compete. Pepsi’s illegal conduct violates the Robinson-Patman Act (RPA), the FTC’s complaint alleges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“When firms like Pepsi give massive retailers a leg up, it tilts the playing field against small firms and ultimately inflates prices for American consumers,” said FTC Chair Lina M. Khan. “The FTC’s action will help ensure all grocers and other businesses—no matter the size—can get a fair shake and compete on the merits of their skill, efficiency, and talent.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the RPA, specifically sections 2(d) and 2(e), sellers are prohibited from engaging in price discrimination by using advertising and promotional allowances—which are financial incentives given to retailers by manufacturers to promote a product or brand—to favor large customers over small businesses. The FTC’s lawsuit alleges Pepsi violated the RPA by engaging in price discrimination using advertising and promotional allowances, as well as other tactics, to favor one large, big box retailer customer over other businesses. This case marks the FTC’s latest RPA enforcement action since the Commission sued the largest U.S. distributor of wine and spirits—&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-sues-southern-glazers-illegal-price-discrimination"&gt;Southern Glazer’s&lt;/a&gt;—in December 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A substantial portion of the law violations alleged by the FTC are redacted in the complaint due to the legal protections afforded to both Pepsi and their preferred customer—the large, big box retailer. The FTC staff will swiftly seek to lift the redactions in order to show the ways in which Pepsi violated the RPA on behalf their preferred customer and how those violations raised prices for Pepsi products for competing retailers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Pepsi’s Practices&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pepsi provides its favored large, big box retailer customer with promotional payments and allowances without making these equally available to that customer’s competitors. Pepsi also provides this favored retailer with various advertising and promotional tools, known as services and facilities, without making those benefits available to its competitors on a similar basis.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until Pepsi’s conduct is remedied, Pepsi’s anticompetitive actions will continue to create an uneven playing field by denying competing retailers, which include family-owned neighborhood grocery stores, the chance to fairly compete against Pepsi’s favored large, big box retailer customer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to authorize staff to file for a permanent injunction and other equitable relief in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York was 3-2, with Commissioners Melissa Holyoak and Andrew N. Ferguson dissenting. Chair Lina M. Khan &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/statement-chair-lina-m-khan-commissioner-alvaro-m-bedoya-matter-non-alcoholic-beverages-price" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="26effe06-8acd-4797-ac59-fcefb64a2b54" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a statement&lt;/a&gt;. Commissioner Holyoak issued a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/dissenting-statement-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-matter-pepsico-inc" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="a2262663-84b0-463f-8de0-7154d13cfed6" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;dissenting statement&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;nbsp;Commissioner Ferguson issued a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/dissenting-statement-commissioner-ferguson-non-alcoholic-beverages-price-discrimination-investigation" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="81caef43-9b02-48e5-93ad-679604a76592" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;dissenting statement&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission issues a complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the law has been or is being violated, and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest. The case will be decided by the court.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87265</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Approves Final Order in Chevron-Hess Deal</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-approves-final-order-chevron-hess-deal</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today finalized a consent order that resolves antitrust concerns surrounding Chevron Corporation’s acquisition of oil producer Hess Corporation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final consent order settles charges brought by the FTC in &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/09/ftc-order-bans-hess-ceo-chevron-board-chevron-hess-deal"&gt;September 2024&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the final consent &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2410008c4814chevronhessorder.pdf"&gt;order&lt;/a&gt;, Chevron is prohibited from nominating, designating, or appointing Hess CEO John B. Hess to the Chevron Board. Additionally, with certain exceptions noted below, under the final consent order, Chevron is prohibited from allowing John Hess to serve in an advisory or consulting capacity to, or as a representative of, Chevron or the Chevron Board.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the final order, Chevron is allowed to consult with John Hess and allow him to serve as an advisor, consultant, or representative of Chevron, solely related to interactions and discussions with (a) Guyanese government officials about Hess’s oil-related and health ministry-related activities in Guyana, and (b) the Salk Institute’s Harnessing Plants Initiative.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following a public comment period, the Commission vote to approval the final order was 3-2, with Commissioners Melissa Holyoak and Andrew N. Ferguson dissenting. Chair Lina M. Khan issued a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/statement-chair-lina-m-khan-matter-exxon-mobil-corp" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="494580b3-94e6-4d41-af94-f914f28052af" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87245</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC and DOJ Jointly Issue Antitrust Guidelines on Business Practices that Impact Workers </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-doj-jointly-issue-antitrust-guidelines-business-practices-impact-workers</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, the Federal Trade Commission and the Department of Justice Antitrust Division (DOJ) jointly issued antitrust guidelines for business activities affecting workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/ftc-doj-antitrust-guidelines-business-activities-affecting-workers" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="a65f3579-2a0f-435a-a7a7-b9f5fe665254" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;guidelines&lt;/a&gt; explain how both the FTC and DOJ assess whether business practices affecting workers violate the antitrust laws. These guidelines replace the 2016&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.justice.gov/atr/file/903511/dl?inline"&gt;Antitrust Guidance for Human Resource Professionals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Competition among employers helps workers through better wages, benefits, and other terms and conditions for working people. Similarly, vibrant, open markets to recruit and retain workers are conducive to new business formation, innovation, and productivity. As the guidelines state, business practices may violate the antitrust laws when they harm competition among employers, which can lead to worse outcomes for workers and the broader economy.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"The antitrust laws protect all Americans, including workers, from illegal monopolization, collusion, and unfair methods of competition," said FTC Chair Lina M. Khan. “These antitrust guidelines provide clarity to businesses about the practices that can violate the law—from agreements between firms to fix workers’ wages to coercive noncompetes.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidelines outline specific types of agreements or business practices that may violate the antitrust laws, such as the use of noncompetes or the sharing of information about wages among companies that compete for workers. The guidelines also outline agreements and other activities that may lead to criminal liability, including agreements to fix wages or agreements not to poach employees. Additionally, the guidelines explain that false claims about workers’ potential earnings may violate federal law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The guidelines also provide information about how to report potential antitrust violations to the FTC and DOJ.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote approving the joint guidance was 3-2, with Commissioners Andrew N. Ferguson and Melissa Holyoak dissenting. Commissioner Ferguson &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/dissenting-statement-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-joined-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-regarding-antitrust-guidelines-for-business-activities-affecting-workers" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="a91c7da6-16a4-4db2-a2a8-4ea41b67ccd2" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a dissenting statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioner Holyoak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87234</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC, States Sue Deere &amp; Company to Protect Farmers from Unfair Corporate Tactics, High Repair Costs </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-states-sue-deere-company-protect-farmers-unfair-corporate-tactics-high-repair-costs</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today, along with the Illinois and Minnesota Attorneys General, sued agricultural equipment manufacturer Deere &amp;amp; Company (Deere) over its use of unfair practices that have driven up equipment repair costs for farmers while also depriving farmers of the ability to make timely repairs on critical farming equipment, including tractors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/DeereCoREDACTEDComplaintCaseNo325-cv-50017.pdf"&gt;complaint alleges&lt;/a&gt; that, for decades, Deere’s unlawful practices have limited the ability of farmers and independent repair providers to repair Deere equipment, forcing farmers to instead rely on Deere’s network of authorized dealers for necessary repairs. This unfair steering practice has boosted Deere’s multi-billion-dollar profits on agricultural equipment and parts, growing its repair parts business while burdening farmers with higher repair costs, the FTC’s complaint alleges.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Illegal repair restrictions can be devastating for farmers, who rely on affordable and timely repairs to harvest their crops and earn their income,” said FTC Chair Lina M. Khan. “The FTC’s action today seeks to ensure that farmers across America are free to repair their own equipment or use repair shops of their choice—lowering costs, preventing ruinous delays, and promoting fair competition for independent repair shops.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Durable, reliable, and easily repairable agricultural equipment is critical to American farmers. Yet, Deere, which maintains a dominant market share position across the large agricultural equipment market, has made it difficult for farmers to repair their own equipment or turn to local, independent repair providers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The only fully functional software repair tool capable of performing all repairs on Deere equipment is produced by Deere. Deere makes this tool available only to Deere’s authorized dealers, forcing farmers to solely rely on more expensive authorized dealers for critical repairs. By creating these restrictions, Deere has unlawfully acquired and maintained monopoly power in the market for certain repair services for Deere agricultural equipment, according to the FTC’s complaint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deere’s Monopoly Power&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Historically, farmers have sought to repair their own equipment or relied on local, independent repair providers, which have offered various advantages over authorized Deere dealers, including lower costs, better reliability, and faster repair times.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yet, with the increasing computerization of Deere’s equipment over the past few decades, farmers must now rely on Deere’s interactive software tool called Service ADVISOR, which Deere makes available only to its authorized dealers, the FTC’s complaint states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;An inferior repair tool exists, called Customer Service ADVISOR, but it is incapable of doing all repairs on Deere agriculture equipment. Deere also fails to make available to generic repair tool developers the information necessary to develop a fully functional repair tool, as equipment manufacturers in the automotive and trucking industries do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through its limited distribution of its repair tools, Deere has been able to control and limit who can repair its agricultural equipment, allowing Deere to maintain a 100% market share and charge higher prices, via its network of authorized dealers, for all repairs that require the fully functional tool.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deere’s repair restrictions allow it to reap additional profits through parts sales, as its authorized network of dealers almost always use expensive Deere-branded parts in their repairs in lieu of generic parts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite increasing public pressure to give farmers the right to repair their own equipment, including state legislative action, Deere continues to unlawfully withhold a fully functional repair tool from equipment owners. Deere’s restrictions deprive farmers of the use of their own repair labor, deny them access to their preferred repair service providers, prevent them from more reliably planting, spraying, or harvesting crops on a schedule that would allow them to maximize yield, and force them to spend more on repair and parts, the FTC’s complaint states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s lawsuit seeks to stop Deere’s anticompetitive conduct by ordering, among other remedies, that Deere make available to owners of Deere large tractors and combines, as well as independent repair providers, access to its fully functional Service ADVISOR repair tool and any other repair resources available to authorized dealers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to authorize staff to file for a permanent injunction and other equitable relief in the U.S. District Court for the Northern District of Illinois was 3-2, with Commissioners Melissa Holyoak and Andrew Ferguson dissenting. Chair Lina M. Khan&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/statement-chair-lina-m-khan-matter-deere-company" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="0d573716-f18a-499e-8e54-bd680626a7b5" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt; issued a statement&lt;/a&gt;. Commissioner Ferguson &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/dissenting-statement-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-joined-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-matter-deere" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="67b7ae6a-7b7d-44e9-8beb-fd8aa39e0882" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a dissenting statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioner Melissa Holyoak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission issues a complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the law has been or is being violated, and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87195</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Seeks Public Comment on Single-Family Rental Home Mega Investors Study </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-seeks-public-comment-single-family-rental-home-mega-investors-study</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission issued a request for public comment on potential FTC orders that seek to understand how large-scale single-family rental owner operators, known as mega investors, have affected home prices and rents across the single-family rental market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission voted to authorize staff to publish a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/federal-register-notices/single-family-rental-investors-notice-request-public-comment" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="222d23e5-f685-4e9e-9936-4fd467aef6f4" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;Federal Register Notice &lt;/a&gt;seeking public comment on potential 6(b) orders that would inform an FTC study of mega single-family rental investors. Mega single-family rental investors are entities that own more than 1,000 single-family rental homes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The potential 6(b) orders would seek information from more than 30 mega investors regarding their corporate structure, current and historical housing inventory information, rental and fee income, as well as strategic business plans and other investor information regarding growth plans, competition, prices, and expenses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“As Americans face a housing shortage and pay soaring rents, it’s vital to understand the role played by large institutional investors,” said FTC Chair Lina M. Khan. “This proposed study would shed much-needed light on the mega-investors that have amassed huge portfolios of single-family rental units and potentially contributed to the housing challenges that Americans face.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The rise in mega corporate landlords has deeply troubling implications for renters,” said Director of the Office of Policy Planning Hannah Garden-Monheit. “The FTC is committed to uncovering the scope of these large corporations’ holdings and their effects on housing costs.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is seeking public comment on the potential orders to mega investors, including comments on which entities may qualify as mega investors. Additionally, the FTC invites comments on the practicality of the proposed orders, the accuracy of the FTC’s estimated cost burden, as well as ways to enhance the quality, utility and clarity of the information being collected while minimizing the burden on the orders’ recipients of producing the requested data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If the potential 6(b) orders are issued, the FTC plans to publish a comprehensive property list that will match individual single-family rental properties to their affiliated owner entities based on information received from the proposed 6(b) orders. In addition,&amp;nbsp;the information obtained in this proposed 6(b) study would help the FTC understand how the rise of mega investors into single-family rental homes has affected house prices and rental rates, as well as the effects of ongoing consolidation in the industry.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These comments will be considered before the FTC submits a request for the Office of Management and Budget to review the 6(b) orders as required under the Paperwork Reduction Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;An Area of Growing Concern&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Following the 2007-2008 financial crisis, the single-family rental home market structure changed with the rise of large-scale investors that own large regional single-family rental inventories. Researchers estimate that mega single-family rental investors collectively own and operate 446,000 homes nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s request for public comment on a proposed 6(b) study into mega investors follows growing concern from local, state, and federal policy makers regarding the growth of mega single-family rental investors in local markets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Members of the public submitted numerous comments specifically identifying large single-family rental investors as responsible for buying up inventories of houses in local markets across the United States in response to a recent FTC and DOJ&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/05/ftc-doj-seek-info-serial-acquisitions-roll-strategies-across-us-economy"&gt;request for information&lt;/a&gt; on serial acquisitions. In an FTC listening session in June 2024 for renters in Atlanta, participants expressed concerns about the effects of mega single-family rental investor expansion. Members of Congress also have sent the FTC letters urging that the Commission use its existing authority to require reporting of residential real estate transactions under the Hart-Scott-Rodino Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The public will have 60 days to submit comments at Regulations.gov. Once submitted, comments will be posted to &lt;a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2025/01/24/2025-01657/agency-information-collection-activities-proposed-collection-comment-request"&gt;Regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote authorizing the publication of the Federal Register notice was 5-0. Commissioner Andrew N. Ferguson &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/statement-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-joined-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-regarding-6b-study" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="026b9d7a-115b-4c0c-ae14-5239b003c49a" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioner Melissa Holyoak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87173</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Releases Second Interim Staff Report on Prescription Drug Middlemen</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-releases-second-interim-staff-report-prescription-drug-middlemen</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today published a second interim staff report on the prescription drug middleman industry, which focuses on pharmacy benefit managers’ (PBMs) influence over specialty generic drugs, including significant price markups by PBMs for cancer, HIV, and a variety of other critical drugs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/reports/specialty-generic-drugs-growing-profit-center-vertically-integrated-pharmacy-benefit-managers" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="57ec9734-5361-4c09-949b-d4ff4e6924fb" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;Staff’s latest report&lt;/a&gt; found that the ‘Big 3 PBMs’—Caremark Rx, LLC (CVS), Express Scripts, Inc. (ESI), and OptumRx, Inc. (OptumRx)—marked up numerous specialty generic drugs dispensed at their affiliated pharmacies by thousands of percent, and many others by hundreds of percent. Such significant markups allowed the Big 3 PBMs and their affiliated specialty pharmacies to generate more than $7.3 billion in revenue from dispensing drugs in excess of the drugs’ estimated acquisition costs from 2017-2022. The Big 3 PBMs netted such significant revenues all while patient, employer, and other health care plan sponsor payments for drugs steadily increased annually, according to the staff report.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The FTC staff’s second interim report finds that the three major pharmacy benefit managers hiked costs for a wide range of lifesaving drugs, including medications to treat heart disease and cancer,” said FTC Chair Lina M. Khan. “The FTC should keep using its tools to investigate practices that may inflate drug costs, squeeze independent pharmacies, and deprive Americans of affordable, accessible healthcare—and should act swiftly to stop any illegal conduct.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“FTC staff have found that the Big 3 PBMs are charging enormous markups on dozens of lifesaving drugs,” said Hannah Garden-Monheit, Director of the FTC’s Office of Policy Planning. “We also found that this problem is growing at an alarming rate, which means there is an urgent need for policymakers to address it.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Staff’s latest report builds on a report issued by FTC staff in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/07/ftc-releases-interim-staff-report-prescription-drug-middlemen"&gt;July 2024&lt;/a&gt;, which found that pharmacies affiliated with the Big 3 PBMs received 68% of the dispensing revenue generated by specialty drugs in 2023, up from 54% in 2016. The latest report analyzes a broader set of specialty generic drugs compared to two specialty generic drugs analyzed in the July 2024 report and finds that the Big 3 PBMs impose significant markups on a wide array of specialty generic drugs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s second interim staff report analyzed all specialty generic drugs dispensed from 2017 to 2022 for members of commercial health plans and Medicare Part D prescription drug plans managed by the Big 3 PBMs for which the FTC has relevant data. This includes an analysis of 51 specialty generic drugs comprising 882 National Drug Codes, which include the generic versions of: Ampyra (used to treat multiple sclerosis), Gleevec (used to treat leukemia), Sensipar (used to treat renal disease), and Myfortic (used by transplant recipients).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Key Findings&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s latest interim staff report is part of the Commission’s ongoing study of the PBM industry. This report highlights several key insights gained from data and documents obtained from special orders the FTC issued in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/06/ftc-launches-inquiry-prescription-drug-middlemen-industry"&gt;2022&lt;/a&gt; under Section 6(b) of the FTC Act, as well as from publicly available information:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Significant price markups:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Big 3 PBMs imposed &lt;em&gt;markups of hundreds and thousands of percent on numerous specialty generic drugs&lt;/em&gt; dispensed at their affiliated pharmacies—including drugs used to treat cancer, HIV, and other serious diseases and conditions. The Big 3 PBMs also reimbursed their affiliated pharmacies at a higher rate than they paid unaffiliated pharmacies on nearly every specialty generic drug examined.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dispensing the most profitable drugs:&lt;/strong&gt; A larger, disproportionate share of commercial prescriptions for specialty generic drugs marked up more than $1,000 per prescription were dispensed by the Big 3 PBMs’ affiliated pharmacies compared with unaffiliated pharmacies. Dispensing patterns suggest that the Big 3 PBMs may be steering highly profitable prescriptions to their own affiliated pharmacies (and away from unaffiliated pharmacies).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Over $7.3 billion of dispensing revenue in excess of NADAC:&lt;/strong&gt; The Big 3 PBMs’ affiliated pharmacies generated over $7.3 billion of dispensing revenue in excess of their estimated acquisition cost, as measured by the National Average Drug Acquisition Cost (NADAC), on specialty generic drugs over the study period. PBM-affiliated pharmacy dispensing revenue in excess of NADAC increased dramatically at a &lt;em&gt;compound annual growth rate of 42 percent&lt;/em&gt; from 2017-2021. In the aggregate, the&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;top 10 specialty generic drugs generated $6.2 billion of dispensing revenue in excess of NADAC&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;(85 percent of total).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating additional income via spread pricing:&lt;/strong&gt; In the aggregate, the Big 3 PBMs also separately generated an estimated $1.4 billion of income from spread pricing—i.e., billing their plan sponsor clients more than they reimburse pharmacies for drugs—on the analyzed specialty generic drugs over the study period.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specialty generic drugs help drive parent healthcare conglomerates’ operating income:&lt;/strong&gt; The top specialty generic drugs accounted for a significant share of the relevant business segments reported by the Big 3 PBMs’ parent healthcare conglomerates. Operating income from the Big 3 PBMs’ affiliated pharmacies dispensing of the analyzed &lt;em&gt;specialty generic drugs accounted for 12 percent of the aggregated operating income reported by the parent healthcare conglomerates’ business segments&lt;/em&gt; that include their PBM and pharmacy businesses in 2021.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plan sponsor and patient drug spending increased significantly:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;In 2021, the last year for which the FTC received full-year data for this study, plan sponsors paid $4.8 billion for specialty generic drugs, while patient cost sharing totaled $297 million. Between 2017 and 2021 plan sponsors and patient payments both increased at compound annual growth rates of 21% for commercial claims, and 14%-15% for Medicare Part D claims.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;FTC staff remain committed to providing timely updates as the Commission continues to receive and review additional information as part of the ongoing study.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission voted 5-0 to allow staff to issue the second interim staff report. Commissioner Andrew N. Ferguson &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/concurring-statement-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-joined-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-regarding-0" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="f26a7dcd-985f-47cc-abbe-e2b6218b835a" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a concurring statement&lt;/a&gt; joined by Commissioner Melissa Holyoak.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87172</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Issues Policy Statement Clarifying that Independent Contractors, Gig Workers’ Organizing Activities Are Shielded from Antitrust Liability</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-issues-policy-statement-clarifying-independent-contractors-gig-workers-organizing-activities-are</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/enforcement-policy-statement-exemption-protected-labor-activity-workers-antitrust-liability" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="cacad8b7-cf69-412d-a0e3-1f76fa1f67d2" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a policy statement&lt;/a&gt; clarifying that independent contractors, including gig workers, are shielded from antitrust liability when engaging in protected bargaining and organizing activities—such as seeking better compensation and job conditions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the FTC’s policy statement, the Commission will not challenge collective action by independent contractors and gig workers, which include rideshare and food delivery drivers, that provide labor services and are seeking better compensation and job conditions because such activities are exempted under the antitrust statutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Companies increasingly rely on gig workers and independent contractors. As more of these workers consider unionizing to secure better pay and conditions, the FTC is making clear that the antitrust laws do not stand in the way of their efforts to collectively organize or bargain,” said FTC Chair Lina M. Khan.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Gig workers shouldn’t be forced to accept low wages or poor working conditions just because they’re independent contractors,” said Hannah Garden-Monheit, Director of the FTC’s Office of Policy Planning. “The FTC’s policy statement today makes clear that the antitrust laws do not prevent gig workers from collectively organizing to fight for a better living.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the Clayton and Norris-LaGuardia Acts, the ability of workers to organize and collectively bargain over wages and labor conditions is protected from antitrust liability. However, as more workers are increasingly classified as independent contractors and gig workers, they face a patchwork of cases regarding the potential application of the labor exemption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s policy statement makes clear that workers engaged in protected bargaining or organizing activity are not categorically excluded from the antitrust exemption simply because they do not have a formal employer-employee relationship with the firm with which they are negotiating regarding compensation or working conditions. According to the policy statement, the protection of all workers from antitrust liability when they are engaged in protected labor activities is firmly grounded in the statutory text, consistent with existing case law, and reflective of the original meaning of the labor exemption.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Categorically excluding all independent contractors from the protections of the labor exemption would give employers both the incentive and opportunity to exploit asymmetries in antitrust liability protection between workers, according to the policy statement. For example, businesses would have an opportunity and incentive to classify (or misclassify) their workers as independent contractors to suppress wages and to gain an unfair advantage against competitors who provide better compensation and job conditions to workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission voted 3-2 to approve the policy statement with Commissioners Andrew N. Ferguson and Melissa Holyoak voting no. Commissioner Ferguson&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/dissenting-statement-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-joined-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-regarding" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="ac8532f8-31d3-4e44-9e7a-2f20a2ea2da7" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt; issued a dissenting statement joined by Commissioner Holyoak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87178</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Announces 2025 Update of Size of Transaction Thresholds for Premerger Notification Filings </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-announces-2025-update-size-transaction-thresholds-premerger-notification-filings</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission has approved a revised jurisdictional and a revised filing fee schedule for the Hart‑Scott‑Rodino (HSR) Antitrust Improvements Act of 1976. Section 7A(a)(2) of the Act requires the Commission to revise the jurisdictional thresholds annually, based on the change in gross national product.&amp;nbsp;The FTC is also required to revise the related HSR filing fee schedule annually based on changes in the gross national product and in the consumer price index under Division GG of the 2023 Consolidated Appropriations Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For 2025, the size-of-transaction threshold for reporting proposed mergers and acquisitions under Section 7A of the Clayton Act will adjust from $119.5 million to $126.4 million.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/federal-register-notices/revised-jurisdicational-thresholds-section-7a-clayton-act-2025" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="b19205e4-b376-4d54-b3a3-690e65ea60a0" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;revised jurisdictional thresholds and filing fee schedule&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;will apply to all transactions that close on or after the effective date of the notice, which is 30 days after its publication in the Federal Register.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vote approving the Federal Register Annual Notice of Revision announcing the new HSR jurisdictional thresholds and filing fee schedule was 5-0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87142</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Announces 2025 Jurisdictional Threshold Updates for Interlocking Directorates</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-announces-2025-jurisdictional-threshold-updates-interlocking-directorates</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission has approved revised jurisdictional thresholds for Section 8 of the Clayton Act, which prohibits interlocking directorates, which is an arrangement that occurs when an officer or director of one firm simultaneously serves as an officer or director of a competing firm.For&amp;nbsp;2025, thresholds under Section 8 of the Act that trigger prohibitions on certain interlocking memberships on corporate boards of directors are $51,380,000 for Section 8(a)(l) and $5,138,000&amp;nbsp;for Section 8(a)(2)(A).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/federal-register-notices/revised-jurisdictional-thresholds-section-8-clayton-act-2025" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="bac2442f-f976-4e9c-ac9e-2cfe8b572cdc" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;thresholds for Section 8 of the Clayton Act&lt;/a&gt; become effective upon their publication in the Federal Register. A&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/premerger-notification-program/current-thresholds"&gt;complete listing of current thresholds&lt;/a&gt; can be found on the FTC’s website, and will be updated closer to the time they become effective.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The vote approving the Federal Register notice announcing the threshold revisions was 5-0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87143</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Oil Companies to Pay Record FTC Gun-Jumping Fine for Antitrust Law Violation </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/oil-companies-pay-record-ftc-gun-jumping-fine-antitrust-law-violation</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, the Federal Trade Commission announced that crude oil producers XCL Resources Holdings, LLC (XCL), Verdun Oil Company II LLC (Verdun), and EP Energy LLC (EP) will pay a record $5.6 million civil penalty to settle allegations they engaged in illegal pre-merger coordination, known as gun jumping, in violation of the Hart-Scott-Rodino Act (HSR Act).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/complaintforcivilpenaltiesandequitablereliefforviolationsofthehartscottrodinoact.pdf"&gt;According to the complaint&lt;/a&gt;, Verdun, which was under common management with XCL at the time of the transaction, agreed to acquire EP in a $1.4 billion transaction that was subject to the HSR Act. The HSR Act requires merging parties to submit an HSR form to the federal antitrust agencies and observe a waiting period before completing a transaction. EP, however, allowed XCL and Verdun to assume operational and decision-making control over significant aspects of EP’s day-to-day business operations prior to the transaction closing, in violation of the HSR Act’s waiting period requirements, the complaint states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The three companies’ unlawful gun-jumping activities during the HSR waiting period included XCL and Verdun ordering a stoppage to EP’s planned well-drilling and development activities; XCL and EP coordinating to manage EP’s customer contracts, relationships, and deliveries in the Uinta Basin region of Utah; and Verdun and EP coordinating on prices for EP’s customers in the Eagle Ford region of Texas. This led to a crude oil supply shortage for EP when the U.S. market was facing significant supply shortages and multi-year highs in oil prices, resulting in Americans paying skyrocketing prices at the pump, the complaint states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The civil penalty settlement reached with XCL, Verdun, and EP provides for the largest dollar penalty ever imposed for a gun-jumping violation in U.S. history.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The HSR Act requires companies and individuals to report large transactions, including securities acquisitions, over a certain threshold to the FTC and DOJ so that the federal agencies can investigate the deals before they close. The agencies have 30 days after a transaction has been reported to conduct an initial investigation and issue a “second request” demand for additional information. It is generally illegal to finalize an acquisition during this investigatory period.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;FTC Investigation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The waiting-period obligation for this transaction went into effect on July 26, 2021, the date XCL, Verdun, and EP executed their purchase agreement and began engaging in gun-jumping activities, according to the FTC’s complaint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s investigation of Verdun’s acquisition of EP uncovered significant competitive concerns given that the deal, as originally structured, would have eliminated head-to-head competition between two of only four significant energy producers and would have harmed competition for the sale of Uinta Basin waxy crude oil to Salt Lake City refiners. To resolve those concerns, the FTC entered into a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/03/ftc-requires-encap-sell-ep-energy-corps-entire-utah-oil-business-amid-concerns-deal-would-increase"&gt;consent agreement&lt;/a&gt; with XCL, Verdun, and EP in March 2022 that required the divestiture of EP’s entire business and assets in Utah.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;XCL, Verdun, and EP’s illegal gun-jumping conduct lasted through October 27, 2021, when they executed an amendment to the purchase agreement, which allowed EP to operate independently once again and in the ordinary course of business, without XCL’s or Verdun’s control over its day-to-day operations.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The HSR waiting period expired on March 25, 2022, which is the date the FTC accepted a consent agreement and granted termination of the waiting period. In total, XCL, Verdun, and EP were in violation of the HSR Act for 94 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to accept the settlement and refer the matter to the Department of Justice for filing was 4-0-1, with Commissioner Holyoak recused. The Department of Justice filed the complaint and proposed stipulated order on the FTC’s behalf in the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As required by the Tunney Act, the proposed settlement, along with a competitive impact statement, was published in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2025/01/21/2025-01252/united-states-of-america-v-xcl-resources-holdings-llc-verdun-oil-company-ii-llc-and-ep-energy-llc"&gt;Federal Register&lt;/a&gt;. Any person may submit written comments concerning the proposed settlement during a 60-day comment period to Maribeth Petrizzi, Special Attorney, United States, c/o Federal Trade Commission, 600 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW, Washington, DC 20580&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="mailto:bccompliance@ftc.gov"&gt;bccompliance@ftc.gov&lt;/a&gt;. At the conclusion of the 60-day comment period, the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia may approve the proposed settlement upon finding that it is in the public interest.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87108</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Announces Tentative Agenda for January 14 Open Commission Meeting</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-announces-tentative-agenda-january-14-open-commission-meeting</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, Federal Trade Commission Chair Lina M. Khan announced that an open meeting of the Commission will be held virtually on Tuesday, January 14, 2025. The open meeting will commence at 11 a.m. ET and will begin with time for members of the public to address the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The following items will be on the tentative agenda for the January 14 Commission meeting:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Business Before the Commission:&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Housing 6(b):&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;The Commission will consider issuing a request for public comment on 6(b) orders related to the housing market. These orders would examine the magnitude of single-family rental investor holdings and to assess mega-investor strategies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Labor Exemption Policy Statement:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission will consider whether to issue a policy statement clarifying its view that the Clayton Act’s labor exemption application does not turn on whether a worker is formally classified as an employee or independent contractor.&amp;nbsp;The proposed policy statement will make clear that workers’ organizing and collective bargaining activity may be protected from antitrust liability when what is at issue is the compensation for their labor or their working conditions. &amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PBM 6(b) Second Interim Report:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission will consider issuing a second interim staff report highlighting additional staff findings from the Commission’s 6(b) study on the contracting practices of pharmacy benefit managers, or PBMs. The second interim report expands on staff’s initial findings regarding specialty drugs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the start of the meeting, Chair Khan will offer brief remarks and will then invite members of the public to share feedback on the Commission’s work generally and bring relevant matters to the Commission’s attention. Members of the public&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/speaker-registration-and-public-comment-submission-form-open-commission-meeting-01-14-25"&gt;must sign up&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;for an opportunity to address the Commission virtually at the January 14 event.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each commenter will be given two minutes to share their comments. Those who cannot participate during the event may submit written comments or a link to a prerecorded video&amp;nbsp;through a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/speaker-registration-and-public-comment-submission-form-open-commission-meeting-01-14-25"&gt;webform&lt;/a&gt;. Speaker registration and comment submission will be available through Friday, January 10, 2025 at 8 pm ET.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A link to view the meeting will be available on the day of the event, shortly before is starts via FTC.gov. The event will be recorded, and the webcast and any related comments will be available on the Commission’s website after the meeting. The Commission retains discretion to make public comments available following the event on FTC.gov.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>ndrayton</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87109</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Orders Building Service Contractors to Stop Enforcing a No-Hire Agreement</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-orders-building-service-contractors-stop-enforcing-no-hire-agreement</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission today ordered building services contractor Planned Building Services and its affiliated companies to cease their enforcement of no-hire agreements that limit the ability of residential and commercial building owners from hiring building service workers employed by Planned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a complaint filed against Planned Building Services, Inc., Planned Security Services, Inc., Planned Lifestyle Services, Inc., and Planned Technologies Services, Inc. which do business as Planned Companies, (Planned), &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2410029plannedcomplaint.pdf"&gt;the FTC alleges&lt;/a&gt; the companies’ enforcement of their no-hire agreements, which are included in customer service agreements with building owners, has limited workers’ ability to negotiate for higher wages, better benefits, and improved working conditions. Under the no-hire agreements, building owners are forced to pay a penalty if they hire a Planned employee.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Planned’s anticompetitive practices have unfairly restrained low wage workers from seeking higher pay, better benefits, and new job opportunities. Today’s action further underscores the FTC’s commitment to stopping unfair business practices that restrict workers’ economic freedom,” said Henry Liu, Director of the FTC’s Bureau of Competition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building service workers, which range from concierge personnel to janitors and maintenance technicians, employed by Planned suffer hardship if the building they work at changes management, as the no-hire agreement may force an employee to leave their job, according to the complaint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s complaint focuses on Planned’s conduct across New York City and New Jersey. This case marks the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-building-service-contractors-no-hire-agreement"&gt;second action&lt;/a&gt; the FTC, in partnership with the offices of the New York and New Jersey attorneys general, has recently taken against anticompetitive no-hire agreements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Planned’s no-hire agreements also limit building owners’ ability to switch to a competing building services contractor since the owner would risk losing any existing employees of Planned who could not continue at the building and work for Planned’s competitor without the new contractor paying a penalty given the terms of Planned’s no-hire agreement. This further restricts Planned’s competitors from making investments and meeting customer demand for increased quantity, quality, and variety of services, and ultimately harming consumers, the complaint states.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/06-Planned-DecisionandOrder.pdf"&gt;FTC’s proposed consent order&lt;/a&gt;, Planned must immediately cease and desist from, directly or indirectly, enforcing a no-hire agreement or communicating to any prospective or current customer that a Planned employee is subject to a no-hire agreement. Planned cannot maintain nor can it enforce, a no-hire agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, under the proposed consent order, Planned must:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide notice to directors, officers, and employees with responsibility for hiring or recruitment of Planned employees or negotiating customer contracts with a copy of the FTC’s order that shows that the no-hire agreement is no longer in effect.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide notice to new employees and in any shared employees spaces stating that their employment will not be subject to a no-hire agreement.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to issue the complaint and accept the proposed consent agreement for public comment was 5-0. Chair Lina M. Khan &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/statement-chair-lina-m-khan-matter-planned-building-services-inc" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="5e2f53c1-73b6-42fb-96a2-879225a6c64e" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a statement&lt;/a&gt;. Commissioner Andrew N. Ferguson joined by Commissioner Melissa Holyoak &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/public-statements/concurring-statement-commissioner-andrew-n-ferguson-joined-commissioner-melissa-holyoak-matter-0" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="0b20e079-73de-4dc6-ad22-14d4340fc5d4" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;issued a statement&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC will publish the consent agreement package in the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/"&gt;Federal Register&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;shortly. Instructions for filing comments appear in the published notice. Comments must be received 30 days after publication in the Federal Register. Once processed, comments will be posted on&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.regulations.gov/"&gt;Regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;The Commission issues an administrative complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the law has been or is being violated, and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest. When the Commission issues a consent order on a final basis, it carries the force of law with respect to future actions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87091</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Statement on Appellate Court Decision Ordering Delisting of Teva Inhaler Patents</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-statement-appellate-court-decision-ordering-delisting-teva-inhaler-patents</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit affirmed a lower district court order against pharmaceutical maker Teva requiring the drugmaker to delist several asthma inhaler patents from the Food and Drug Administration’s (FDA) Orange Book.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The appellate court order stems from a case brought by Teva against drugmaker Amneal after Amneal sought FDA approval to bring a generic version of the asthma inhaler ProAir HFA to market. The FTC had&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/03/ftc-files-amicus-brief-asthma-inhaler-patent-dispute"&gt;previously submitted&lt;/a&gt; amicus briefs in this case, with both the appellate and district courts, urging the delisting of Teva’s patents because they are improperly listed in the FDA’s Orange Book, which can ultimately harm competition by delaying or deterring the entry of cheaper generic products. The FTC also&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/11/ftc-challenges-more-100-patents-improperly-listed-fdas-orange-book"&gt;previously challenged&lt;/a&gt; Teva’s inhaler patents via the FDA’s Orange Book dispute process, as well as hundreds of other similar device patent listings by major pharmaceutical manufacturers—including&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2023/11/ftc-challenges-more-100-patents-improperly-listed-fdas-orange-book"&gt;other companies’ inhaler listings as well as listings on epinephrine autoinjectors&lt;/a&gt; and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/04/ftc-expands-patent-listing-challenges-targeting-more-300-junk-listings-diabetes-weight-loss-asthma"&gt;diabetes and weight loss drugs.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to the appellate court’s decision ordering the delisting, Hannah Garden-Monheit, Director of the FTC’s Office of Policy Planning, issued the following statement:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“We are pleased the court agreed with the FTC that these improper inhaler patent listings must be wiped from the Orange Book. Removal of junk patent listings is critical to ensuring drugmakers can fairly compete to offer generic drugs at a lower price for consumers. This decision is important not only for lowering asthma inhaler costs, it also sets the stage for removal of junk listings on a range of other critical medications where junk device listings impede competition.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Orange Book is a list of drug products approved by the FDA as safe and effective. When a brand pharmaceutical company lists a patent in the Orange Book, it may lead to a statutory stay that generally blocks the introduction of competing drug products for 30 months, including lower-cost generic alternatives. Listing patents in the Orange Book may negatively affect competitive conditions if listings are improper, as defined by law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In September 2023, the FTC also issued a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/p239900orangebookpolicystatement092023.pdf"&gt;policy statement&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;that warned that the agency would be scrutinizing the improper submission of patents for listing in the Orange Book. The Commission said improper listings in the Orange Book may harm competition from cheaper generic alternatives and keep brand prices artificially high.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87048</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Hosts Virtual Workshop on Predatory Pricing</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-hosts-virtual-workshop-predatory-pricing</link>
  <description>&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHAT:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;The Federal Trade Commission will host a virtual public workshop, Competition Snuffed Out: How Predatory Pricing Harms Competition, Consumers, and Innovation, that will examine predatory pricing and its potential effects on consumers, competition, and innovation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHEN:&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Wednesday, December 18, 9:30 AM – 12:30 PM ET&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHERE:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;The event is free and will be held online. Registration is not required to view the webcast. The webcast can be accessed&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://kvgo.com/ftc/Competition-Snuffed-Out-How-Predatory-Pricing-Harms-Competition-Consumers-and-Innovation-Workshop"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHO:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;The public workshop will&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events/2024/12/competition-snuffed-out-how-predatory-pricing-harms-competition-consumers-innovation"&gt;feature remarks&lt;/a&gt; by FTC Chair Lina M. Khan and Commissioner Alvaro Bedoya. Economists, academics, and antitrust litigators will discuss predatory pricing caselaw and economic scholarship.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TWITTER/X:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Follow the discussion using the hashtag #PricingFTC&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">86993</guid>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
