<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:schema="http://schema.org/" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#" version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.ftc.gov/">
  <channel>
    <title>Federal Trade Commission - Protecting America's Consumers</title>
    <link>https://www.ftc.gov/</link>
    <description/>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.ftc.gov/feeds/press-release-consumer-protection.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>

    <item>
  <title>FTC Warns Operators of Websites that Charge for an Employer Identification Number and Claim Affiliation with the IRS </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/04/ftc-warns-operators-websites-charge-employer-identification-number-claim-affiliation-irs</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Federal Trade Commission staff &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/warning-letters/ein-warning-letter-template" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="6ec43d50-1092-427b-b242-35b8bdf1324d" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;sent letters&lt;/a&gt; to operators of websites that sell Employer Identification Number (EIN) filing and delivery services warning that some of their practices may violate the FTC Act and the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/04/ftc-announces-impersonation-rule-goes-effect-today"&gt;Impersonation Rule&lt;/a&gt;, which prohibit posing as or misrepresenting affiliation with a government agency. According to the letters, these services charge consumers up to $300 per EIN even though consumers can obtain EINs for free directly from the &lt;a href="https://www.irs.gov/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed/get-an-employer-identification-number"&gt;Internal Revenue Service’s (IRS) website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/FraudandIDTheftMaps/FraudbyState"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-sm"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/scaled_sm/public/u97525/badge-explore-data-fraud1.jpg?itok=_4mow1yd" width="500" height="313" alt="Consumer Fraud graphic " loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 500/313"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Impersonating the government is unlawful, period,” said Chris Mufarrige, Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection. “The FTC is warning businesses that sell services the government provides to review their websites and advertisements for symbols and words that mislead consumers.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;EINs are a type of corporate identifier similar to a Social Security Number. Consumers need EINs for a variety of reasons, including opening a business; opening estates upon the death of a loved one or family member; opening a non-profit organization; and hiring a household employee, such a nanny.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to consumer complaints, some of the practices that EIN filing and delivery services use to imply an affiliation with the IRS include:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;using seals, logos, imagery, layouts, formatting, colors, and fonts similar to the IRS on their websites and in ads that lead to their websites;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;using the acronym “IRS” in their domain names;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;prominently displaying the terms “IRS” or “EIN Assistant” (the name the IRS uses for its &lt;a href="https://sa.www4.irs.gov/modiein/individual/index.jsp"&gt;free EIN application tool&lt;/a&gt;); and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;failing to clearly and conspicuously disclose that their websites are not the IRS’s site nor a government website.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumers also say that the EIN filing and delivery services websites do not adequately disclose that the several hundred dollars they charge are entirely service fees because the IRS provides EINs for free.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The letters note that violations of the FTC Act and the Impersonation Rule may result in legal action. In addition, companies or individuals violating the Impersonation Rule can face civil penalties of up to $53,088 per violation and may be required to provide refunds to defrauded consumers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, the letters state that while the Commission is not suggesting recipients have broken the law, they should conduct a comprehensive review of their marketing and advertising practices – including paid or other online ads, as well as representations made on their websites, social media, or in other promotional materials – to ensure they are complying with the law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the past two years, the FTC has brought law enforcement actions to protect consumers from similar deceptive conduct, including &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-acts-stop-scheme-bilked-millions-out-student-loan-borrowers"&gt;FTC v. Superior Servicing LLC&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/06/ftc-acts-stop-student-loan-debt-relief-scheme-took-millions-consumers-first-case-under-impersonation"&gt;FTC v. Panda Benefit Services, LLC&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2018/03/operators-dotauthoritycom-motor-carrier-registration-service-settle-ftc-charges-they-misled-small"&gt;FTC v. DOTAuthority.com, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;; and &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2018/10/american-immigration-center-settles-ftc-government-imposter-allegations"&gt;FTC v. Forms Direct, Inc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>mkatz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87983</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title> Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson Issues Letter on 23andMe Bankruptcy Impact to Consumers</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/federal-trade-commission-chairman-andrew-n-ferguson-issues-letter-23andme-bankruptcy-impact</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N Ferguson issued a letter to the U.S. Trustee regarding the 23andMe bankruptcy proceeding, expressing the concerns American consumers have with the potential sale or transfer of their 23andMe data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Many Americans are concerned about the impact of a potential sale of their personal data, and I understand those concerns,” said Chairman Ferguson. “Consumers should be able to trust that companies will keep their promises, including when it comes to handling of sensitive information.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The full text of Chairman Ferguson’s letter can be found &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/legal-library/browse/cases-proceedings/staff-letters/chairman-ferguson-letter-regarding-23andme" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="30b6a968-ee39-4bdd-8ce4-b559b70b7584" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87969</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Names Additional Defendants in Student Loan Debt Relief Case </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-names-additional-defendants-student-loan-debt-relief-case</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission named five additional corporate defendants and two individuals in its ongoing case against&amp;nbsp;a student loan debt relief operation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In November 2024,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-acts-stop-scheme-bilked-millions-out-student-loan-borrowers"&gt;the FTC filed its initial complaint against Nevada-based Superior Servicing&lt;/a&gt; and its operator, Dennise Merdjanian,&amp;nbsp;alleging they pretended to be affiliated with the U.S. Department of Education and falsely promised student loan forgiveness, taking millions from student loan borrowers. In November, a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/superior_servicing_tro.pdf"&gt;federal court temporarily halted the scheme and froze its assets&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;at the request of the FTC, which is seeking a permanent ban on the defendants’ deceptive practices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/superiorservicing_first_amedneded_complaint.pdf"&gt;amended complaint&lt;/a&gt; adds corporate defendants&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;Sunrise Solutions USA LLC, Alumni Advantage LLC, Student Processing Center Group LLC, SPCTWO LLC, Accredit LLC &lt;/strong&gt;and individual defendants Eric Caldwell and David Hernandez, alleging they work with Merdjanian to operate an unlawful debt relief operation through a maze of shifting corporate entities that prey on consumers with student loan debt. According to the complaint, the defendants falsely claim that they can help consumers erase their student-loan debt. In reality, the defendants take hundreds of dollars from consumers in illegal advance payments in exchange for virtually nothing, often leaving consumers even further in debt.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote authorizing the staff to file the second amended complaint was 4-0. The complaint was filed in the U.S. District Court for the District of Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87967</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Cash Advance Company Cleo AI Agrees to Pay $17 Million As Result of FTC Lawsuit Charging It Deceives Consumers</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/cash-advance-company-cleo-ai-agrees-pay-17-million-result-ftc-lawsuit-charging-it-deceives-consumers</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Online cash advance company Cleo AI has agreed to pay $17 million to settle the Federal Trade Commission’s allegations that the company deceived consumers about how much money they could get and how fast that money could be available. The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/cleo_ai_redacted_complaint_2025.03.27.pdf"&gt;complaint&lt;/a&gt;, filed in federal district court along with the proposed &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/cleo_order_-_executed_-_for_press_release.pdf"&gt;settlement order&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;also alleges that Cleo made it difficult for consumers to cancel Cleo’s subscription service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The Complaint lays out how Cleo misled consumers with promises of fast money, but consumers found they received much less than the advertised hundreds of dollars promised, had to pay more for same day delivery, and then had difficulty canceling,” said Christopher Mufarrige, Director of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complaint charges that:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cleo’s ads promised consumers access to hundreds of dollars in cash advances, but almost no one received anything close to the advertised amounts.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cleo’s ads promised consumers access to same-day or instant advances. In reality, subscribers had to pay an additional fee for this service. And even after paying the fee, they could have to wait until the next day for their money.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cleo made it difficult for consumers to cancel subscriptions. Consumers said they were charged monthly fees despite repeated requests to cancel, and were told they could not cancel their subscription until outstanding cash advances were paid.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;One consumer cited in the complaint said, “There’s no other way for me to say it. I need my money right now to pay my rent. I have no other option I can’t wait 3 days. I can’t wait 1 day I need it now. I would never have used Cleo if I would have thought I would ever be in this situation.”&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Another consumer said, “I just subscribed and paid for IMMEDIATE 35 dollars. Now I go on here and it says up to 24 hrs. I have my son today and he needs food and I need gas to go get it. I can’t wait 24 hours, or I wouldn’t have bothered.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The proposed settlement order would prohibit Cleo from misleading consumers about any material terms of its advances, including the amount of money available to a consumer and any fees consumers will be charged. It would require Cleo to clearly and conspicuously disclose the terms of any subscription; to get consumers’ express, informed consent before charging them for a subscription; and provide a simple way for consumers to cancel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The $17 million payment from Cleo would be used to provide refunds to consumers harmed by the company’s practices.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote authorizing the staff to file the complaint and stipulated final order was 2-0. The FTC filed the complaint and proposed settlement order in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of New York.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission files a complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the named defendants are violating or are about to violate the law and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest. Stipulated final orders have the force of law when approved and signed by the District Court judge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff attorneys on this matter are Adam Saltzman and Sally Tieu of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87670</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title> FTC Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson Appoints Deputy Directors of the Bureaus of Competition and Consumer Protection</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-chairman-andrew-n-ferguson-appoints-deputy-directors-bureaus-competition-consumer-protection</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson today announced he has appointed Taylor C. Hoogendoorn as Deputy Director of the Bureau of Competition and Katherine White as Deputy Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hoogendoorn is a talented litigator with expertise in a wide range of litigation, including antitrust, tort, contractual, energy, and intellectual property matters. Hoogendoorn joins the FTC after spending time in private practice at a law firm in Houston. He clerked for the Hon. Samuel A. Alito Jr. on the Supreme Court of the United States; the Hon. Gregory G. Katsas on the United States Court of Appeals for the D.C. Circuit; and the Hon. J. Harvie Wilkinson III on the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hoogendoorn holds a J.D. from Yale Law School, where he won the Morris Tyler Moot Court of Appeals and served on the Yale Law Journal, and a B.B.A. with majors in Economics, Finance, Mathematics, and Business Fellows from Baylor University. While at Baylor, he served on the university’s Board of Regents and graduated as the top-ranked student in the Hankamer School of Business.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;White is an experienced privacy and consumer protection attorney, with a career in both government service and private practice. White has deep experience in all aspects of consumer protection law and has led complex investigations relating to privacy, data security, and credit reporting.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most recently, White was a partner at a law firm. Prior to joining the firm, White spent nearly 15 years at the FTC and served in a variety of roles, including as an Attorney Advisor to former Commissioner Noah Phillips during the first Trump administration, Counsel to the Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection, and as a senior attorney in the Division of Privacy and Identity Protection. In addition, White worked on detail for the Senate Commerce Committee where she provided advice on a range of consumer protection issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;She is a graduate of the George Washington University Law School and the University of Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87662</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC to Hold Workshop on May 28 on The Attention Economy: How Big Tech Firms Exploit Children and Hurt Families </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-hold-workshop-may-28-attention-economy-how-big-tech-firms-exploit-children-hurt-families</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, the Federal Trade Commission announced a workshop entitled "The Attention Economy: How Big Tech Firms Exploit Children and Hurt Families." The workshop will be held on May 28th at the Federal Trade Commission in Washington, D.C. and streamed online.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event will bring together parents, and child safety experts, and government leaders to discuss how Big Tech companies impose addictive design features, erode parental authority, and fail to protect children from exposure to harmful content. Experts will also discuss concrete solutions to protect kids online, including age verification and parental consent requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Protecting kids online is a priority of the Trump-Vance FTC – and hosting this workshop will make that very clear,” said FTC Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson. “I look forward to hearing from some of the leading policy experts in this space as we continue to explore ways the FTC can support families.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The event will begin at 9 a.m. ET at the FTC’s headquarters at 600 Pennsylvania Ave, NW, Washington, D.C. 20580. Registration will be required to attend in-person. Registration information will be posted to the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events/2025/05/attention-economy-tech-firms-exploit-children" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="3bc0b6c1-3fc8-403f-b51d-c1615eeca5c0" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;event page&lt;/a&gt; prior to the workshop and a link to the livestream will be posted to FTC.gov the morning of the event.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is seeking input from those who are interested in participating as panelists for the workshop or who have expertise and relevant information to provide on any of the topics listed above. If you have expertise, email&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="mailto:AttentionEconomy@ftc.gov"&gt;AttentionEconomy@ftc.gov&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;by&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;April 30, 2025&lt;/strong&gt;. The FTC is not seeking substantive comments at this time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additional information, including a list of speakers and the agenda, will be posted to the event page in advance of the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87660</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Suit Against E-Commerce Business Opportunity Scam Leads to Permanent Bans for Operators</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-suit-against-e-commerce-business-opportunity-scam-leads-permanent-bans-operators</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is requiring operators of a deceptive business opportunity to pay hundreds of thousands of dollars to settle allegations they misled consumers with false promises of big returns selling goods through Amazon and Walmart.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the settlement orders entered by the court, Trevor Duffy Young and Wessam Baiz, along with two companies associated with Baiz, will turn over the profits they made from the alleged scam, which operated under the names Lunar Capital Ventures, Ecom Genie and Profitable Automation, and before that as Valiant Consultants.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Young, Baiz, and Baiz’s companies were part of a deceptive operation that took advantage of consumers looking to invest their hard-earned money, only to learn that promises of successful e-commerce stores were a total sham,” said Christopher Mufarrige, Director of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection. “Today’s action holds these defendants accountable by banning them from marketing or selling business opportunities and requiring payments to defrauded consumers.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC filed suit in October 2024, alleging that the companies and their operators made false claims that consumers could earn large profits from online e-commerce stores that the defendants would establish and operate for them. For example, they promised that consumers would generate sales of “$100K+ per month” and that their stores could become “million-dollar” operations. These promises rarely, if ever, materialized, and most consumers lost the tens of thousands of dollars they each invested in the business opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The court orders ban Young, Baiz, and Baiz’s companies from any involvement with the sales, marketing, or operations of any business opportunity. The orders also prohibit them from deceiving consumers about any good or service they sell or market.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The order against&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/84-StipulatedOrder-BaizSalespreneursBaizSales.pdf"&gt;Baiz and his companies, Baiz Sales and Salespreneurs&lt;/a&gt;, requires them to turn over assets held by the court-appointed receiver in the case along with the contents of numerous bank accounts to the FTC. The order contains a total monetary judgment of $13,988,712, which is largely suspended based on an inability to pay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The order against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/83-StipulatedOrder-TrevorDuffyYoung_0.pdf"&gt;Young&lt;/a&gt; requires him to turn over the contents of several bank accounts to the FTC. The order contains a monetary judgment of $6,024,211, which is largely suspended based on an inability to pay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If any of the defendants are found to have lied to the FTC about their financial status, the full monetary judgment against them would be immediately payable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s case against the remaining defendants, who are currently subject to preliminary injunctions issued by the court that shuttered their operations, is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote approving the stipulated final orders was&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;4-0. The FTC filed the proposed order&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of Florida. The Court approved the final orders on March 19.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff attorneys on this matter are Sara Tonnesen and Molly Rucki of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87654</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Acts to Stop ‘Click Profit’ Online Business Opportunity that Has Cost Consumers At Least $14 Million</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-acts-stop-click-profit-online-business-opportunity-has-cost-consumers-least-14-million</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;At the request of the Federal Trade Commission, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/ClickforProfit-20250305-TRO.pdf"&gt;a federal court temporarily halted&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;a business opportunity scheme known as Click Profit, which took millions from consumers by falsely promising consumers that they could earn big profits through online sales.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a complaint, &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/ClickProfit-20250303-Complaint.pdf"&gt;the FTC alleged&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;that Click Profit and its owners deceived consumers by promising they could make large sums in “passive income” using a proprietary system powered by artificial intelligence. The system supposedly enables consumers to sell goods through online platforms such as Amazon, Walmart, and TikTok. Click Profit also deceived consumers by claiming to be affiliated with major companies like Nike and Disney as a ploy to convince consumers to turn over tens of thousands of dollars each, according to the complaint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Click Profit misled consumers by falsely promising them guaranteed passive income using cutting-edge AI technology and exclusive brand partnerships,” said Christopher Mufarrige, Director of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection. “Their deception caused individual consumers to lose tens of thousands of dollars while the Click Profit’s operators enriched themselves. The FTC is working to hold the defendants accountable and secure redress for their victims, who have collectively lost millions of dollars.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In its ads, Click Profit, which also does business under the names FBALaunch, Automation Industries, and PortfolioLaunch, claimed that the business opportunity was “safe, secure, and proven to generate wealth,” and that consumers could expect profits outperforming traditional investments in ways that were consistent and predictable, according to the complaint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure role="group"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/images/clickprofit-image-press-release-embed.jpg"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-xs"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/styles/ftc_scaled_tiny_250_/private/ftc_gov/images/clickprofit-image-press-release-embed.jpg?itok=jkoy8lbo" width="250" height="452" alt="Click Profit, LLC image" title="If earning passive income from Ecommerce was illegal - Click Profit, LLC advertisement" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 250/452"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Click Profit, LLC social media advertisement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers who purchased the company’s business opportunity were charged a “management fee” of at least $45,000, in addition to thousands of dollars more, purportedly to buy inventory for their stores. The complaint alleges that few of these consumers see a return on their investments, much less the promised earnings. In fact, most consumers lose their entire payments, and some are saddled with burdensome credit card debt and unsold products.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Click Profit’s online advertising on social media and search ads emphasized that consumers could expect to earn six-to-eight figure income from their online storefront. According to the complaint, co-founder Craig Emslie appeared in advertisements fanning himself with wads of cash to emphasize the point of how much money consumers could expect to make.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the complaint, Click Profit promoted alleged testimonials from customers who made huge profits. At the same time, the company’s ads claimed that it could guarantee such income, and even implied that consumers’ online store could be bought out by venture capital firms connected with the company “at a 3-6x multiple.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complaint highlights actual statistics on Click Profit’s stores, which are mainly on Amazon, showing that after Amazon’s fees, more than one-fifth of the company’s stores on the platform earn no money at all and another third earns less than $2,500 in gross lifetime sales. After factoring in Click Profit’s own startup fees, ongoing charges, and “profit share” fees, most consumers are never able to recoup the costs of starting a store, much less earn the profits promised by the company.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, the complaint alleges that Click Profit often takes months to open consumers’ stores, and in some cases has not opened stores at all. Even when Click Profit does open a store for consumers, the complaint alleges, many of these online stores are blocked or suspended by the selling platform. According to the complaint, Amazon has blocked, suspended, or terminated about 95% of Click Profit’s stores. In instances where consumers’ stores begin to generate revenue, Click Profit pressures the consumers into using that revenue to buy additional inventory for their stores.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumers have often found the company unresponsive after making their initial payments and fails to respond to consumer complaints, according to the complaint. Most consumers only received refunds from Click Profit after complaining to outside organizations like the BBB or law enforcement. The complaint also alleges that in many instances, Click Profit would threaten customers who filed complaints with lawsuits, citing an unlawful non-disparagement clause in the company’s contracts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s complaint charges that Click Profit, its co-founders Emslie and Patrick McGeoghean, partners Jason Masri and William Holton, and a number of associated companies have violated the FTC Act, the Business Opportunity Rule, the Consumer Review Fairness Act, and the Rule On Impersonation of Government and Businesses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote authorizing the staff to file the complaint was 4-0. The complaint was filed in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of Florida. The court entered the temporary restraining order against the company on March 5, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission files a complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the named defendants are violating or are about to violate the law and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest. The case will be decided by the court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff attorneys on this matter are Lisa W. Bohl and James Davis of the FTC’s Midwest Region.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87635</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title> New Report Shows FTC Returned $337.3 Million to Consumers in 2024</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/new-report-shows-ftc-returned-3373-million-consumers-2024</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;As a result of the agency’s law enforcement actions, the Federal Trade Commission sent $337.3 million in refunds to consumers in 2024, according to the FTC’s annual report on refunds released today.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Getting money back for people across the country is a top priority for the FTC,” said Chris Mufarrige, Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection. “We will relentlessly pursue refunds for Americans who lost money to unlawful practices.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-_3-width"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/ftc_scaled_extra_small_350_/public/u97525/explore_data_refunds_20.gif?itok=eligfPgF" width="350" height="219" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 350/219"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/reports/2024-annual-report-refunds-consumers" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="1d8f9b05-1d9e-4cf4-a70a-82961d6ddc2a" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;Annual Report on Refunds to Consumers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;provides a breakdown of the total amount refunded by the FTC nationally, as well as the amount sent to consumers in each state. The report also includes a list of cases in which the agency sent first distribution payments in 2024. For example, the agency sent $99.3 million to consumers who were charged for&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/03/ftc-sends-nearly-100-million-refunds-consumers-harmed-benefytt-technologies-sham-health-plans"&gt;sham health plans marketed by Benefytt Technologies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to providing statistics about each distribution in 2024, the report also includes information about the FTC’s refund process, including how it determines who is eligible for a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC also has interactive dashboards online with more detailed information about consumer refunds at &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/exploredata"&gt;ftc.gov/exploredata&lt;/a&gt;. The dashboards include the ability to search for the number of refunds issued by state for each case as well as breakdowns of the forms of payment used to provide refunds in various cases.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>mkatz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87622</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sends More Than $934,000 in Refunds to Consumers Harmed by Vroom’s Failed Delivery Promises</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-sends-more-934000-refunds-consumers-harmed-vrooms-failed-delivery-promises</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending more than $934,000 in refunds to consumers who were harmed by online used car dealer Vroom’s shipment delays.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/07/ftc-takes-action-against-online-used-car-dealer-vroom-deceiving-customers-failing-deliver-time"&gt;FTC charged in July 2024 that Vroom&lt;/a&gt; failed to follow the Mail, Internet, and Telephone Order Rule, the Pre-Sale Availability Rule, and the Used Car Rule. The FTC’s complaint alleged the company misrepresented that it thoroughly examined all vehicles before listing them for sale and failed to obtain consumers’ consent to shipment delays or provide prompt refunds to consumers when cars weren’t delivered in the time promised. The complaint also alleged that Vroom violated the Used Car Rule by not providing consumers the Buyers Guide until late in the purchase process and that the guides were often missing required information. Finally, the complaint alleged that Vroom also failed to provide warranty information required by law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-_3-width"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/ftc_scaled_extra_small_350_/public/u97525/explore_data_refunds_20.gif?itok=eligfPgF" width="350" height="219" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 350/219"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is using money obtained from a settlement with Vroom, also announced in July 2024,&amp;nbsp;to compensate consumers affected by Vroom’s failed delivery promises. The settlement order also prohibits the company from further misleading consumers about inspections or shipping and requires Vroom to provide required disclosures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is sending checks to 20,361 affected consumers. Recipients should cash their checks within 90 days, as indicated on the check. Consumers who have questions about their payment should contact the refund administrator, Simpluris, at 866-675-2533, or visit the FTC website to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/recent-ftc-cases-resulting-refunds/refund-programs-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;view frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt; about the refund process. The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to get a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt; provide a state-by-state breakdown of refunds in FTC cases. In 2024, FTC actions led to more than $337 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87617</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sends More Than $15.5 Million in Refunds to Consumers Affected by Career Step’s Deceptive Job Placement and Employer Partnerships Claims</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-sends-more-155-million-refunds-consumers-affected-career-steps-deceptive-job-placement-employer</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending more than $15.5 million in refunds to consumers, including servicemembers and their spouses, lured by online career-training company&amp;nbsp;Career Step’s deceptive ads and false claims about its training programs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;FTC &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/07/career-step-pay-435-million-cash-debt-cancellation-resolve-charges-it-used-deceptive-advertising"&gt;alleged that Career Step, LLC&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;targeted servicemembers and their spouses using false claims about job placement and career outcomes, externships, and hiring partnerships with prominent companies. The company used deceptive incentivized reviews to promote its services and marketed its services through military-focused publications, such as Military.com, and events sponsored by the military, the FTC alleged.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-_3-width"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/ftc_scaled_extra_small_350_/public/u97525/explore_data_refunds_20.gif?itok=eligfPgF" width="350" height="219" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 350/219"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of a settlement, Career Step paid more than $15.5 million that the FTC is using to compensate some students harmed by the company’s deceptive advertising. The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/07/career-step-pay-435-million-cash-debt-cancellation-resolve-charges-it-used-deceptive-advertising"&gt;settlement also required Career Step to&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;cancel nearly $28 million in unpaid balances owed by current or former students who enrolled between February 2020 and February 2023. Other debts, such as federal and private student loans or military benefits, are not affected by this settlement. The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/CareerStep-Filed-Stipulated-Order.pdf"&gt;stipulated order also prohibits Career Step&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;from deceptively advertising any educational product or service in the future.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is sending checks and PayPal payments to 42,794 affected consumers who enrolled, and paid for training between August 7, 2018 and September 11, 2024 and who did not get debt cancellation as part of this settlement. Career Step sent letters in August 2024 to notify people who got debt cancellation. Individuals who receive a refund should cash their checks within 90 days, as indicated on the check, or redeem their PayPal payments within 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumers who have questions about their payment should contact the refund administrator, Simpluris, at 866-675-2824, or visit the FTC website to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/recent-ftc-cases-resulting-refunds/refund-programs-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;view frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt; about the refund process. The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to get a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt; provide a state-by-state breakdown of&amp;nbsp;refunds in FTC cases. In 2024, FTC actions led to more than $337 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>hbarber</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87610</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sends More than $25.5 Million to Consumers Impacted  by Tech Support Firms’ Scam</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-sends-more-255-million-consumers-impacted-tech-support-firms-scam</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending payments totaling more than $25.5 million to consumers who were tricked into signing up for computer repair services through the deceptive marketing tactics of two tech support companies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/03/tech-support-firms-will-pay-26-million-settle-ftc-charges-they-deceived-consumers-buying-repair"&gt;alleged in March 2024&lt;/a&gt; that Restoro Cyprus Limited and Reimage Cyprus Limited, both based in Cyprus, violated the FTC Act and the Telemarking Sales Rule by deceiving consumers into buying computer repair services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is returning money it obtained from the companies as part of a&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/Restoro.SignedOrder.pdf"&gt;settlement order&lt;/a&gt; with Restoro and Reimage. The order also prohibited the companies from misrepresenting security or performance issues related to the sale, marketing or distribution of any product or service, and from engaging in deceptive telemarketing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC will send 736,375 PayPal payments on March 13 and 14 to consumers who paid for computer repair services. Consumers who are eligible for a payment will get an email between now and March 13. Recipients should redeem their PayPal payment within 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div data-entity-type="block_content" data-entity-uuid="0fa652c4-baf3-48fe-9f0d-8fb3fa7044d2" data-embed-button="basic_block" data-entity-embed-display="view_mode:block_content.full" class="align-right embedded-entity" data-langcode="en" data-entity-embed-display-settings="[]"&gt;
&lt;div class="block-content block-content--type-basic block-content--840 block-content--view-mode-full"&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class="block-content__content"&gt;
    

&lt;div class="field field--name-field-body field--type-text-long field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-sm"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/scaled_sm/public/ftc_gov/images/badge-explore-data-ftc-refunds-resized.jpg?itok=Yc2wmn7d" width="390" height="244" alt="Explore Data Badge Resized" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 390/244"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers who have questions about their payment should call the redress administrator, Rust Consulting, Inc., at 844-590-1102 or visit the FTC’s website to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/recent-ftc-cases-resulting-refunds/refund-programs-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;view frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;about the refund process.&amp;nbsp;The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to submit a claim or receive a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fpublic.tableau.com%2Fapp%2Fprofile%2Ffederal.trade.commission%2Fviz%2FRefunds_15797958402020%2FRefundsbyCase&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7CMKATZ%40ftc.gov%7Cf2b61860f3594822937108dd5be8c261%7C7302cabc5af5469baf17700007935a01%7C0%7C0%7C638767777455402862%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=JFYG67nrbSP6vGIPw0jJIsahRzoYPSRkJZKW%2B2rxiyA%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt; provide a state-by-state breakdown of refunds in FTC cases. In 2024, FTC actions led to more than $337 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>mkatz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87595</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>New FTC Data Show a Big Jump in Reported Losses to Fraud to $12.5 Billion in 2024 </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/new-ftc-data-show-big-jump-reported-losses-fraud-125-billion-2024</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Newly released &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/exploredata"&gt;Federal Trade Commission data&lt;/a&gt; show that consumers reported losing more than $12.5 billion to fraud in 2024, which represents a 25% increase over the prior year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the FTC’s data book, this number is not driven by an increase in fraud reports, which remained stable. Instead, the percentage of people who reported losing money to a fraud or scam increased by double digits. In 2023, 27% of people who reported a fraud said they lost money, while in 2024, that figure jumped to 38%.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumers reported losing more money to investment scams—$5.7 billion—than any other category in 2024. That amount represents a 24% increase over 2023. The second highest reported loss amount came from imposter scams, with $2.95 billion reported lost. In 2024, consumers reported losing more money to scams where they paid with bank transfers or cryptocurrency than all other payment methods combined.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The data we’re releasing today shows that scammers’ tactics are constantly evolving,” said Christopher Mufarrige, Director of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection. “The FTC is monitoring those trends closely and working hard to protect the American people from fraud.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/images/csn-scammy-snapshot-2024.png"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-_3-width" hspace="10"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/styles/ftc_scaled_extra_small_350_/private/ftc_gov/images/csn-scammy-snapshot-2024.png?itok=F3YiIBqN" width="350" height="453" alt="A Scammy Snapshot of 2024 - Top Fraud" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 350/453"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC received fraud reports from 2.6 million consumers last year, nearly the same amount as 2023. The most commonly reported scam category was imposter scams. Losses to government imposter scams in particular increased $171 million from 2023 to a total of $789 million in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Online shopping issues were the second most commonly reported in the fraud category. This was followed by business and job opportunities, where reported losses totaled $750.6 million—up nearly $250 million from 2023.&amp;nbsp; The other most reported categories of fraud were investment-related reports and internet services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Showing major growth in recent years within business and job opportunities is the subcategory job and employment agency scams, where the number of reports tripled from 2020 to 2024, and the amount consumers reported losing to these scams jumped from $90 million to $501 million in that time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the second consecutive year, email was the most common way that consumers reported being contacted by scammers. Phone calls were the second most commonly reported contact method for fraud in 2024, followed by text messages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission monitors these trends carefully and takes a comprehensive approach to detect, halt, and deter consumer fraud.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s Consumer Sentinel Network is a database that receives reports directly from consumers, as well as from federal, state, and local law enforcement agencies, the Better Business Bureau, industry members, and non-profit organizations. More than 20 states contribute data to Sentinel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sentinel received 6.5 million reports in 2024; these include the fraud reports detailed above, as well as identity theft reports and complaints related to other consumer issues, such as problems with credit bureaus, banks and lenders. In 2024, there were more than 1.1 million reports of identity theft received through the FTC’s IdentityTheft.gov website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC uses the reports it receives through the Sentinel network as the starting point for many of its law enforcement investigations, and the agency also shares these reports with federal, state, and local law enforcement professionals across the country. While the FTC does not intervene in individual complaints, Sentinel reports are a vital part of the agency’s law enforcement mission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;People who report to ReportFraud.ftc.gov about losing money to a scam receive next steps information on how to try to recover their money. These reports are a vital part of the agency’s law enforcement mission and also help the FTC to warn consumers about fraud trends in the data.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A full breakdown of reports received in 2024 is now available on the FTC’s data analysis site at &lt;a href="https://ftc.gov/exploredata"&gt;ftc.gov/exploredata&lt;/a&gt;. These data dashboards break down the reports across a number of categories, including by state and metropolitan area, and also provide data from a number of subcategories of fraud reports. New this year is a data dashboard showing more detail on fraud reports received for &lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/FraudReports/AgeState"&gt;each state broken down by age&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 08:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87602</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Takes Action to Stop Sprawling ‘Growth Cave’ Business Opportunity and Credit Repair Scam</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-takes-action-stop-sprawling-growth-cave-business-opportunity-credit-repair-scam</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;As a result of a Federal Trade Commission lawsuit, a federal court has &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/GrowthCave-OrderGrantingExParteTRO-unsealed.pdf"&gt;temporarily halted&lt;/a&gt; the operations of a wide-ranging business opportunity and credit repair scam that has operated under the name “Growth Cave” since at least 2020.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/GrowthCave-Complaint.pdf"&gt;FTC’s complaint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;against the operation and its owners and officers, Lucas Lee-Tyson, Osmany Batte (also known as “Ozzie Blessed”), and Jordan Marksberry, alleges that the Growth Cave operation has taken approximately $50 million from consumers using false promises of huge income.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Consumers seeking to start a business deserve an honest chance—not false promises of reliable income and expert help,” said Chris Mufarrige, the FTC’s Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection. “The FTC has its eye on business opportunity schemes like this one and will take decisive action to stop them.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In videos, Lee-Tyson and Batte have claimed to be experts who have made significant money through the programs and techniques they sell and who are ready to share their supposed expertise with consumers—for a price. In these videos, Lee-Tyson portrays himself as a marketing guru and self-made millionaire. Batte, according to the complaint, implies that he contributes to Growth Cave’s success with his ability to fix negative “mindsets” and his certification in hypnosis. Lee-Tyson, Batte, and Marksberry post videos of their lavish lifestyles as proof of their programs’ earning potential, but according to the complaint those lifestyles are funded by the consumers who lost money to Growth Cave’s bogus programs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Growth Cave operation’s primary scheme is called Knowledge Business Accelerator (KBA) which, according to the complaint, is sold via YouTube ads. The KBA scheme’s central pitch to consumers is that by developing and marketing a so-called “digital education program,” consumers can “generate $20,000 to $50,000 in passive income.” In videos cited in the complaint, Lee-Tyson guaranteed to consumers that “It is literally IMPOSSIBLE to fail…”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;figure role="group"&gt;

&lt;article class="align-center media media--type-image media--view-mode-default"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/images/growth-cave.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/styles/scaled_lg/private/ftc_gov/images/growth-cave.jpg?itok=y7CnbN9G" width="500" height="338" alt="Screenshot from Growth Cave video" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 500/338"&gt;

&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;

&lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot from Growth Cave video&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the complaint, consumers who reach out to learn more about the KBA program are hit with email marketing that reinforces the videos’ deceptive messages and are pushed to watch more videos and schedule a “strategy call” with a Growth Cave employee, where they are told they will begin making money within four to six weeks. Consumers report that Growth Cave offers them a $10,000 profit guarantee that they are told will ensure they recoup the money they spend to buy the KBA business opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the complaint, Consumers pay thousands of dollars each for the KBA program, but soon after learn that Growth Cave’s promises are empty. The complaint alleges that consumers had trouble reaching Growth Cave employees and obtaining promised assistance. Consumers report that Growth Cave did not develop customized advertisements and instead provided KBA purchasers with generic scripts, which KBA purchasers had to spend significant time revising before recording their own advertisements. Even after completing previously undisclosed “requirements” from Growth Cave to launch their courses, many consumers reported that they were unable to earn the promised income.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scheme’s operators also pushed an “upgraded” version of the KBA program, called Digital Freedom Mastermind (DFM), in which all of the work to create an educational course is supposedly completed by Growth Cave on consumers’ behalf, at a cost of an additional $30,000 to $50,000. Consumers who purchased this supposed upgrade reported that the promised services never materialized.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the complaint, in most cases, KBA purchasers, including those who pay for the DFM upsell, do not make a single sale and therefore do not earn any income. Instead, they find themselves owing thousands of dollars to Growth Cave, credit card companies, or third-party lenders, prompting numerous consumer complaints.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the complaint, Lee-Tyson and Batte also sold another business opportunity scheme called the Cashflow Consultant Academy (CCA), which promised to teach purchasers to close new sales for “wealthy business owners” and guaranteed that it would place participants with one of Growth Cave’s “business owner clients,” leading to tens of thousands of dollars in monthly income. According to the complaint, the people who endorse the program in video advertisements talking about their own successes are all Growth Cave employees—but this is never disclosed. Real consumers have regularly complained that, after paying as much as $6,800 for the CCA opportunity, instead of being placed with a business owner as promised, they often are never placed with any client at all. In the rare instances where a consumer is “placed,” consumers report that, instead of a “wealthy business owner,” their client is just a consumer who is embroiled in Growth Cave’s KBA scheme. Most CCA purchasers never earn any income or profit.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the complaint, Growth Cave also established a bogus credit repair scheme in 2023 called Buffalo Bridge, aimed at consumers who had purchased the company’s other bogus schemes. Buffalo Bridge claimed to provide credit repair services and 0% interest business loans, but in reality, consumers report, it merely signed up consumers for multiple business credit cards. The complaint alleges that Growth Cave unlawfully charged consumers $6,800 upfront for this supposed service.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even after facing multiple private lawsuits from consumers who lost money to their schemes, the complaint alleges, Lee-Tyson and Batte have continued pitching new business opportunity schemes. After announcing a “rebrand” in March 2024, Lee-Tyson started selling a supposed AI-fueled program called PassiveApps, which, according to the complaint, follows the same blueprint as KBA, with supposed full-service upgrades available for thousands of dollars. The complaint alleges that Lee-Tyson even deceptively re-uses the exact same “testimonials” provided by KBA purchasers to advertise PassiveApps.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the complaint, Batte is pitching a service similar to CCA called ApexMind and is recycling many of the same deceptive tactics, including the prior bogus testimonials, according to the complaint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s complaint charges that the defendants have violated the FTC Act, the Business Opportunity Rule, the Credit Repair Organizations Act and the Reviews and Testimonials Rule.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The Commission vote authorizing the staff to file the complaint was 4-0-1, with then-Commissioner Lina M. Khan not participating. The complaint was filed in the U.S. District Court for the Central District of California.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission files a complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the named defendants are violating or are about to violate the law and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest. The case will be decided by the court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff attorneys on this matter are Maris Snell and Adrienne Jenkins of the FTC’s East Central Region and Miles Freeman of the FTC’s Western Region Los Angeles.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Mar 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87591</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sends Refunds to Consumers Deceived by Pure Green Coffee Weight Loss Ads </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-sends-refunds-consumers-deceived-pure-green-coffee-weight-loss-ads</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending more than $905,000 in refunds to consumers who bought Pure Green Coffee, a sham weight loss product marketed using false health claims, bogus testimonials, and fake news websites by NPB Advertising.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;FTC sued&amp;nbsp;NPB Advertising, its principals and related companies in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2014/05/ftc-charges-green-coffee-bean-sellers-deceiving-consumers-through-fake-news-sites-bogus-weight-loss"&gt;May 2014&lt;/a&gt;. The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/documents/cases/150205npbaamendedcmpt.pdf"&gt;2015 amended complaint&lt;/a&gt; charged them with deceptively promoting Pure Green Coffee.&amp;nbsp;Most of the defendants&amp;nbsp;settled the FTC’s charges in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2015/11/ftc-brings-action-stop-marketer-making-deceptive-opiate-addiction-withdrawal-treatment-claims"&gt;November 2015&lt;/a&gt;. The FTC won its suit against the ringleader of the operation in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2016/11/ftc-wins-summary-judgment-against-pitchman-deceptive-green-coffee-weight-loss-ads-30-million"&gt;November 2016&lt;/a&gt;, and engaged in extensive efforts to collect on the judgment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div data-entity-type="block_content" data-entity-uuid="0fa652c4-baf3-48fe-9f0d-8fb3fa7044d2" data-embed-button="basic_block" data-entity-embed-display="view_mode:block_content.full" class="align-right embedded-entity" data-langcode="en" data-entity-embed-display-settings="[]"&gt;
&lt;div class="block-content block-content--type-basic block-content--840 block-content--view-mode-full"&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class="block-content__content"&gt;
    

&lt;div class="field field--name-field-body field--type-text-long field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-sm"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/scaled_sm/public/ftc_gov/images/badge-explore-data-ftc-refunds-resized.jpg?itok=Yc2wmn7d" width="390" height="244" alt="Explore Data Badge Resized" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 390/244"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FTC is sending&amp;nbsp;checks and PayPal payments to 39,977&amp;nbsp;affected consumers. Recipients should cash their checks within 90 days, as indicated on the check, or redeem their PayPal payments within 30 days.&amp;nbsp;Consumers who have questions about their payment should contact the refund administrator, Epiq Systems, at&amp;nbsp;877-839-1696, or visit the FTC’s website to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/recent-ftc-cases-resulting-refunds/refund-programs-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;view frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt; about the refund process. The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to get a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s &lt;a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fpublic.tableau.com%2Fapp%2Fprofile%2Ffederal.trade.commission%2Fviz%2FRefunds_15797958402020%2FRefundsbyCase&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7Cndrayton%40ftc.gov%7C0942f5ffffd74d7c043008dd5bed18e2%7C7302cabc5af5469baf17700007935a01%7C0%7C0%7C638767796073708850%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=uLzlkm3eObKqQDn6mk7mZLXFDAoG8yLMhMQvE6cnncQ%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt; provide a state-by-state breakdown of refunds in FTC cases. In 2024, FTC actions led to more than $337 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>ndrayton</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87585</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Secures Initial Win in Small Business Finance Scheme Case Against Seek Capital  </title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-secures-initial-win-small-business-finance-scheme-case-against-seek-capital</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission secured an initial win in its case against Seek Capital and the company’s founder and CEO, Roy Ferman, after the U.S. Court for the Central District of California granted the FTC’s motion for a preliminary injunction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Under the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/50.PIOrderGrant.pdf"&gt;preliminary injunction granted&lt;/a&gt; by the district court, Seek Capital is prohibited from making false claims related to small business loans or lines of credit and is forbidden from contacting any consumers whose information the company obtained before February 20, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/11/ftc-takes-action-against-bogus-business-finance-scheme-seek-capital-costing-small-business-owners"&gt;FTC’s complaint&lt;/a&gt; filed in November 2024, Seek Capital targets new and aspiring small business owners looking for loans or lines of credit to open or grow their businesses. The company falsely advertises that it can secure business loans or lines of credit and instead charges clients thousands of dollars simply to open credit cards in the owners’ names. These actions have cost small business owners more than $37 million.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The district court granted the FTC’s motion for a preliminary injunction on February 20, 2025, finding that the FTC was likely to succeed on the merits of all its claims. The court entered the FTC’s proposed order in full and found that the requested relief was necessary and appropriate given that Seek Capital and Ferman were continuing to collect on invoices to consumers who “fell victim to their deceptive scheme.” The court found that the injunction was necessary to mitigate harm pending trial.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff attorneys on this matter are Maya Sequeira, Katherine Worthman, and Laura Antonini of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87572</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Action Leads to Court Order Halting Phantom Debt Collection Scheme That Took Millions from Consumers and Threatened Consumers’ Credit, Homes, and Employment</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/03/ftc-action-leads-court-order-halting-phantom-debt-collection-scheme-took-millions-consumers</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;As a result of a Federal Trade Commission lawsuit, a federal court has &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/Blackstone-TRO.pdf"&gt;temporarily halted&lt;/a&gt; the operations and frozen the assets of a phantom debt collection scheme and its operators. The scheme has operated under numerous names, including Blackrock Services, Blackstone Legal Group, Capital Legal Services, Quest Legal Group, Viking Legal Services, and others.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;According to the &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/Blackstone-Complaint.pdf"&gt;FTC’s complaint&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;the operators of this scheme are Ryan and Mitchell Evans and their affiliated companies. Debt collectors working for the scheme’s operators and their affiliated companies have sent consumers deceptive warning and collection letters or called them directly, claiming that consumers owed a debt of some kind and threatening legal action, wage garnishment, negative impacts to consumers’ credit, and even arrest if they don’t pay. The debts described in these letters and calls never existed, according to the complaint, and the defendants have no basis to make legal threats toward consumers.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The complaint further alleges that the defendants have sent letters and made phone calls to consumers claiming they owed money to a payday lender, and that the purported “law firm” contacting the consumer will imminently be filing suit against the consumer if the consumer does not pay up. The letters and calls also claim that consumers’ credit will be damaged by the fictitious debt, and that if consumers agree to pay to settle that debt, the harm to their credit could be lessened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;All of the claims in these letters and calls are false, according to the complaint.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The complaint notes that the letters sent by the operators often contain a wealth of sensitive personal information about the consumer, including the last four digits of their Social Security number, leading consumers to believe the letter may be legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When consumers visit the websites set up by the defendants for the bogus debt collection companies, they are again faced with false warnings that failure to pay these fake debts could result in garnishment of the consumer’s wages, along with lawsuits and impacts to their credit. In follow-up calls, the threats increase, with collectors falsely telling consumers that they have defrauded a financial institution, could be arrested at their workplace, or that their homes could be seized if they do not settle, according to the complaint.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;According to the complaint, the scheme has operated under a wide variety of names, including the names of unaffiliated existing businesses and law firms, in violation of the FTC’s Rule on Impersonating Government and Businesses. In addition, the complaint alleges that the defendants have regularly failed to follow numerous requirements set out by the Fair Debt Collection Practices Act, including disclosing that they are debt collectors when their collectors contact consumers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC’s complaint asks the court to stop the defendants’ unlawful conduct and provide redress to consumers harmed by the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote authorizing the staff to file the complaint was 4-0. The complaint was filed in the U.S. District Court for the Central District of California.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;The Commission files a complaint when it has “reason to believe” that the named defendants are violating or are about to violate the law and it appears to the Commission that a proceeding is in the public interest. The case will be decided by the court.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff attorneys on this matter are Quinn Martin and Jason Sanders of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87563</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Launches Joint Labor Task Force to Protect American Workers</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-launches-joint-labor-task-force-protect-american-workers</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson directed the FTC to form a Joint Labor Task Force that will work to prioritize rooting out and prosecuting deceptive, unfair, and anticompetitive labor-market practices that harm American workers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pursuant to a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/public-statements/directive-regarding-labor-markets-task-force" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="97c63754-8479-4869-8b1d-c843ad055af3" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;memorandum&lt;/a&gt; issued by Chairman Ferguson, the FTC’s Bureau of Competition, Bureau of Consumer Protection, Bureau of Economics, and Office of Policy Planning are directed to work together to carry out a variety of responsibilities. The task force will focus on, for example, prioritizing investigations and prosecutions of deceptive, unfair, or anticompetitive labor market conduct and coordinating all such actions across the Bureaus, creating information-sharing protocols across the FTC’s Bureaus and offices to exchange best practices for uncovering and investigating such conduct, and promoting research regarding harmful labor market practices to inform the FTC and the public.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A healthy labor market is critical to the country’s success. But deceptive, unfair, and anticompetitive labor practices are widespread. They negatively affect workers across all types of industries by limiting their mobility and ability to earn a living. Such harmful practices come in a variety of forms. For example, the Chairman’s directive highlights no-poach, non-solicitation, or no-hire agreements, noncompete agreements, wage-fixing agreements, deceptive job advertising such as misleading earnings claims, deceptive business opportunities, misleading franchise offerings, and collusion or unlawful coordination on DEI employment metrics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Chairman’s directive seeks to harmonize the FTC’s law-enforcement efforts on behalf of workers to ensure that the FTC prioritizes labor issues in both its consumer-protection and competition matters.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>vgraham</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87551</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Announces Refund Claims Process for Avast Customers Impacted by Deceptive Privacy Claims</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-announces-refund-claims-process-avast-customers-impacted-deceptive-privacy-claims</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending claim forms to consumers who bought deceptively marketed antivirus software from Avast.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/02/ftc-order-will-ban-avast-selling-browsing-data-advertising-purposes-require-it-pay-165-million-over" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="b1825251-6092-4c21-b129-ab7f7568aef6" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;FTC&amp;nbsp;alleged&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;in a February 2024 complaint that Avast deceived users by claiming that its software would protect consumers’ privacy by blocking third party tracking, but it failed to adequately inform consumers that it would collect and sell their detailed, re-identifiable browsing data. The FTC alleged Avast sold that data to more than 100 third parties through its subsidiary, Jumpshot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of a settlement order with the FTC, Avast was required to pay $16.5 million, which will be used to compensate consumers. The order also bans Avast from misrepresenting how it uses the data it collects and from selling or licensing any browsing data from Avast-branded products to third parties for advertising purposes, along with other requirements.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is emailing notices to 3,690,813 consumers who bought antivirus software from Avast between August 2014 and January 2020. Consumers who are eligible to apply will get an email notice between now and March 7, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Eligible consumers can file a claim online at &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/Avast"&gt;www.ftc.gov/Avast&lt;/a&gt;. Payment amounts will depend on several factors, including how many people file claims.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The deadline for filing a claim is June 5, 2025. Consumers who have questions or need help filing a claim should call the claims administrator at 866-290-0165 or email &lt;a href="mailto:info@AvastSettlement.com"&gt;info@AvastSettlement.com&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to submit a claim or receive a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;provide a state-by-state breakdown of refunds in FTC cases. In 2024,&amp;nbsp;FTC actions led to more than&amp;nbsp;$285 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>rkern</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87527</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Secures Court Order Barring Gravity Defyer and its Owner  from Making Unsupported Pain-Relief Claims to Market Company’s Footwear</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-secures-court-order-barring-gravity-defyer-its-owner-making-unsupported-pain-relief-claims</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Gravity Defyer Medical Technology Corporation (Gravity Defyer) and its owner Alexander Elnekaveh will have to stop making alleged deceptive pain-relief claims for Gravity Defyer footwear, under a settlement with the Federal Trade Commission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The federal order also requires Elnekaveh to pay a $175,000 civil penalty for allegedly &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2001/11/super-fuelmax-marketers-settle-ftc-charges"&gt;violating a prior Commission order&lt;/a&gt; barring him from deceptive advertising.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;California-based Gravity Defyer advertised their Gravity Defyer footwear as containing soles with “VersoShock” technology that supposedly relieves pain, including pain from numerous medical conditions, according to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/06/federal-trade-commission-sues-gravity-defyer-its-owner-violating-ftc-order-making-baseless-pain-relief-claims"&gt;FTC’s complaint&lt;/a&gt;. The complaint alleged the ads claimed, without adequate scientific evidence, that Gravity Defyer footwear:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;will relieve pain, including knee, back and foot pain;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;will relieve pain in people suffering from multiple conditions such as plantar fasciitis, arthritis, joint pain, and heel spurs; and&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;was clinically proven to relieve pain, including 85% less knee pain, 91% less back pain, 92% less ankle pain, and 75% less foot pain.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC alleged that Elnekaveh’s conduct violated&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2005/05/bogus-fuel-saving-device-sellers-settle-ftc-charges"&gt;a 2001 order barring him from such allegedly deceptive advertising&lt;/a&gt; by making scientifically unsupported claims and using misleading consumer testimonials to sell Gravity Defyer products.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/Doc33-StipulatedOrder%28signedbyJMoss%29.pdf"&gt;stipulated order&lt;/a&gt; settling the complaint bars&amp;nbsp;Gravity Defyer and Elnekaveh&amp;nbsp;from making pain relief claims or claims that a device will cure, mitigate, or treat any disease unless they have competent and reliable scientific evidence to back up the claims, including human clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The order further prohibits&amp;nbsp;Gravity Defyer and Elnekaveh from making health, efficacy, and safety claims about other products unless they are supported by scientific evidence, bars them from misrepresenting the results of any test, study, or research, and requires them to preserve certain scientific records related to human clinical studies.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, the order imposes a $175,000 civil penalty against Elnekaveh. He must also notify retailers selling Gravity Defyer footwear of the Commission’s order.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote approving the stipulated final order was 5-0. The FTC filed the proposed order in the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia and it has now been entered by the judge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The staff attorneys on this matter are&amp;nbsp;Maria Del Monaco, Derek Diaz, Adrienne Jenkins, and Matthew Scheff of the FTC’s East Central Region.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>mkatz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87514</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Federal Trade Commission Launches Inquiry on Tech Censorship</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/federal-trade-commission-launches-inquiry-tech-censorship</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, the Federal Trade Commission launched a public inquiry to better understand how technology platforms deny or degrade users’ access to services based on the content of their speech or affiliations, and how this conduct may have violated the law.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Censorship by technology platforms is not just un-American, it is potentially illegal. Tech firms can employ confusing or unpredictable internal procedures that cut users off, sometimes with no ability appeal the decision. Such actions taken by tech platforms may harm consumers, affect competition, may have resulted from a lack of competition, or may have been the product of anti-competitive conduct.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC issued a &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/P251203CensorshipRFI.pdf"&gt;Request for Information (RFI)&lt;/a&gt; requesting &lt;a href="https://www.regulations.gov/docket/FTC-2025-0023/document"&gt;public comment&lt;/a&gt; on how consumers may have been harmed by technology platforms that limited their ability to share ideas or affiliations freely and openly.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Tech firms should not be bullying their users,” said FTC Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson. “This inquiry will help the FTC better understand how these firms may have violated the law by silencing and intimidating Americans for speaking their minds.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tech platform users who have been banned, shadow banned, demonetized, or otherwise censored are encouraged to share their comments in response to the RFI. The FTC is interested in understanding how consumers—including by potentially unfair or deceptive acts or practices, or potentially unfair methods of competition—have been harmed by the policies of tech firms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The public will have until May 21, 2025 to &lt;a href="https://www.regulations.gov/docket/FTC-2025-0023/document"&gt;submit a comment&lt;/a&gt;. Once submitted, comments will be posted to Regulations.gov. If consumers would prefer to file a private report with the FTC instead, they can go to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://gcc02.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Freportfraud.ftc.gov%2F&amp;amp;data=05%7C02%7Cjhenderson2%40ftc.gov%7Cbbcdb33a908b472e0b9b08dd51cac936%7C7302cabc5af5469baf17700007935a01%7C0%7C0%7C638756653585499846%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJFbXB0eU1hcGkiOnRydWUsIlYiOiIwLjAuMDAwMCIsIlAiOiJXaW4zMiIsIkFOIjoiTWFpbCIsIldUIjoyfQ%3D%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;amp;sdata=fxah%2FqaiTMUWwLc0dCmr%2BYUDcrCJ%2FuL8DBCwHqRRHnk%3D&amp;amp;reserved=0"&gt;ReportFraud.ftc.gov&lt;/a&gt; and click “Report Now.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87524</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sends More Than $19.8 Million in Refunds to Consumers Harmed by Aqua Finance’s Deceptive Sales Tactics</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-sends-more-198-million-refunds-consumers-harmed-aqua-finances-deceptive-sales-tactics</link>
  <description>&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-_3-width"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/ftc_scaled_extra_small_350_/public/u97525/explore_data_refunds_20.gif?itok=eligfPgF" width="350" height="219" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 350/219"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending more than $19.8 million in refunds to consumers who were harmed by deceptive sales tactics from household water treatment funding company Aqua Finance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC filed a lawsuit&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/05/ftc-action-leads-436-million-financial-relief-water-treatment-financing-company-aqua-finance"&gt;in May 2024&lt;/a&gt; against&amp;nbsp;Aqua Finance, charging that the company’s nationwide network of dealers, in door-to-door sales, deceived consumers about the financing terms for water filtering and softening products. According to the complaint, the false claims left consumers with hundreds to thousands of dollars in unexpected debt and large interest payments, while its financing terms impaired some consumers’ ability to sell or refinance their homes. The company agreed to a settlement with the FTC that requires the company to closely monitor its dealers and make clear disclosures to consumers. The settlement also required the company to provide $23.6 million in debt relief to consumers in addition to providing money for refunds.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is sending checks to 29,653 affected consumers. Recipients should cash their checks within 90 days, as indicated on the check. Consumers who have questions about their payment should contact the refund administrator, Epiq Systems, at 888-884-8509, or visit the FTC website to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/recent-ftc-cases-resulting-refunds/refund-programs-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;view frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt; about the refund process. The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to get a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt; provide a state-by-state breakdown of refunds in FTC cases. In 2024, FTC actions led to more than $285 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87508</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson Appoints Deputy Directors for the Bureau of Competition and Bureau of Consumer Protection</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/federal-trade-commission-chairman-andrew-n-ferguson-appoints-deputy-directors-bureau-competition-bureau-consumer-protection</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson has appointed David Shaw as Principal Deputy Director and Kelse Moen as Deputy Director of the agency’s Bureau of Competition and Douglas C. Geho as Deputy Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Shaw is an experienced antitrust lawyer with expertise in high-stakes litigation and contentious merger review. During the first Trump Administration, Shaw served in the Department of Justice’s Antitrust Division in a variety of roles, from the front lines as a trial attorney to the front office as acting chief of staff. As a trial attorney, he served on multiple trial teams, including the first litigated vertical merger challenge in forty years. While serving in DOJ’s front office, he held a leadership role in the Big Tech investigations and successfully coordinated a bipartisan coalition of state attorneys general joining the DOJ complaint in the Google search monopolization case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to his government service, Shaw&amp;nbsp;was a partner in the antitrust practice of a large international law firm. He received his J.D. from the Georgetown University Law Center and his B.A. from Patrick Henry College.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moen is an experienced antitrust attorney, with a career in both government service and private practice. Most recently, he served as senior counsel to the U.S. Senate Judiciary Committee for Senator Lindsey Graham, where he focused on antitrust, technology, and intellectual property issues, a position that he held until his appointment to the FTC.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Before joining the Judiciary Committee staff, Moen spent nearly a decade practicing antitrust law at major international law firms, representing businesses and individuals in high-stakes and high-profile government investigations, class actions, civil and criminal litigation, and merger reviews. He clerked for Judge Robert Mariani of the U.S. District Court for the Middle District of Pennsylvania. He is a graduate of Emory University and Cornell Law School.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Geho is a highly talented lawyer with extensive enforcement, regulatory, and litigation experience. During the first Trump Administration, Geho served at the Department of Labor as Counsel and Policy Advisor, and then Counselor to the Assistant Secretary for Policy, where he advanced efforts relating to regulatory and enforcement reform, worker safety and training, and additional Administration priorities. He then served as a lead attorney for the House Judiciary Committee and two of its subcommittees. He also managed investigations for the Senate Committee on Homeland Security and Governmental Affairs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most recently, Geho served as an Attorney Advisor to Commissioner Melissa Holyoak handling consumer protection matters for her office. He clerked for Judge Alice M. Batchelder on the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit. Prior to his government service, Geho was a litigator in private practice. Geho is a graduate of Georgetown University’s Law School and Grove City College.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>hbarber</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87495</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Finalizes Order with DoNotPay That Prohibits Deceptive 'AI Lawyer' Claims, Imposes Monetary Relief, and Requires Notice to Past Subscribers</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-finalizes-order-donotpay-prohibits-deceptive-ai-lawyer-claims-imposes-monetary-relief-requires</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission has &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/system/files/ftc_gov/pdf/2323042_donotpay_decision_and_order_0.pdf"&gt;finalized an order&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;requiring&amp;nbsp;DoNotPay, a company that promoted its online subscription service as “the world’s first robot lawyer,” to stop making deceptive claims about the abilities of its AI chatbot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a complaint&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/09/ftc-announces-crackdown-deceptive-ai-claims-schemes"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; in September 2024, the FTC charged that DoNotPay’s so-called robot lawyer failed to live up to claims that it was an adequate substitute for the expertise of a human lawyer. According to the complaint, the company did not test whether its “AI lawyer” operated to the level of a human lawyer when generating legal documents and giving advice, and the company did not hire or retain attorneys to test the quality and accuracy of its service’s law-related features.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final order requires DoNotPay to pay $193,000 in monetary relief and notify consumers who subscribed to the service between 2021 and 2023 about the FTC settlement. The order also prohibits DoNotPay from advertising that its service performs like a real lawyer unless it has sufficient evidence to back it up.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;After receiving five comments, the Commission voted 5-0 on January 16, 2025,&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;to approve the final order and send responses to the commenters.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87474</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Publishes Inflation-Adjusted Civil Penalty Amounts for 2025</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-publishes-inflation-adjusted-civil-penalty-amounts-2025</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission has adjusted the maximum civil penalty dollar amounts for violations of 16 provisions of law the FTC enforces, as required by the Federal Civil Penalties Inflation Adjustment Act Improvements Act of 2015. The Act directs agencies to implement annual inflation adjustments based on a prescribed formula.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The new maximum civil penalty amounts became effective once they were published in the Federal Register on January 17, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The maximum civil penalty amount has increased from $51,744 to $53,088 for violations of Sections 5(l), 5(m)(1)(A), and 5(m)(1)(B) of the FTC Act, Section 7A(g)(l) of the Clayton Act, and Section 525(b) of the Energy Policy and Conservation Act. It has increased from $680 to $698&amp;nbsp;for violations of Section 10 of the FTC Act.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The maximum civil penalty amount has increased from $1,472,546 to $1,510,803 for violations of Section 814(a) of the Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007. The maximum civil penalty amounts for other law violations within the agency’s jurisdiction&amp;nbsp;are listed in the Federal Register notice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote to publish the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2025/01/17/2025-01361/adjustments-to-civil-penalty-amounts"&gt;Federal Register notice&lt;/a&gt; amending Commission Rule 1.98 was 5-0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>mkatz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87476</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Postpones Workshop on Attention Economy: Monopolizing Kids’ Time Online</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-postpones-workshop-attention-economy-monopolizing-kids-time-online</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is postponing a February 25 virtual workshop examining the use of design features on digital platforms aimed at keeping kids, including teens, online longer and returning more frequently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When a new date is chosen, the FTC will post that information to the workshop’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/events/2025/02/attention-economy-monopolizing-kids-time-online"&gt;event webpage&lt;/a&gt; along with other updates.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>rkern</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87479</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Chairman Ferguson Appoints Christopher Mufarrige as Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-chairman-ferguson-appoints-christopher-mufarrige-director-bureau-consumer-protection</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;Federal Trade Commission Chairman Andrew N. Ferguson has appointed Christopher Mufarrige as Director of the agency’s Bureau of Consumer Protection.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;“I am delighted to appoint Chris Mufarrige as the next Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection. Chris is a stellar attorney and a tireless public servant,” Chairman Ferguson said. “The Bureau of Consumer Protection with Chris at the helm will work every day to protect the American consumer from fraud, and to safeguard children when they are online.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mufarrige is an experienced consumer protection lawyer who served in the first Trump Administration as a Senior Adviser to the Director and Deputy Director of the Consumer Financial Protection Bureau, advising on enforcement, rulemaking, and supervisory exams relating to the country’s largest banks and nonbank financial institutions. Most recently, he was Commissioner Melissa Holyoak’s Chief of Staff and Attorney Adviser. He has also worked at private law firms and as an in-house lawyer. In his free time, Mufarrige taught a class on financial services and consumer protection at George Mason University’s Antonin Scalia Law School.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mufarrige graduated from Scalia Law School, has a master’s degree in economics from George Mason University, and a B.S. in economics from Texas Christian University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission vote approving Mufarrige’s appointment as Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection was 4-0.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jhenderson2</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87468</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sends More Than $2.6 Million in Refunds to Small Businesses Harmed by Payment Processor First American Payment Systems</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/02/ftc-sends-more-26-million-refunds-small-businesses-harmed-payment-processor-first-american-payment</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending more than $2.6 million in refunds to small businesses harmed by payment processor First American Payment Systems.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC filed a lawsuit&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/07/ftc-takes-action-stop-payment-processor-first-american-trapping-small-businesses-surprise-exit-fees" data-entity-type="node" data-entity-uuid="349a6ab8-8a44-43b8-b7e8-bca9955f678e" data-entity-substitution="canonical"&gt;in July 2022&lt;/a&gt; against&amp;nbsp;First American, charging the company with trapping small businesses with hidden terms, surprise exit fees, and zombie charges. The FTC alleged the company made false claims about fees and cost savings to lure merchants. Once merchants were enrolled, the defendants withdrew funds from their accounts without their consent and made it difficult and expensive for them to cancel the service. The defendants settled the lawsuit with the FTC by paying money to refund small businesses. They also agreed to stop misleading businesses about their fees and make it easier for businesses to cancel their services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is sending checks to 5,588 small businesses. Recipients should cash their checks within 90 days, as indicated on the check.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The agency is also mailing claim forms to 16,181 businesses who&amp;nbsp;enrolled with First American Payment Systems&amp;nbsp;between June 2017 and April 2020 and later canceled their enrollment. Businesses who were charged an early termination fee may apply for a refund. The deadline to submit a claim is May 7, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;More information about this refund and claims process is available at&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/FirstAmerican"&gt;ftc.gov/FirstAmerican&lt;/a&gt; or by calling the refund administrator, JND Legal Administration, 877-595-0114. The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to get a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt; provide a state-by-state breakdown of refunds in FTC cases. In 2024, FTC actions led to $285 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87462</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sends Refunds to Consumers Affected by Fashion Nova’s Deceptive Review Practices</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-sends-refunds-consumers-affected-fashion-novas-deceptive-review-practices</link>
  <description>&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-_3-width"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/ftc_scaled_extra_small_350_/public/u97525/explore_data_refunds_20.gif?itok=eligfPgF" width="350" height="219" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 350/219"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending payments totaling nearly $2.4 million to consumers who bought products from fast fashion retailer Fashion Nova, which the FTC alleged blocked negative reviews of its products from being posted on its website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/01/fashion-nova-will-pay-42-million-part-settlement-ftc-allegations-it-blocked-negative-reviews"&gt;alleged in January 2022&lt;/a&gt; that Fashion Nova misrepresented that the product reviews on its website reflected the views of all customers who submitted reviews, when in fact it suppressed reviews with ratings lower than four stars out of five. It was the FTC’s first case involving efforts to conceal negative customer reviews.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fashion Nova &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/03/ftc-finalizes-order-fashion-nova-over-allegations-it-blocked-negative-reviews"&gt;agreed to a settlement order&lt;/a&gt; that prohibits the company from suppressing customer reviews of its products. Fashion Nova was also required to pay money to compensate affected consumers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is sending checks and PayPal payments to 148,351 Fashion Nova customers who filed a valid claim. Consumers selected their payment method when they completed their claim form. Recipients should cash their checks within 90 days, as indicated on the check, or redeem their PayPal payments within 30 days.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Consumers who have questions about their payment should contact the refund administrator, JND Legal Administration, at 855-678-0018 or visit the FTC’s website to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/recent-ftc-cases-resulting-refunds/refund-programs-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;view frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;about the refund process. The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to get a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;provide a state-by-state breakdown of refunds in FTC cases. In 2023,&amp;nbsp;FTC actions led to $330 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>hbarber</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87389</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>FTC Sends More Than $5 Million in Refunds to Consumers Harmed by Bogus Debt Relief Scheme</title>
  <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2025/01/ftc-sends-more-5-million-refunds-consumers-harmed-bogus-debt-relief-scheme</link>
  <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Trade Commission is sending more than $5 million in refunds to consumers harmed by a deceptive credit card debt relief scheme known as ACRO Services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC filed a lawsuit&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2022/11/ftc-halts-debt-relief-scheme-bilked-millions-consumers-while-leaving-many-deeper-debt"&gt;in November 2022&lt;/a&gt; against&amp;nbsp;ACRO Services, which operated under multiple names such as American Consumer Rights Organization, Consumer Protection Resources, Reliance Solutions, Thacker &amp;amp; Associates, and Tri Star Consumer Group. The complaint charged the company and its owners with running a deceptive telemarketing operation that made numerous phony debt relief promises to consumers, including that they could greatly reduce or eliminate consumers’ credit card debt in 12 to 18 months. They charged consumers thousands of dollars in unlawful upfront enrollment fees and told them it was part of the debt that will be eliminated as part of the program. Consumers were also charged monthly fees ranging from $20-$35 for “credit monitoring” services.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The individual defendants agreed to a settlement order that permanently bans them from the debt relief and telemarketing industries and required them to surrender assets to be used to refund consumers. The funds in this distribution also came from the FTC’s case against &lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/05/ftc-takes-action-against-bluesnap-its-former-ceo-senior-vp-credit-card-laundering-processing"&gt;payment processor BlueSnap&lt;/a&gt;, which provided services to, and profited from, the ACRO Services scheme.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The FTC is sending checks to 7,687 consumers. Recipients should cash their checks within 90 days, as indicated on the check. Consumers who have questions about their payment should contact the refund administrator, JND Legal Administration, at 877-753-2846, or visit the FTC website to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://www.ftc.gov/enforcement/recent-ftc-cases-resulting-refunds/refund-programs-frequently-asked-questions"&gt;view frequently asked questions&lt;/a&gt; about the refund process. The Commission never requires people to pay money or provide account information to get a refund.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div data-entity-type="block_content" data-entity-uuid="0fa652c4-baf3-48fe-9f0d-8fb3fa7044d2" data-embed-button="basic_block" data-entity-embed-display="view_mode:block_content.full" class="align-right embedded-entity" data-langcode="en" data-entity-embed-display-settings="[]"&gt;
&lt;div class="block-content block-content--type-basic block-content--840 block-content--view-mode-full"&gt;
  
  
  &lt;div class="block-content__content"&gt;
    

&lt;div class="field field--name-field-body field--type-text-long field--label-hidden"&gt;
    &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;
&lt;article class="align-right media media--type-image media--view-mode-sm"&gt;
  
      &lt;div class="media__content"&gt;
      
  &lt;div class="field field--name-field-media-image field--type-image field--label-visually_hidden"&gt;
          &lt;div class="field__label usa-sr-only"&gt;Image&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class="field__items"&gt;
              &lt;div class="field__item"&gt;  &lt;img src="https://www.ftc.gov/sites/default/files/styles/scaled_sm/public/ftc_gov/images/badge-explore-data-ftc-refunds-resized.jpg?itok=Yc2wmn7d" width="390" height="244" alt="Explore Data Badge Resized" loading="lazy" typeof="foaf:Image" style="aspect-ratio: 390/244"&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
          &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/article&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Commission’s&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://public.tableau.com/app/profile/federal.trade.commission/viz/Refunds_15797958402020/RefundsbyCase"&gt;interactive dashboards for refund data&lt;/a&gt; provide a state-by-state breakdown of refunds in FTC cases. In 2023,&amp;nbsp;FTC actions led to $330 million in refunds to consumers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 07:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>jmayfield</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">87312</guid>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
